<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>61</commentCount>
    <id>3erhhr</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3erhhr/cmvthose_positively_identified_and_convicted_of/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Glory2Hypnotoad</author>
        <ReplyBody>Are you familiar with the saying "in for a penny, in for a pound?" It's a commentary on how overly severe punishments create perverse incentives. If a person knows they'll face the death penalty for robbery, what reason do they have not to commit murder or whatever other crimes might prevent them from getting caught?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthoe6t</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>I understand what you're saying, but to me this does not justify reducing the ramifications of serious crimes just in the hopes that the criminal doesn't do something worse to get out of it. If that's the case, why not reduce the penalty for all major crimes in the hopes that the criminals just turn themselves in?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthpczl</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Glory2Hypnotoad</author>
                <ReplyBody>Speaking from an American perspective, we already offer incentives for criminals to turn themselves in, which sometimes include reduced sentences. Even the harshest prisons offer privileges dependent on good behavior because they recognize that criminals require some basic level of incentive for compliance. The danger of a broad a mandatory death penalty is that it gives criminals no incentive to comply. On the other hand, a prisoner who can bargain their way down to jail time has every reason in the world to cooperate. On top of that, to best prevent murder, we need levels of punishment that are unique to murder without being cruel and unusual. Being tough on crime is not the same as being effective against crime, and incentives for compliance have a long track record of getting results.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthqfci</id>
                <upvotes>13</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>cacheflow</author>
                <ReplyBody>We don't even have the death penalty for most murder cases.

Why should threatening to murder someone have a harsher penalty than actually murdering them?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthqgh3</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>ryan_m</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I assume OP would also be in favor of the death penalty for other serious crimes as well.

In my opinion, the death penalty shouldn't exist at all, in any capacity.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cthqlxl</id>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>4</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>22</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>hey_aaapple</author>
        <ReplyBody>Now those people have no reason not to go on a killing spree when the police comes for them, because they are going to die anyways.

Also, the criminals would now be better off leaving no witnesses.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ctho57f</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Snedeker</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think that you'd find this a lot less of an issue if the penalty for those crimes was death. Anyone going on a killing spree or "leaving no witnesses" under those circumstances was probably going to do it anyway. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ctho9pa</id>
            <replies>
                <author>hey_aaapple</author>
                <ReplyBody>I don't think you get the point.

If the penality for armed robbery is already death, any criminal who does armed robbery has nothing to lose by committing more crimes. If those crimes might allow them to get away, they actually have an incentive to do more crime.

Example: if you want to rob a house, why tie up the person living in it? Just kill them, if they catch you you'll die anyways and it will be a tad harder to find you if there is no witness.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthofqn</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Snedeker</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;any criminal who does armed robbery has nothing to lose by committing more crimes.

I don't think that *you* get the point. If the penalty for armed robbery is death, there will be far fewer armed robbers. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cthp3fb</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>TalkingHawk</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Are there less murders in the US states that still have the death penalty?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cthpw03</id>
                        <upvotes>9</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Daedalus1907</author>
                        <ReplyBody>There's no evidence that the death penalty deters criminals.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cti13h6</id>
                        <upvotes>8</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>hey_aaapple</author>
                        <ReplyBody>If your line of reasoning was correct, you should be able to show me studies indicating that abolishing death penality causes significant crime increase for the crimes that were affected.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cthpn6x</id>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>First, who do you think commits most home invasions? 

Second, do you think a bunch of methheads who want to steal your VCR will really be influenced to not rob a house because of threat of the death penalty? 

Third, since when has the death penalty ever deterred crime? Do states that have a death penalty report fewer murders than those that don't? Did the murder rate skyrocket when the Supreme Court put a stay on the death penalty?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cthv5qa</id>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Bratmon</author>
                        <ReplyBody>People in favor of the death penalty can say things like that all they want, but that doesn't make it true.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ctigtk2</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>9</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>I understand what you're trying to say, but if they do that, it just reaffirms the fact they don't have any place in society and should be removed. That doesn't change the fact that they have something fundamentally wrong with them that disqualifies them from participating in a modern society.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthoa2h</id>
            <replies>
                <author>hey_aaapple</author>
                <ReplyBody>You are making a circular reasoning: "we are going to kill those people, if they fight back that's proof they needed to die".

You could use the same exact line of thought to ask for death penality for lollygagging or any other dumb reason.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthoi2d</id>
                <upvotes>10</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Glory2Hypnotoad</author>
                <ReplyBody>All the same, we as a society have a choice in whether we want every instance of robbery to end in a shootout with the police. Every part of our justice system that works acknowledges that even criminals require some basic level of incentive for compliance.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthomiw</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>16</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BadKeyMachine</author>
        <ReplyBody>1.  If the state puts people to death, it puts innocent people to death.  Period.  Some percentage of the men you put on death row will be falsely accused.  Your 'positively identified' clause is assumed in a court that asks the jury to only convict men who are guilty "with no reasonable doubt."  You will put innocent men to death.  In my view, putting a free, innocent man to death is something that a democratic, secular society cannot do and still call itself free, but that is a value judgement.

2.  Any kind of sentencing, at some point, comes down to the question of redeemability.  If an idiot kid holds up a convenience store at 17, is it then impossible that anything good could ever come from his life?  To say "no" is a strong, bold position, especially considering we have many men, in or outside of prison, that have sworn off violence after committing heinous crimes in their youth, and turned their energy toward religion, social justice, whatever else.  Also, you would definitely to have a citation for the idea that people who have committed armed robbery necessarily have a "fundamental defect in their brain chemistry."

3.  The level of incarceration in America, at least(not sure where you are), is already unprecedented.  America has 5% of the world's population, but 25% of the world's prisoners.  We have 700% more people incarcerated now than in 1970.  Yet, we still have far greater gun violence than Europe.  There is no indication that being "hard on crime" works as a deterrent.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthofhw</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>I understand your point about the death penalty, for this CMV, lets assume though that the criminal is 100% identified beyond any reasonable doubt, I agree that it is not an acceptable punishment for a juvenile, I should have clarified.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthows6</id>
            <replies>
                <author>BadKeyMachine</author>
                <ReplyBody>I don't understand why that is a meaningful debate, though.  We would be debating an imaginary, impossible scenario.  If this is something you *really* think should be implemented in the *real* world, I don't think you get to make that distinction.

Anyway, let's say the kid is 18, then.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthoytl</id>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;for this CMV, lets assume though that the criminal is 100% identified beyond any reasonable doubt,

Since we're living in fantasy land, why don't we just commit these people to azkaban instead? 

The thing that makes the death penalty so barbaric is that any system of man will get things wrong. 

Why are you so willing to give the government so much power over life and death? I mean, that is an awesome power over meth-heads who want to get their next score by robbing a house. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthvfm9</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>HauntedFrog</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Your point about trusting the government with life and death is a critical one. Government systems fail all the time, so I don't understand why people are so ready to believe that one specific system is infallible.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cti3472</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>jt4</author>
        <ReplyBody>* It would be inhumane to put a person to death because of an issue with their brain chemistry. Many people with schizophrenia who commit crimes of all kinds are sent to institutions where their mental health can be properly dealt with.
* You've assumed the purpose of the gun or knife is to cause bodily harm. Not everybody who brandishes a gun in a robbery is ready to fire it and kill or injure the person. Some people are using the gun merely for intimidation purposes - it's a *threat* of harm. And if it were up to them, they wouldn't need to use it. I have heard stories of people who get what they wanted from a robbery and then shoot their victims anyway.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthoggu</id>
        <replies>
            <author>HauntedFrog</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is a very important point. One thing we were taught in martial arts is that if someone is brandishing a knife at you, chances are they *don't actually want to use it*. That's why they're making sure you see it, because that way they won't have to. If they're hiding the knife or keeping it out of your view, then *that's* when you need to run like hell because they mean to hurt you. The thing is, that second scenario is way less common.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cti38ge</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>(reposting this response from above)
I understand that most robbers would like to get out of the situation without killing, but if they go into the situation with a LOADED firearm or a knife, then in my mind, they are prepared to kill if they situation escalates to that point.
I'm not saying everyone has to add value to society like Hitler's master race dream or something, if you're in a wheelchair or have spina bifida, that sucks, but you can still contribute art, research, great works in science.
I really meant if you clearly DETRACT from society by having the urges and acting up those urges to commit violent crime with loaded and dangerous weapons. Even if your grandma is dying of cancer, that's not an acceptable excuse for me.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthougp</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Lobrian011235</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I really meant if you clearly DETRACT from society by having the urges and acting up those urges to commit violent crime with loaded and dangerous weapons.

People who commit armed robberies aren't usually acting on an *urge*, they are usually acting on desperation.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ctidulh</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Jaica_</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;You're brandishing a weapon, ready to kill a person you do not even know, for short term profit.

I think the weapon is mostly used for intimidation and not all robbers are willing to kill for their profit of the robbery. 
Because of this not all robbers 'have a fundemental defect in their brain' but some can have a place in society (even though they might need help).
Therefore I'm convinced we can not use the death penalty for robbery. The collateral damage of the rule kills people who still have value for society. 

(Just to avoid side-tracking discussions: I do not think someone must have value for society to be kept alive and I'm opposed to the death penalty, but that is not what this CMV is about.)</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthohvc</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>I understand that most robbers would like to get out of the situation without killing, but if they go into the situation with a LOADED firearm or a knife, then in my mind, they are prepared to kill if they situation escalates to that point.
I'm not saying everyone has to add value to society like Hitler's master race dream or something, if you're in a wheelchair or have spina bifida, that sucks, but you can still contribute art, research, great works in science.
I really meant if you clearly DETRACT from society by having the urges and acting up those urges to commit violent crime with loaded and dangerous weapons. Even if your grandma is dying of cancer, that's not an acceptable excuse for me.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthoqzo</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Jaica_</author>
                <ReplyBody>I do not think all robbers will kill in an escalated situation. Inherently good people who are desperate do very stupid things. Robbing has a minor effect on the victim compared to taking their lives. Their desperation might drive them to commit a robbery, but their goodness can stop them from taking a life. There is a huge leap between those two things.

I believe there are too much people in this category to justify the death penalty for robbery.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthp12p</id>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;or a knife, then in my mind, they are prepared to kill if they situation escalates to that point.

Based on what are you making the assertion that people who are willing to use deadly threats are willing to go that extra step and actually use deadly violence? 

That seems like a massive logical leap and I am curious how you arrived at that conclusion. 

Because I think this is where your logic fails. 

Like, suppose you're a meth-head and want to rob a house to get money for your next score. You keep a Swiss Army knife in your pocket to clean your nails and in your high, you forget that it's there. The state will kill you under what you're proposing. 

Or... The only reason you bring your knife is to pry open a window, like a tool. 

Or, the only ready you bring your knife is to wave it around in case you're caught so you can run away. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthvoot</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>ThanksButIDontCare</author>
                <ReplyBody>What if they intend to fire the weapon at something other than a person as an act of intimidation. Simply carrying a loaded weapon isn't enough to infer intent. If you could prove that in this contrived case their intent was never to fire upon a person would you still want to punish them with death?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cti0ujw</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>mehatch</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;have a fundamental defect in their human brain chemistry

If medical science developed a way to fix their brain, would you continue to hold that they should be put to death?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthqlt2</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>Well, that opens up another can of worms, I suppose not, provided they didn't kill or hurt anyone. I suppose you could apply that argument to literally every crime though.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthqpn0</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Aclopolipse</author>
                <ReplyBody>And that's exactly what the rehabilitative model of criminal justice is about.  It's the crazy idea that treating criminals like human beings can help them to not be criminals anymore, *and it works*.

The United States uses a punitive model of criminal justice, and is one of the only Western nations to still have a death penalty in any capacity.  The United States has [more prisoners per person than any country in the world,](https://www.salve.edu/sites/default/files/filesfield/documents/Incarceration_and_Recidivism.pdf) and, more importantly, [a repeat offender rate of 51.8 out of 100, **at the very lowest**.](http://www.bjs.gov/content/reentry/recidivism.cfm)  These figures knock all EU countries out of the park, but special mention goes to [Sweden,](http://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/dec/01/why-sweden-closing-prisons) and sub-5000 prison population and its recidivism rate of 30%.  Their prison system is focused on humanity and rehabilitation above all else, with both in-prison and post-prison counseling and psychiatric services available for all manner of offenders.

So what does this have to do with the OP?  It goes to show that treating violent offenders as irreparably damaged time bombs *does not and will not work*, and you don't need a miracle pill that absolves any and all violent tendencies to rehabilitate a violent criminal to be less violent, especially when it was a crime of desperation, as armed robbery often is.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthtcne</id>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>mehatch</author>
                <ReplyBody>In that case, is the person *culpable* for having that brain?

</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthslzd</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>saintbenny</author>
        <ReplyBody>There is a great danger in categorizing all robbers or thieves as 'disturbed people prepared to kill just to get money'. 

One always has to look at every possible aspect of WHY these people are doing what they are doing. 

Sure, there's plenty of bad people out there who simply want to fill their chest with gold and live happily ever after through a simple act of greed.

But what about those who are doing it for moral reasons? A family of 5 in which the income is so low they can barely survive. The grieving father may take extreme measures just to he can feed his children - so he goes off to buy a simple BB gun and uses it to rob convenience stores.

Or a son who is witnessing his mother dying from terminal illness because there isn't enough money to pay for crucial surgeries. He, too, might convince his friends to go with him on a robbing spree so that he can save his mother's life. His reasoning could be 1) He doesn't want to lose his mother forever. 2) If she dies, he will spend the rest of his life thinking "was there something I could have done to save her?"

^These two examples can make people do crazy things to save the people they love. 

Putting them up on trial and concluding they are disturbed folks who don't contribute to society and are willing to murder others for a petty buck - is a little over the top? Especially if the sentence for these people is as extreme as taking their life in the name of the law. 

Sure, they may not contribute to society with their acts. But they contribute to the value of human ethics and morals - which I believe is worth far more than any law out there. 

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthoerd</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Miguelinileugim</author>
            <ReplyBody>/u/PorscheWTE

This guy with the comment above me does have a point goddammit.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ctitn4q</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>AnecdotallyExtant</author>
        <ReplyBody>Would your view change if they were using an unloaded gun?  
   
And why?  
It would have the same psychological effect on the victim, but there could be no intent to actually kill.   
     
Would this finality apply to juvenile cases?  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthoglj</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>Yes, because you clearly had no intention and no means to cause lethal bodily harm to another person. It would need to be a loaded gun or a knife.
In my mind, this would not apply to juvenile cases, although in the case of home invasion with a lethal loaded weapon, I'm on the fence.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthotlj</id>
            <replies>
                <author>AnecdotallyExtant</author>
                <ReplyBody>Ok, what about the starving man who needs to feed to his family?  
   
The man who can be seen in the video to be clearly remorseful even during the robbery, and who could have had no other choice?   
  
What about [this man?](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ih5Q2RCnuHE)   
Can you believe he should be executed for this act?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cthowkw</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>PorscheWTE</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No, there is always another choice, whether it is apparent or not. If he is robbing with a loaded weapon, he should be put to death. If he steals items or money and runs without interacting with a person, he deserves jail time, but not the death penalty.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cthp18e</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>AnecdotallyExtant</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Maybe you can help me understand why you feel this specific crime warrants the death penalty.      

Why not attempted murder?   
There is intent to murder there.  
   
    
Why not 3rd DUI offense?  
There is a pattern of endangering without care there.    
    
Why not poaching?   
This is literally both robbing the state of resources at gun-point and unjustly taking a life. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cthp4nx</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Attempted murder I could agree with the death penalty if it was premeditated and not aggravated. Armed robbery is premeditated.
DUI, while terrible and they should lose their license for a number of years, is not the same as holding a loaded gun or knife in someones face and taking from them.
Poaching, while terrible, is an animal, not a human life, which is far less important (but i'm not against game reserves killing poachers that shoot at the gamewardens). But if a poacher surrendered peacefully, I don't think he should be executed gangland style or anything, jail time for sure.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cthpiwe</id>
                            <replies>
<author>AnecdotallyExtant</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; DUI, while terrible and they should lose their license for a number of years, is not the same as holding a loaded gun or knife in someones face and taking from them. 

It is not the same as holding a loaded gun, no. But it is the same as operating a loose bullet. A 3rd offense is a clear indication that nothing will stop the person from repeating the behavior until another person is dead. Or a family.   
Or anything else that happened to be unfortunate enough to be born without the predictive power to know that our drunken driver would decide he really needed a new 12 pack that night.    
This is the equivalent of your armed robber just firing rounds randomly. For three consecutive robberies.    
    
&amp;gt;Poaching, while terrible, is an animal, not a human life, which is far less important (but i'm not against game reserves killing poachers that shoot at the gamewardens).    
   
Are you aware that he world has decided that poachers don't even get a trial anymore?    
We've also hired people to hunt the poachers. Kill on sight.    
    
&amp;gt;Attempted murder I could agree with the death penalty if it was premeditated and not aggravated.    
   
This is a literal attempt to end a person. Premeditated or not.   
   
&amp;gt; Armed robbery is premeditated.   
   
This is a literal property crime.     
      
_______________    
    
Are you honestly of the opinion that an attempt to end a life; a third attempt to end as many as possible; and a crime for which the world has decided to shoot on sight -- can you honestly say that a property crime is more egregious than these?  </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cthpvne</id>
<replies>
    <author>PorscheWTE</author>
    <ReplyBody>I'm more concerned with the motivations and the goals of each crime and what it means for the person. When a person gets into a vehicle drunk, they aren't thinking about killing or maiming someone, they are concerned about getting to a destination. 

While they are a terrible person and should be locked away, they aren't maliciously and with forethought taking from someone with a loaded weapon with the preparedness to kill.

I don't feel bad for poachers, they know the stakes, and if they are willing to do it anyway, those are the consequences. While I admit don't think killing an animal directly deserves the death penalty, even if its an extremely endangered species.

Premeditated murder is heinous, you have time to think about the ramifications to everyone involved, and decide to do it anyway. Aggravated murder as in you are provoked and a guy starts fighting you and you end up throwing him down and he hits his head on a stone and dies, you meant to hurt him, but not kill him, (maybe im thinking on manslaughter, on second thought.) Or perhaps the crime of passion example where you walk in on your wife having sex with the neighbor and you kill them both. While terrible and you should be locked up, I don't think you should be killed for that.

If you are committing premeditated armed robbery or home invasion with a loaded deadly weapon and have a history of violent crime. You are prepared to kill someone for petty gain and your value of human life is therefore very small. You deserve to be killed in my mind.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cthq84c</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>kolobian</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The reason I added the 'positively identified' caveat is that I don't want to leave any room for putting an innocent person to death, so for this case to kick in, I would need either CCTV confirming their identity, or multiple eye witnesses confirming their identity.

You realize this still leaves the chance of error, right? Every wrongfully convicted inmate who was sentenced to die had a trial where the jury had instructions to only give a guilty verdict if they were convinced beyond a reasonable doubt that prosecution proved their case and that the defendant was guilty.

Secondly, there's a BIG difference between armed robbery and home invasion. Home invasion is much, much, much worse. Neither should give the death penalty unless they actually hurt someone. If we gave the death penalty to anyone caught doing one of these horrible crimes, regardless whether they actually killed someone, then they would have no reason NOT to kill the victims. If they'd face the death penalty no matter what, they'd probably then ALWAYS kill the clerks and family members to avoid being identified, so it would actually make life much worse for everyone else.

Lastly, I disagree with this statement:

&amp;gt;I believe that if someone is willing to forcefully take from another innocent person with the threatening use of a knife, gun, or other easily lethal weapon, they have no place in society and have a fundamental defect in their human brain chemistry (without even touching on the trauma and psychological damage the victims must suffer). To me, this type of crime shows an extreme amount of depravity. 

So I'm friends with someone who cleaned up his life. When he was a teenager, he fell into substance abuse, starting with alcohol and then working his way up to harder drugs. I know that at least at one point, he robbed a convenience store with a loaded gun, maybe more. He was in and out of jail and rehab until he decided one day to clean his act up. He became sober, found a good job, found new friends and hobbies, stayed away from anything alcohol or drugs, and went back to school. A decade later, now he's happily married, has a kid, a house, and is just finishing up his doctoral degree. Right now he's teaching classes at the university.  If you were one of his students, you'd have no idea that he had a criminal past years ago, and all you'd see now is a happy guy with a good life who enjoys giving back to the community. 

What good would it have done society to kill him? There's plenty of people like this who at one point had gone down the wrong road (likely from the influence of drugs) and then eventually sobered up and came back to a be a productive member of society. There's probably someone you know who has a past that they overcame.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthukn5</id>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>CireArodum</author>
        <ReplyBody>While crime is a shitty thing to do not all crimes are equally heinous. Not everyone who brandishes a knife will use it. Not every gun is loaded. Most of the time these people aren't looking to kill someone. They just want to scare them to get the goods and get out. Should scaring someone while robbing them be a capital offense? Or do they need to be willing to kill. How do you figure out which ones are willing to kill and which are just trying to steal and avoid a fight?

Also, not all robberies are done for the same reason. What if someone told you if you don't go get some money they were going to kill you? What if that person telling you that was hunger, or addiction, or putting a roof over your kids' heads?

Now, robbery is and always should be a crime. And maybe the most hardened brutal robbers are not worth trying to rehabilitate. But it's way too heavy handed to suggest all robbers need to be put to death. Remember that poverty creates crime and no one is in poor on purpose.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthoju8</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>thatmorrowguy</author>
        <ReplyBody>I don't know about you, but I've done a few things while drunk that I probably would never do sober.  I've not partaken of drugs, but from what I have heard and read, they can alter your perception of reality much more than even alcohol.  When someone is very drunk / high / stoned, their perception of reality and their level of inhibitions can be very different than it is while sober.  In that case, while of course they deserve to pay a penalty for the crime they have committed, they may be entirely rehabilitated by simply going through detox and staying off of mind altering substances.

Punishment for a crime comes down to rehabilitation, deterrence, retribution, removal, retaliation.  Capital punishment removes any chance of rehabilitation.  No level of punishment would deter a crime of passion, crime of desperation, unthinking crimes or crimes of opportunity.  It only has a very small chance of deterring one particular class of criminal - who is in control of their faculties, their morals, and can make a rational cost/benefit analysis of whether committing this crime is worth the risk of punishment.  

As for retribution, you're advocating for something even more harsh than "eye for an eye".  The crime was that they put another person at risk while depriving them of property.  While yes, there was a risk of harm, they did not actually harm in any way that is irreparable.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthoplj</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is a really good post, you've swayed me somewhat. I do feel like it's possible to make a terrible mistake if something traumatic has happened to you, like your spouse cheated on you, or your child passed away.
I'm willing to concede that if a perpetrator has no prior violent criminal history and commits an armed robbery under duress or some kind of extenuating circumstance, perhaps the death penalty is not fair. I'd be willing to just put them in jail for an appropriate amount of time, but if they committed another armed robbery with a loaded weapon, they would deserve death penalty. Partial Delta?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthp9we</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>antiproton</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; have a fundamental defect in their human brain chemistry

You start off bad. Many theft-related crimes are a result of poverty. Very few of them are because the person is legitimately unbalanced. 

Now, I'm not saying that people who rob a liquor store are Jean Valjean, but they aren't Patrick Bateman either. 

Criminal justice is, ostensibly, about punishment, deterrence and, ideally, rehabilitation. It is not supposed to be about vengeance. A person who robs a store at gun point is going to jail for the crime they committed. They are not, however, necessarily irredeemable. 

You would assume from the start that, regardless of circumstances, someone who pulls a gun on another person must *ipso facto* be capable of murder and should therefore be put to death, because that person is a timebomb waiting to go off. 

Not only are you doling out a massively asymmetrical punishment, you are opening a can of worms that could easily slide into assigning death penalties to a whole slew of crimes based entirely on your subjective opinion of "depravity". 

Hypothetical: Person A robs a store at gun point. The clerk is scared shitless, as is the intention, and hands over the money in the register. The thief flees, but, thanks to surveilance, is caught and sentenced to death. The clerk is not injured and the store is reimbursed for the loss by insurance. 

Person B is a homophobe and sees a gay couple on the street. He beats the gay couple so badly, they are hospitalized. The couple survive, Person B is caught, charged and convicted of aggravated assault and sent to prison for 10 years. 

Are you prepared to sentence person B to death as well? It seems pretty clear that person B is a more direct threat to the actual members of society than person A. 

If so, where do you draw the line? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cthp132</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>If person A and B have a history of at least one violent crime, and person A's gun is LOADED, I think he should be put to death. He is prepared to shoot the store clerk if he fought back or someone else fought back.
Person B, if having a history of at least one other violent crime, should be put to death. If really the only connection to the victim is the thought that he might be gay, he really should be killed regardless if he beats him to within an inch of his life without being provoked whatsoever.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cthpoyh</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>HauntedFrog</author>
        <ReplyBody>First and foremost, the death penalty is wrong because it's intrinsically irreversible. If new evidence comes up, too late, the accused is dead. If they're in prison, the damage done to them can be mitigated by releasing them.

Secondly, the death penalty is (usually) overkill. If your goal is to prevent someone from hurting more people, locking them up will have the same effect. It may not give the same sense of satisfaction to the general population because the criminal didn't get what they deserved, but that's my point: what someone deserves is subjective and based on revenge-driven thinking, whereas prevention and rehabilitation are not.

Thirdly, why do people commit violent crimes? If you look at the socioeconomic status of most criminals, they're poor. They commit crimes out of desperation. Punishment isn't a deterrent if you already feel that you *have* to do something to survive. Alternatively, you're crazy. If you're on drugs, we can put you in a place where you won't be on drugs and thus you no longer will hurt people (preventing future crimes). Or, if you have a mental disorder, we can get you help for that too. These methods allow people to get out of their criminal circumstances without drastically killing them. You can look at the rates of relapse for prisoners who gain an education while in prison vs. those who don't. People with access to education/jobs/skills that lift them out of desperate circumstances don't usually fall back into crime.

Do some people deserve death? Sure. But laws shouldn't be about subjectively *punishing* wrongdoers, they should be about *fixing the problem*. If you go the punishment route, you end up in the Middle Ages again just being generally horrible.

Edit: I haven't addressed the reparation aspect of justice, but that's important too.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cti2dp9</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ccasella3</author>
        <ReplyBody>1. There's not a correlation between crime rates dropping in areas where the severity of punishment is harsher. For example, in Texas, the death penalty is present, but it doesn't stop people from murdering other people. Another example: in the top 20 states with murders per 100,000 people, or rather, in the top 20 worst states for murder rates, only 5 do not have the death penalty. In the top 20 states with the LOWEST murder rates, 12/20 do NOT have the death penalty. It can be argued that punishment is not a detractor of criminal behavior. [Source](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/murder-rates-nationally-and-state#MRord)

2. As a personal anecdote, my apartment was broken into when I was just a year out of college. My girlfriend at the time came home to find the house had been broken into and apparently the people had just left. She went upstairs and found a knife from our kitchen, upstairs in our bedroom. So the robber had broken in, taken the knife from our kitchen and brought it upstairs with him in case he met anyone up there, I guess. But who is to say his intent? Was it scary as shit? YES. Did it make me feel very unsafe in my home? YES. But I also know that some robbers carry weapons solely for personal protection and not to actively harm people. Some robbers take them and use them to scare or intimidate people. Who is to say that it was ever their intention to use it on someone? Seems a pretty stiff penalty to give someone the death penalty when you could never truly know their intentions or if they would have gone through with it.

Edits made for spelling, punctuation and just generally awful flow of the paragraphs. Hopefully most have been caught and ~~killed~~ I mean, uh... fixed.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cti58vh</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>CarrotMcGee</author>
        <ReplyBody>It doesn't seem like the moral arguments are changing your mind, so I'll try taking a different approach. The death penalty for armed robberies would be insanely, unrealistically expensive.  Death penalty cases cost way more than even life in prison, because we want to be really really sure we're right before we execute someone.

Last year, according to the FBI, there were about 345,454 armed robberies in the US.  The actual costs of a death penalty case vary, but somewhere around $1,000,000 seems like a pretty common estimate.  So, in a year, we're looking at about $345,454,000,000.  Is that really worth it?  Are the benefits (reduced crime rate, comfort to the victims...) really worth the 300 BILLION dollar price tag?  Who's paying for that?  Is that really the best use of the money?

Morality aside (and for the record, I'm very morally against it), death penalty for armed robbery would just be too expensive.



https://www.fbi.gov/about-us/cjis/ucr/crime-in-the-u.s/2013/crime-in-the-u.s.-2013/violent-crime/violent-crime-topic-page/violentcrimemain_final

http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/costs-death-penalty</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ctiarao</id>
        <replies>
            <author>PorscheWTE</author>
            <ReplyBody>∆
Thanks, I didn't realize deathrow cases were so incredibly expensive and drawn out. While I think there should be a 3 strike rule or something for violent crimes of this nature, maybe putting them to death isn't the answer. Thank you.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ctj6py7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>DeltaBot</author>
                <ReplyBody>Confirmed: 1 delta awarded to /u/CarrotMcGee. ^[[History](/r/changemyview/wiki/user/CarrotMcGee)]

^[[Wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/deltabot)][[Code](https://github.com/alexames/DeltaBot)][/r/DeltaBot]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ctj6wn9</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>lij2015</author>
        <ReplyBody>That would cost so much damn money to have all those appeal cases (which is automatically required of every death penalty case in the US) as that's a decently common crime. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ctieqzr</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>PoppyOncrack</author>
        <ReplyBody>As someone who is completely against the death penalty, i could not disagree with you more, if any people ''have'' to be put to death, they should be the absolute worst of the worst, Serial killers, Child Murderers, Terrorists. people like that, certainly not People who commit robbery, even if it is with a weapon.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ctkap6c</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>Hey CMV, I'll keep this one simple. I believe that if someone is willing to forcefully take from another innocent person with the threatening use of a knife, gun, or other easily lethal weapon, they have no place in society and have a fundamental defect in their human brain chemistry (without even touching on the trauma and psychological damage the victims must suffer).
To me, this type of crime shows an extreme amount of depravity. You're brandishing a weapon, ready to kill a person you do not even know, for short term profit. This especially applies to home invasions and store robberies.
The reason I added the 'positively identified' caveat is that I don't want to leave any room for putting an innocent person to death, so for this case to kick in, I would need either CCTV confirming their identity, or multiple eye witnesses confirming their identity. 
I'm willing to admit this view may be on the extreme side, but I like to think I'm a reasonable person and I'm open to change. So reddit, please CMV.

**EDIT: I should have clarified, please assume LOADED weapons or a knife, and the offender is NOT a juvenile. To me, these are different cases and do not deserve the death penalty.**

_____

&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
