<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>94</commentCount>
    <id>3gwou8</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3gwou8/cmv_sexual_predators_who_prey_upon_minors_should/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>EmpRupus</author>
        <ReplyBody>If the punishment for sexual assault equals the punishment for murder, there is no incentive for the perpetuator to leave their victims alive after the act.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu25o76</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu28065</id>
            <replies>
                <author>MadTwit</author>
                <ReplyBody>And the punishment for theft should be to have a hand cut off yes?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu28g1y</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>lamasnot</author>
                    <ReplyBody>There is a bit of differance in stealing a loaf of bread and ruining a child's life.  </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu2bm6v</id>
                    <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu298di</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>keegan112099</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Imagine how much worse it is your falsely convicted of rape or theft.  </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu29kxq</id>
                        <upvotes>14</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>smurgleburf</author>
                        <ReplyBody>that didn't seem to stop thieves when it was actually in place. if the death penalty isn't an effective deterrent, what makes you think that cruel punishment is? civilized societies rehabilitate their criminals, extreme punishment isn't a viable way of doing that.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu29kdk</id>
                        <upvotes>9</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>BreaksFull</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Think of how many potentially useful members of society would be crippled and made significantly less useful for one minor crime. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu2b8du</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu2bc5y</id>
                            <replies>
<author>BreaksFull</author>
<ReplyBody>Theft has remained overwhelmingly common for thousands of years, despite a history of draconian punishment, which speaks volumes as to how effective it is. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu2bhfz</id>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Bashi_Hart</author>
                        <ReplyBody>So a starving person steals a loaf of bread, and gets there hand cut off... maybe they can eat that</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu2ciup</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>11</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Bashi_Hart</author>
                <ReplyBody>The government can't do that because they would be denying that person the right to have children... but the bigger issue with that is that castrating them isnt going to stop them from having pedophilia, which is a mental issue, not effected by sex organs. They could still victimize people</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2chfe</id>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>77</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Ansuz07</author>
        <ReplyBody>I have two counterpoints:

1)  Your solution does not allow for any leeway based on the nature of the case.  In your system, an 18 year old boy who had sex with his 16 year old girlfriend now spends the rest of his life in prison.

2)  Why stop at just child molestation?  Recidivism rates for criminals are very high; you are statistically much more likely to commit a crime again if you have already committed it once.  

You acknowledge in your argument that the potential for rehabilitation shouldn't matter in the interest of public welfare, so extending that logic means that **no** criminal should be trusted to rehabilitate.  After all, every crime has a negative social impact and many crimes produce long term damage for victims, therefore we should protect the potential victims of **all** future crimes from people who have shown a propensity to commit those crimes.

Its not a large stretch to use your logic to put anyone who commits  any violation punishable by jail time in prison for life if we are to discount the possibility of rehabilitation.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu25o0i</id>
        <replies>
            <author>are_you_seriously</author>
            <ReplyBody>Your 18/16 scenario is flawed. Romeo and Juliet laws exist for cases like this.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu2bijb</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>They don't exist everywhere though, and they can be flawed even when implemented; there was a case a friend and I argued about where an 18 year old girl was convicted of statutory rape for having what would be consensual sex with her 14 year old girlfriend (freshman/senior), and the 14 year old's parents were super-religious and had her arrested. The 18 year old was convicted but the judge ruled that she wouldn't be put on the sex offender's registry.

(In case you cared, the argument was that my friend was yelling about how adults shouldn't fuck children and it was inappropriate that the judge even considered that an option, while I said that cases like this were why we bothered with judges and didn't just have sentencing computers.)</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2da90</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>are_you_seriously</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I'm pretty sure they exist in all states, just the ages are defined differently, same as age of consent. The other thing I really dislike is how a lot of people view laws as so black and white and set in stone. We're not robots and laws shouldn't be interpreted as so inflexible. I guess I'm agreeing with you and I'm glad the judge took a middle ground for sentencing.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu2dksj</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>bamfbarber</author>
                        <ReplyBody>They dont.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu2t5hp</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Lapulta</author>
                        <ReplyBody>They don't exist in my state. The moment you turn 18, any sexual relationship you had with someone younger becomes illegal and you can be persecuted/put on the registry. It's pretty damn terrifying.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu4y3jq</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>13</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Ansuz07</author>
                <ReplyBody>Is it? There have been cases where this has happened. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2eh05</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>I didn't include that in my post. An 18 year boy or girl who has a 16 year old boyfriend or girlfriend is not a sex offender in my eyes and what I am suggesting does not apply to cases like that. It applies to cases where a grown adult forcibly has sex or some form of sexual contact with a minor/child.

Also though your following points may be valid, they don't address the original proposition. You're using the slippery slope fallacy. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu25wzm</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Ansuz07</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I didn't include that in my post. An 18 year boy or girl who has a 16 year old boyfriend or girlfriend is not a sex offender in my eyes and what I am suggesting does not apply to cases like that.

Except that, per current laws, he **is** a sex offender.  Even if you change that law, where do you draw the line?  19/15?  20/14?  There will always be fringe cases and the law needs the flexibility to punish those cases appropriately.

&amp;gt; It applies to cases where a grown adult forcibly has sex or some form of sexual contact with a minor/child.

Which is what my 18/16 scenario was - a grown adult (in the eyes of the law) having some form of sexual contact with a minor/child (in the eyes of the law).

&amp;gt;Also though your following points may be valid, they don't address the original proposition. You're using the slippery slope fallacy

How so?  The crux of your argument is that the nature of the crime is so heinous that the potential damage to future victims should be prioritized above the potential for the perpetrator to rehabilitate and life a prosperous, lawful life.  Is this correct?

My argument is that there are **many** crimes where an innocent victim is traumatized by a criminal; many more than just child molestation.  Rape victims often never recover from their traumatic events - should raping a child land you in jail for life but raping an adult doesn't?  Both criminals could very well go on to cause devistation so, based on your justification, they should both be locked up, right?

If you argee to that, the slippery slope argument has weight - most crimes cause some level of trauma to the victim so, if the goal is to reduce future victim trauma, many more crimes will warrant life sentances.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu267th</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Which is what my 18/16 scenario was - a grown adult (in the eyes of the law) having some form of sexual contact with a minor/child (in the eyes of the law).

I said "forcibly"

&amp;gt;How so? The crux of your argument is that the nature of the crime is so heinous that the potential damage to future victims should be prioritized above the potential for the perpetrator to rehabilitate and life a prosperous, lawful life. Is this correct?

Yes. 

&amp;gt;...should raping a child land you in jail for life but raping an adult doesn't? Both criminals could very well go on to cause devistation so, based on your justification, they should both be locked up, right?

Yes. They should both be locked up. I was just focusing on child rapists because those are the ones that come up in discussion on Reddit concerning whether or not they should be rehabilitated or just locked away.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu26c1q</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Ansuz07</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I said "forcibly"

No - this is what you said:  It applies to cases where a grown adult forcibly has sex _or some form of sexual contact_ with a minor/child.

Unless you mean that non-forced sex with a minor is ok...  which is not what you mean.  You can't use consent as a metric here - sometimes the younger kid does think this is what they want to do and "consents" which is why we don't have that as a standard in statutory rape or child molestation charges.

So my poor 18 year old is still in jail.

&amp;gt;Yes. They should both be locked up. I was just focusing on child rapists because those are the ones that come up in discussion on Reddit concerning whether or not they should be rehabilitated or just locked away.

So by acknowledging that you want to apply this to more than just one type of crime, you are giving my "slippery slope" fallacy some legitimacy; you **want** it applied to more than just child molestation.

So now we have rape and child rape on the books:

- Murder - that is pretty traumatic.  Better lock all of them up
- Assault - that can cause PTSD, which can be as damaging as rape PTSD.  They're gone
- Robbery - that is pretty traumatic for a while.  Get rid of them.
- Stalking - that is really traumatic.  Peace out!

Where does it stop? 

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu26m1p</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Unless you mean that non-forced sex with a minor is ok...

No it isn't ok.

So by acknowledging that you want to apply this to more than just one type of crime, you are giving my "slippery slope" fallacy some legitimacy; you want it applied to more than just child molestation.

&amp;gt;So now we have rape and child rape on the books:

    &amp;gt;Murder - that is pretty traumatic. Better lock all of them up
    Assault - that can cause PTSD, which can be as damaging as rape PTSD. They're gone
    Robbery - that is pretty traumatic for a while. Get rid of them.
    Stalking - that is really traumatic. Peace out!

&amp;gt;Where does it stop? 

I only mentioned rape of adults because crimes of a sexual nature-whether or not the victim is a child or an adult are often met with arguments saying that we should focus on rehabilitating sex offenders of all types so when they are released they don't commit more sex crimes.

Of course not all crimes traumatize the victims to the same extent. You are using the slippery slope for crimes I haven't mentioned. Can we please just focus on child sex offenders?

I'm only trying to explain why I believe the idea of rehabilitation for **sex offenders** is an idea that isn't feasible in moral terms. I'm not here to discuss littering or jaywalking.

I'm here to discuss one thing: Is the rehabilitation and release of sex offenders who prey upon children feasible or ethical? 

So can you address that argument instead of going off on tangents about other crimes that I have never referred to in my original post? I'm trying to have a discussion to see if my reasoning is sound and if not can it be changed.

</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu26x1q</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Ansuz07</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;No it isn't ok.

Which was my point.  It isn't about the forced sex, it's about sex with a minor.  This still puts my 18 year old kid in jail for life, which you would probably agree isn't ok.

&amp;gt;Can we please just focus on child sex offenders?

No, we can't for two reasons

1)  You openly said that you want it applied to more crimes than just child sex offenders

2)  The logic you are using to justify it is not exclusive to child sex offenders.  If you are going to propose that potential for rehabilitation should not be a factor when compared to the rights of potential victims, you don't get to draw a box around a single crime and claim that your argument is only valid inside the box.  

If the majority of criminals can't be rehabilitated, you are proposing locking them up for life - even the ones that **can** be rehabilitated.  You can't hide behind a particularly heinous crime to protect yourself from defending the fundamental premise.

&amp;gt;I'm only trying to explain why I believe the idea of rehabilitation for sex offenders is an idea that isn't feasible in moral terms.

Statistics say it isn't feasible for robbery, assault, drug use or vagrancy either.  All of those crimes cause trauma (to an extent) to victims as well.

&amp;gt;I'm here to discuss one thing: Is the rehabilitation and release of sex offenders who prey upon children feasible or ethical?

That is not the CMV you submitted.  What yo submitted was:   _Sexual predators who prey upon minors should either be executed or kept in prison for life. No attempt at rehabilitating them for release back into society should be made._  I have been challenging the premise of that CMV.  If that wasn't the view you wanted changed, you shouldn't have said that.

&amp;gt;So can you address that argument instead of going off on tangents about other crimes that I have never referred to in my original post. I'm trying to have a discussion to see if my reasoning is sound and if not can it be changed?

And I am trying to challenge that reasoning by challengin the premise you laid out in your expliation **and** the premise you agreed with me on earlier in this comment thread.  Apparently, that isn't the view you _actually_ want changed...</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu278rq</id>
<replies>
    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;You openly said that you want it applied to more crimes than just child sex offenders

Besides those who rape adults I haven't said I wanted it applied to more crimes.

&amp;gt;If the majority of criminals can't be rehabilitated, you are proposing locking them up for life - even the ones that can be rehabilitated. You can't hide behind a particularly heinous crime to protect yourself from defending the fundamental premise.

I'm not proposing that the majority of criminals be kept in prison for life. I'm proposing that sex offenders who rape or molest children or other adults be kept in prison for life. I never said I wanted all criminals to be locked away. You are attacking arguments I haven't made.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cu27gc5</id>
    <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>10</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>warsage</author>
<ReplyBody>Everyone is bringing this point up because they're trying to hit one of your points of logic. From what I see, your point of view goes like this.

1. Child molesters hurt someone terribly and permanently.
2. Any criminal who hurts someone terribly and permanently should be given the death sentence or life in prison without possibility of parole, regardless of potential rehabilitation or evident good behavior.
3. Therefore, child molesters should be given the death sentence or life in prison.

Everyone is trying to work on your logical point number 2. If they can destroy point 2, then your whole argument falls apart. You would have a logical inconsistency in your own argument.

They're trying to show you that "you hurt someone badly" is not sufficient reason for life in prison.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu282q2</id>
<replies>
    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
    <ReplyBody>I see your point.

It isn't the trauma that happens after the crime has been committed, though that is a part of it, it's the crime itself and the potential for re offense.

Raping a child is a horrible thing to do. Trying to compare its severity to beating someone up or robbing someone is false.  

&amp;gt;Any criminal who hurts someone terribly and permanently should be given the death sentence or life in prison without possibility of parole, regardless of potential rehabilitation or evident good behavior.

I may have made a miscommunication. This is not my claim at all. I'm not saying we should put people away solely for doing horrible things (Though that is what the law is for), I'm saying we should put child predators away for life because of the **potential** that they can inflict more harm as soon as they get out regardless of any attempt at rehabilitation.

I'm specifically focusing on child molesters. I am not saying it should apply to every single crime because every crime is not as severe or comparable to raping a child. Apparently some people would beg to differ.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cu28dvn</id>
    <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>7</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>9</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu26v2z</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>lamasnot</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Okay so the 43 year old man did not have beat the 6 year old into allowing him access he bribed her with candy like her other abusers.... this is somehow better?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu2bpi5</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu2c2lp</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>lamasnot</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Perhaps. But clearly there need to be some sort of laws for this type of thing</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu2chof</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Sadsharks</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Seriously?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu3e0sh</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>We are getting off topic. This is irrelevant to what I originally posted.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu270m5</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>alexandertwentytwo</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Yes it is. You use force a lot. What if it's not forced. Does that change your mind on death? Is statutory the same as aggressive rape.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu27a26</id>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-7</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-9</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>23</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>chevybow</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Any measure that prevents children from harm is necessary and ethical. Even if it means keeping convicted sex offenders in prison for the rest of their natural lives.


At what cost? Should all crimes against children result in execution or life imprisonment to "try and make the world a better place". 


Here are some crimes where the child is a victim: 

* Child Abduction/Kidnapping

* Murder of a child

* Child abuse (can be physical and not sexual)

* Production/Possession/Viewing of child pornography


* Sex with anyone under the age of consent 


* Soliciting a minor 

* Neglect of a child

* Child abandonment 

* Sexting with an underage person



According to your logic we should execute people who get arrested for any of the above crimes. Obviously some are worse than others, but do you honestly believe every single person who gets a charge related to a crime to a child has no chance of changing their ways and instead the ethical decision is to kill all these criminals? How far are you willing to go to protect children? 


What makes children so special that people who murder or rape adults aren't required to be executed or imprisoned for the rest of their lives? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu274v7</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Any measure that prevents children from harm is necessary and ethical. Even if it means keeping convicted sex offenders in prison for the rest of their natural lives.

I apologize if I wasn't clear. I don't mean in general. The context I'm referring to is in relation to sex offenders. I'm not proposing anything for those who neglect or abandon children.

I'm only talking about the rape and molestation of children by sex offenders who are released from prison. Anything else is just slippery slope fallacies and irrelevant to this discussion.

It seems as if the only flaw in my post that people can find is that it can lead to a slippery slope. How about you address what I actually specifically proposed instead of going off on tangents?

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu27bpr</id>
            <replies>
                <author>chevybow</author>
                <ReplyBody>I don't see how its going off on a tangent. Are you saying that none of the other crimes against children should be held to as a high a degree (I guess you think rape is worse than any other crime?). Or do you believe that the other crimes I listed aren't committed by repeat offenders. 


By all means do stop replying to me because I "go off on tangents". But as I see this discussion it seems you're only willing to consider a very select amount of responses, convenient on your behalf, and the rest you dismiss as "irrelevant" because you're unable to form an intelligent response. 


When you suggest that we murder a select few amount of criminals, criminals who commit very similar crimes are definitely relevant to the discussion. This includes both rape against adults by repeat sexual offenders and crimes against children that might not be as bad in your eyes. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu27hor</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;When you suggest that we murder a select few amount of criminals

I said either we create a system of rehabilitation that has a 100% success rate (Not possible with modern technology), put them away for life, **or** execute them. I'm fine with any of those options.

Murder wasn't my first resort. Putting them away for life is just as good to me as executing them. I don't care which one happens.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu27qrw</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ryancarp3</author>
                        <ReplyBody>If those are your options, how are we supposed to change your view? A 100% success rate is impossible, and the other two options are your view. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu289of</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Explain that the moral cost of keeping child molesters in prison for life are higher than rehabilitating them and releasing them into society with the chance that they may re offend and harm other children.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu28vwj</id>
                            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>MarcusWilliamsII</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The context I'm referring to is in relation to sex offenders. I'm not proposing anything for those who neglect or abandon children.

Why not? What is the distinction, in your mind, between sex crimes and other crimes? Sex crimes tend to have a very low recidivism rate compared to violent crimes, so this doesn't really make sense.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu3zpc3</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu264lt</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;In order to morally/ethically hold the view that you do, to be consistent in that view, you'd also have to take this stance with many crimes which we as a society have decided do not warrant throwing away the key over.

Though there are heinous crimes that may be deserving of life in prison, I'm not focusing on those. 

I'm focusing on the one crime that people argue over what should be done with the perpetrator. Pedophilia is unique because it's inherent to the person. They can't help being attracted to children. They can help whether or not they act on those feelings. 

People often propose that since they can't be locked away forever they should be rehabilitated before being released. I'm saying this shouldn't happen for this particular crime because the chances of re offense outweigh the chances of success in moral and ethical terms.

I'm not here to debate about whether or not shop lifting or bank robbery should be met with life in prison. That's irrelevant. I'm strictly focusing on a crime that many people say should be fought with rehabilitation instead of punishment.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu26kcv</id>
            <replies>
                <author>warsage</author>
                <ReplyBody>Could you also respond to the other point of /u/gabrielamodesta?

&amp;gt;First, it can give someone a 'nothing else to lose' mindset more quickly, and may have some pre-incarceration unintended consequences (like, instead of just molesting them, maybe they kill them too). Can you really argue that a molester should be punished more severely than a killer? A living (but abused) child has an opportunity to move past the abuse, and live a full life. A dead child is dead. Both are horrific, but one is clearly worse than the other in terms of what has been 'taken'.

If you threaten any molesters with the death sentence, then they're much more likely to **kill** the child instead of just hurting them. That way the child can't talk, right? And the punishment for the molester is the same no matter what.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu27o64</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;If you threaten any molesters with the death sentence, then they're much more likely to kill the child instead of just hurting them. That way the child can't talk, right? And the punishment for the molester is the same no matter what.

We can't control whether or not child molesters kill or leave their victims alive. But we can control what child molesters in prison do. We can attempt to rehabilitate them, release them without any attempt to rehabilitate them, or we can put them away for life.

Whichever option causes the least amount of harm to innocent children, is the option I'll consider to be the right one.

I'm trying to find out which option is better for society and which option causes more harm to innocent lives.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu27ydf</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu29369</id>
                        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>therapy</author>
        <ReplyBody>Three points:

 * **[The recidivism rate for sex offenders is extremely low](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex_offender#Recidivism)**. In other words, someone locked up for rape is very very unlikely to be found guilty of another rape. This is in stark contrast to other crimes, in which a drug dealer is in fact quite likely to repeat that offense. As mentioned in that link, sex offenders are the least likely type of criminal to commit their crime again, except for murder.
 * You mention people that rape minors as having an innate attraction for children, but actually **[not all people that rape minors are pedophiles](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child_sexual_abuse#Pedophilia)**. Some are, but some are not. Offenders might do it because of other reasons than sexual attraction to children. And while pedophilia seems to be an innate disposition, and not a choice, other reasons might be more treatable by therapy.
 * Finally, an important principle in our system of justice is that "**[better that ten guilty persons escape than that one innocent suffer](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackstone's_formulation)"**. We require very strong reasons to lock people up.

If someone rapes a minor, that is a horrifying crime. They should serve an appropriate prison sentence as well as any monetary penalties, and should receive mental health treatment. But once they finish their sentence, we know as mentioned above that the chances of them doing it again are very slim. Yes, there is some chance they will, but to prevent that small chance you will need to keep a very large number of innocent people locked up in an unjust manner.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu28dml</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is an excellent post that addresses my argument.

&amp;gt;Finally, an important principle in our system of justice is that "better that ten guilty persons escape than that one innocent suffer". We require very strong reasons to lock people up.

This is valid.

&amp;gt;Yes, there is some chance they will, but to prevent that small chance you will need to keep a very large number of innocent people locked up in an unjust manner.

You make it seem as if a large percentage of people convicted of raping or molesting a child are innocent people that were unlucky. If it means that x amount of children won't be raped or molested then that is something I'm willing to accept.

Which I know many people disagree with but this is merely my belief. If I have to lock up 1 innocent person if it means keeping 10 actual criminals away also, I'll do it. It isn't perfect but no system is perfect. It's sad that innocent people get locked up but sometimes you have to make the best of a situation like that.

I'd never let 10 guilty people escape to stop one innocent from suffering. Any other circumstance I would do my best to save that innocent person but in this case the cost is greater than the benefit

I'd let 1 criminal get away to save 1 innocent person. But any higher than 1 criminal and I'm sorry but the cost is too high. If those 10 criminals escape and rape and murder more people, you basically let x amount of people die or be raped just so you could save one person. That doesn't make sense if you value the well being of others. Sometimes a small number have to suffer so an even larger group doesn't.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu28s8t</id>
            <replies>
                <author>therapy</author>
                <ReplyBody>Sorry if I was unclear. I don't think that people that serve a sentence for rape are often innocent. They are generally guilty. However, after they **finish** their sentence, they are obviously not "innocent" in the sense that they did do something very bad in the past, but they are "innocent" in that they have no current crime for which they deserve punishment, and have a new chance to live their lives out of jail. A chance which, the data shows, most of them take, and do not commit another crime.

If you do not let them out of jail, you will be imprisoning many innocent people just to prevent 1 actually dangerous person from being released.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu298lq</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;If you do not let them out of jail, you will be imprisoning many innocent people just to prevent 1 actually dangerous person from being released.

You mean I'll be imprisoning many guilty/dangerous people from being released along with a tiny amount of innocent people?

Like I said, the benefit of locking up many criminals outweighs the harm of also imprisoning a few innocents. Though some would disagree.

It isn't like 50 percent are innocent and 50 percent are guilty. It's a a larger number of people who are guilty of child rape or molestation than those who were unjustly convicted. 

Which I believe is worth it and is a lot better both practically and morally than just saying "Well we don't know if 100% are guilty so let's release everyone"

Releasing 10 dangerous people to protect 1 innocent person doesn't make sense considering 1 is not equal to 10 and you have to include all of the future victims those 10 criminals will rape or kill after they are released. 

Not that all 10 of them will re offend, but some of them will. And if the price of preventing those x amount of people from becoming victims of released criminals is having a small fraction of innocents locked up as well, then it is worth it.

it's unfortunate that innocent people get locked up but that doesn't mean you free everyone to save one person. No system is perfect. Accept that and move on. You have to look at it rationally and without emotion. 

"If I release these 10 bad guys to save one good guy, what about the other good guys the bad guys will kill or rape once released? Surely that amount justifies keeping them all imprisoned."</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu29o3g</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>therapy</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; You mean I'll be imprisoning many guilty/dangerous people from being released along with a tiny amount of innocent people?

Maybe I wasn't clear, let me try again: After their sentence is served, we know that only 1 out of 20 convicted rapists will commit another rape. The remaining 19 will never rape again. So if you keep all 20 locked up, you are keeping **one** dangerous person off the street, at the cost of jailing **19** that are innocent of any chance of raping again.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu29z3z</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I understand now.

Is this rate the same for child molesters?

Because a pedophile (unless he's been treated and even then) isn't going to walk out of prison and never think about a child in a sexual manner ever again. That's not realistic. Unless you can brainwash him or chemically castrate him, there's still the chance he goes back to his old ways. 

Which is what I want to prevent. Because any rape or molestation that could have been prevented should be. Even if the failure rate of any rehabilitation program for child molesters is only 5 percent, that's still too high for me. What are you going to say to the parents when you tell them their child was attacked by someone who the system guaranteed was cured of his impulses and that he posed no threat to society?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu2actw</id>
                            <replies>
<author>therapy</author>
<ReplyBody>I see what you mean. But, why stop at 5%? If you are willing to go even lower, you can prevent even more rapes and molestation of children.

For example, it is known that **[pedophilia is comorbid with substance abuse](http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10327918), among other things: That study found that 60% of pedophiles had a substance abuse diagnosis, far higher than the general public. Given that information, we could consider taking inmates about to be released, that were **not** convicted with anything related to pedophilia, but that do have a substance abuse diagnosis, and keeping them incarcerated. Since pedophilia and substance abuse have a correlation, we will be preventing some future child abusers and child rapists from reentering society.

In other words, why stop at people actually convicted of rape or abuse of a child, when we can predict who is at risk of doing so in the future? Most of our guesses would be wrong, of course, but if we use the proper scientifically-validated criteria - by making the best guess we can - we will prevent some rapes that way, at the cost of locking up a lot of people that are no danger to anyone.

This is a hard decision to make. It's similar to speed limits: The speed limit might be 60 MPH in some area. If you lower it to 55, you'll save some lives, because people driving more slowly suffer less harm when they crash (or crash less). But then, why not lower it to 50, or 45, or 40? The lower you go, the more lives you save.

We don't go all the way down because there is a **cost** to lowering the speed limit. Forcing people to drive slowly on a highway means a lot of wasted time on the road.

The same is true with pedophiles. When we catch them we should lock them up. But we can't keep going to further and further extremes to prevent any chance of anyone being a pedophile from being out of prison, because the further we go, the more innocent people are locked up unjustly.

At some point, we have to make a compromise and decide where to draw the line. Society has drawn that line at the current punishments for those crimes. We can debate if those should be a little longer or a little shorter, but once the time is served, the person should be let go.
</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu2bxzo</id>
<upvotes>4</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>MarcusWilliamsII</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Because a pedophile (unless he's been treated and even then) isn't going to walk out of prison and never think about a child in a sexual manner ever again. That's not realistic.

It is not a crime to think about children in a sexual manner. Sexual abuse is a crime.

Keep in mind that most acts of sexual abuse towards children are not committed by pedophiles, and most pedophiles do not commit acts of sexual abuse. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu3zsql</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Ansuz07</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Which I know many people disagree with but this is merely my belief. If I have to lock up 1 innocent person if it means keeping 10 actual criminals away also, 

Are **you** willing to be that 1 innocent person?  Are you willing to have your entire life taken away from you to keep those 10 guilty people in jail?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2v8ro</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Yes. And even if I wasn't it wouldn't make it wrong.

It would make me a hypocrite but it wouldn't make the argument wrong.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu3lp60</id>
                    <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>lamasnot</author>
                <ReplyBody>I used to think very similarly to you on this point. I have recently read a historical series of narratives called "The devil in the grove" about Marshall 
And the NAACP in the south.  While I pray that the false convictions and the murders of innocent people as "justice" don't happen any more, I'm not so sure.  This book has drastically changed my view on "justice" in this country not too long ago. While we do have DNA and other technologies which drastically help decrease false convictions I feel myself horribly naive in my assumptions about innocence and guilt and our legal system.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2cbwi</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>teerre</author>
        <ReplyBody>I acknowledge your edit, but I don't see how can you make that distinction. Can you explain to me how is child rape different than any other crime? I read your other replies, apparently it's because "They can't help being attracted to children", how is that so? What about murderers or thieves or even white collar criminals? Why don't you say they can't help "being attracted to" killing, stealing or whatever?

Many other crime, if not all, will cause "more pain and suffering", arguably not in the same scale, but they will. If we go no second-chance with child molesters, we'll have to do it to a lot of other crimes, which (I imagine) you would agree really unreasonable, am I correct?




</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu28lu9</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;we'll have to do it to a lot of other crimes, which (I imagine) you would agree really unreasonable, am I correct?

It would have to be a case by case basis. Someone who beats someone in a bar fight wouldn't be punished to the same extent as a child rapist.

Someone who robs banks shouldn't be punished to the same extent.

I could go on and on.

My opinion is not that we should put every single criminal away forever.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu28yrj</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>EpicZiggles</author>
        <ReplyBody>Chemical castration is a much better alternate solution. A scheme was introduced in some parts of the UK where inmates could voluntarily chemically castrate themselves for a reduced sentence but it ran into legal issues. It rendered the inmates impotent and it was a great success before it was stopped. It can be introduced as a preventive measure as well. Most paedophiles do want help with their urges and if chemical castration was easily available, I think it would be both more humane and more effective.
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu26svd</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>**This** is what I wanted to hear. Your idea sounds reasonable.

How successful was it? 

How many offenders went on to re offend after being chemically castrated?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu26zj2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>warsage</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;How many offenders went on to re offend after being chemically castrated?

Who cares? According to you, even is the answer is "1%," it's still not a good enough solution. Throw away the key for all of them.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu27r7g</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>zasasa</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Stop getting aggressive. You're just acting ridiculous.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu29ew3</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>hey_aaapple</author>
                        <ReplyBody>OP is acting ridiculous by ignoring points and saying "that is not related" all over the thread</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu2uz8s</id>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I would like further information on the topic. Is that bad? </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu27t0p</id>
                    <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>10</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>EpicZiggles</author>
                <ReplyBody>It was fairly successful. I can't find exact numbers as it's a fairly new development, but in Scandinavian countries where it is quite widely enforced reoffending rates fell from 40% to 5%.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu275pc</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Were any other treatments tried or did they immediately go to chemical castration?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu27iqg</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>EpicZiggles</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It was a voluntary thing for any prisoner with dangerous sexual thoughts e.g. paedo/necro etc. so it would have varied but I would assume it would have been the box standard therapy/support stuff.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu27sd7</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>So it was voluntary. If I was implementing it I would make it mandatory if they want to be released.

Because if we are trying to protect society from these people, we have to do whatever is necessary to make sure they don't re offend.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu287jv</id>
                            <replies>
<author>are_you_seriously</author>
<ReplyBody>I want to agree with you on the mandatory thing but i think in this case, one of the key factors is that most of the chemical castration was voluntary.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu2bkso</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>EpicZiggles</author>
<ReplyBody>Fair enough.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu2k0ss</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>mizuromo</author>
        <ReplyBody>**NOTE: I WILL BE USING SOMETHING LIKE YOUR "SLIPPERY SLOPE FALLACY" AS PART OF MY ARGUMENT. I WILL ADDRESS WHY I USE IT AT THE BOTTOM OF THIS POST, EVEN THOUGH YOU SPECIFICALLY SAY NOT TO USE IT.**

I agree with many other peoples' posts here, but I noticed a trend in your arguments in which you argue that the cost of letting people who would hurt somebody else go free does not outweigh the detriment of imprisoning someone who would never do such an act again. This is what I will address in this comment, as it seems if I addressed anything else I would just be typing the same thing as other people. 

When people commit a crime and are caught, they pay a price to society. They are locked up or sentenced to community service or whatever as punishment, and once they have served their time they are set free. The punishment varies, but let us assume that the punishment given by the government is for the most part fair. (If we assume that it isn't, that is a completely different issue to address.) 

Now in this particular case, we are talking about molesting children, or more specifically, sexual offenses towards children (which are not always caused by people who are pedophiles). For my example, though, I will use the example of theft. Let's say somebody robbed a bank and was caught by the police and went to jail for however many years the court has mandated them to be in jail. After their debt to society was paid, (no matter how arbitrary the number is, they have paid their society-issued price) they were let free under the assumption that they would never commit theft again. If they were mentally ill, they also received care for that. The question now is this: Does the government allow him to go free after paying his debt, or do they keep him imprisoned under the assumption that he may steal again? 

This is a question about our rights as citizens, and how a justice system can deal with our rights for our offenses. I took theft as an example, which has a much higher repeat offender situation than child molestation. The question is not whether they will commit the crime again, it is whether we can morally punish people for crimes they have not yet committed. 

Now, let's ASSUME that if you have molested children before, it will increase your probabilities of molesting children again. This is an assumption. It is probably not true. (I have no numbers for it, though.) In your argument it would be alright to lock up all sexual offenders indefinitely the for a first offence, rather than allow them to go free. Note that this is the punishment generally given to serial killers. This punishment is not given even towards most murderers or rapists. By this logic, the probability that you will be a terrorist who hijacks a plane increases if you happen to be Muslim. Does this mean we should lock up Muslims for crimes that they have not committed? This is a pretty extreme case, though. Let's take the case of a man who was selling narcotics, which is a crime that people have a much higher chance of returning to once out of prison. Is it moral to imprison them indefinitely because of a crime they might commit? 

The problem isn't that they might commit the crime again. The problem is that we are the ones committing a crime if we are to imprison them indefinitely for whichever crime. 

Also, in terms of sexual predators who target minors: yes, this crime is terrible. It is arguably worse than murdering somebody or raping somebody. Arguably. Yet people who have gone to prison or had current treatment for this crime have one of the lowest rates for committing it again, especially with treatment such as chemical castration. 

**Slippery slope "fallacy" argument:**

Now in this comment, I have argued that we should not lock people up for crimes they have not committed because of the moral issues with it. I have not implied that you mean to lock people up for the other crimes which are not sexual assault of minors. Most of these were analogies to imply that the moral consequences of imprisoning (or executing) people for crimes they have not yet commit. 

A slippery slope fallacy implies that I argued that executing people who commit sexual assault would lead to executing people for other crimes. I did not imply this. If anything, I committed a naturalistic fallacy, in which I implied that it is more morally wrong to lock up innocent people than it is to allow them to commit the crime a second time. 

I am familiar with logical fallacies, and I am aware that nearly all arguments people can make about any particular issue will generally have one. Note that there is also a logical fallacy called the "Logical Fallacy Fallacy", where it is a logical fallacy to imply somebody has a moot argumentative point when they have used a logical fallacy. 

But I digress. I am not implying that doing what you say will be a slippery slope to doing other things. The biggest point of my argument is this: **It is irrelevant whether they will commit the crime in the future. It is morally wrong to incriminate people for crimes they have not yet committed.You have a large moral argument against releasing sex offenders for what they may do in the future. I argue that not releasing them is also immoral. (It also breaks the 5th amendment I think if you live in the US. Something about due process of law or punishments that are too extreme. Sorry if I got the amendment wrong, I didn't do much research for that.) In the end... is it moral to execute or imprison for life an individual for something he hasn't done?**

PS: I am also aware that using analogies is a logical fallacy if the analogy is not well-suited.  I believe my analogy was well-suited enough. I guarantee you that if we were to comb through your arguments on these comments or the OP, we would find many fallacies. Don't be so quick to judge others on fallacies in their arguments when yours probably has some, too. (I acknowledged that my argument also has some fallacies.)</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu2kgxy</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>gurduloo</author>
        <ReplyBody>You should change your view because it is based on a overly strong principle that would justify pre-crime.

&amp;gt;*Any measure* that prevents children from harm is necessary and ethical.

This principle would justify preemptive incarceration of anyone determined to have a greater-than-zero chance of harming a child. If we found, for example, that a certain category of people was 1% more likely to harm children than any other category, this principle would justify us in locking them up before they ever did anything. There is no meaningful difference between incarcerating a person on the grounds that they may assault a child after they have already done so versus before. In either case, we are punishing them for something they have not done and may never do based on our assessment of the risk they pose. 

If you do not support this, then you will have to look at the parents of a raped child and say: 'We knew the man who assaulted your child had a greater-than-zero chance of 
doing this at some point, after all he was a [insert group here], but we didn't arrest him. We had to wait until he *actually* assaulted a child. We're sorry it was your child.' That's fucked up and inconsiderate, don't you think? /s</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu3d2q4</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>keegan112099</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think the problem is that life in prison for a pedophile is also a death sentence.  Either they're completely isolated in which case many would just commit suicide.  Or they're exposed to other criminals who don't care much for pedophiles and you run the risk of them just getting stabbed to death or beaten.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu29ht1</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>Is that a bad thing?

That's unfortunate but like I said, I value the well being of the victims and would be victims over that of a convicted rapist or molester. I don't have much pity for some sick monster who raped/molested children. Neither should any reasonable or moral person.

And there are ways to protect prisoners from the general population within the prison.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu29rez</id>
            <replies>
                <author>keegan112099</author>
                <ReplyBody>I believe in punishment not cruelty.  I disagree that a pedophile should be either isolated or thrown to the wolves and I wouldn't want someone to falsely accused and executed.  I think a year of therapy to determine who they truly are and then a hearing to decide if they truly should be put away for life is a better plan.  If they don't display remorse for their actions and tend to show more signs of sadism than yes I think they should be locked away forever but if not they can come to a decision on how long they remain incarcerated.  This way someone falsely accused or someone who finds what they did deplorable can at least get off easier than someone whose clearly not sane of mind and shows little remorse for what they did.  </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2cd5f</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MonsieurLeMeow</author>
        <ReplyBody>I want to focus on an angle you may not have considered. I have no idea if we have effective rehabilitation techniques to reform child molesters, but I have to believe that if we don't now, we will one day have the knowledge and technology to achieve it. Right now I feel we aren't conducting enough research to find out what causes this phenomenon to occur in the brain and how to prevent it. 

I think research could be done on some limited scale within a prison environment, but you would get a truer data set from all walks of life if your subjects were living out normal lives in the world. For this to work you would need some forgiveness from the population. Obviously the subject would have to be cooperative and really want to reform, but I believe some people deserve that chance. 

Another point on the subject of forgiveness. It's natural to demonize people with these urges, because it's utterly unrelateable. No one can put themselves in the shoes of a paedophile. It's like, "have you tried NOT being a paedophile?" Well these people are aware of what society thinks of that and they fear what will happen if they come out about it. They may be able to get help from a therapist but they try to bottle it up. Maybe the urges get to be too much and they commit an atrocious act. Or maybe they don't. Many paedophiles never act on their feelings and realize they are not healthy thoughts.

Anyway, I think we would be more successful with an approach of helping people before they become dangerous.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu2brp1</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Anyway, I think we would be more successful with an approach of helping people before they become dangerous.

I agree.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu2c08m</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Bashi_Hart</author>
        <ReplyBody>Do you realize that the child molesting predator your talking about is very rare? More than 90% of sexual molestation cases involving children are perpatrated by a family member or close friend? 

This type of offender doesn't re-offend often, and can be helped. It is usually just a case of oppertunity, not grooming or predation.


The old idea of a stranger on the playground watching your kids for a chance to grab them in a windowless van is just laughable. While rare, it is these type of offenders that go out and prey upon children, but even in these cases, death is not the answer, and never is. 
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu2d10h</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>I didn't say death was the answer. I said they should be imprisoned for life OR executed. I don't care which.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu2d3px</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Bashi_Hart</author>
                <ReplyBody>Execution almost always results in death...


And prisons are already over crowded and underfunded.  You wanna lock up everyone who molests a child for life which could be 60 years? There isnt space, nor are there funds to house and feed someone who isnt likely to reoffend. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cu2defg</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Shoot them then</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cu2fpuf</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Bashi_Hart</author>
                        <ReplyBody>You sir, are being an asshat. If you think killing anyone is a form of punishment for any reason, then you are deranged. I submit to you, that no matter what anyone says, you will not change your ass backwards way of thinking, Good day to you sir.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cu2g931</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>[I guess that means that 56% of Americans are asshats and deranged.] (http://deathpenaltyinfo.org/node/6118)</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cu2ghd7</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Bashi_Hart</author>
<ReplyBody>Yeah, and according to your own source, that number is on the decline... probably cus that 56% keeps going out and killing each other... </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cu2gjzr</id>
<replies>
    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
    <ReplyBody>Yeah definitely even though murder rates are lower now than they have been in years.

I guess if you support the death penalty you are a crazed bloodthirsty degenerate who can snap and kill someone on a whim.

Have fun attacking your death penalty strawman.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cu2gzpo</id>
    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu2t60q</id>
        <replies>
            <author>garnteller</author>
            <ReplyBody>Sorry justin1983r, your comment has been removed: 

&amp;gt; Comment Rule 1\. "Direct responses to a CMV post must challenge at least one aspect of OPs current view (however minor), unless they are asking a clarifying question. Arguments in favor of the view OP is willing to change must be restricted to replies to comments." [See the wiki page for more information.](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules#wiki_rule_1)  

If you would like to appeal, please [message the moderators by clicking this link.](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Fchangemyview&amp;amp;subject=Removed+Comment+Rule+1+Post+Appeal&amp;amp;message=justin1983r+would+like+to+appeal+the+removal+of+[his/her+post](https://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3gwou8/cmv_sexual_predators_who_prey_upon_minors_should/cu2t60q\))</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu2tp14</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>LivingReaper</author>
        <ReplyBody>This is copy pasted from a previous talk I had with someone, but it's mostly relevant.

1) Paedophelia is listed as a mental disorder under the DSM V (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Version 5) and without proper acceptance of it as such a thing people with the disorder, whether it be severe or temperate, help is not there or they will become an outcast if they seek help and it is found out by the general public.

2) I want to point out the fact that not all sex offenders are paedophiles. Yes, they commited a crime. No, it was not always relating to a child. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex_offender_registry...
Excerpt: So an offender's tier is not necessarily based on the seriousness of the crime, nor does it reflect the danger or re-offense risk of the offender. However, offenses must be punishable by imprisonment for more than 1 year (i.e., a felony) to be classified higher than Tier I. Critics claim that mandatory registration requirement based solely on the virtue of a conviction makes sex offender registries less efficient in keeping track of more dangerous offenders, and *unnecessarily exposes non-dangerous low-level offenders to severe adverse consequences* of being labelled as a sex offender.

The part that I attempted to highlight (the *s, Facebook isn't exactly discussion friendly) explains that there are situations where someone is not a paedophile and was put on the list.

3, and relating to 2) Paedophelia is widely used for anyone under 18, while it is only correct for anyone under 13. People under 18 are minors.
Via Wikipedia: 
Pedophilia or paedophilia is a psychiatric disorder in which an adult or older adolescent experiences a primary or exclusive sexual attraction to prepubescent children, generally age 11 years or younger. As a medical diagnosis, specific criteria for the disorder extend the cut-off point for prepubescence to age 13.
Hebephilia is the strong and persistent adult sexual interest in pubescent individuals, typically ages 1114.
Ephebophilia is the primary or exclusive adult sexual interest in mid-to-late adolescents, generally ages 15 to 19.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu3vxn2</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MarcusWilliamsII</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; However, I believe the margin of error is too great to take the chance to release these people back into society as opposed to keeping them in prison for life or executing them.

The margin of error of false criminal convictions is also not 0%. I think you will kill a lot more innocent people than will ever be protected by this measure. 

&amp;gt; But the human cost is too high.

The human cost of executing hundreds of thousands of people is far higher.

&amp;gt; No system is perfect. Chances are that out of all the sex offenders who are "rehabilitated", at least some of them WILL go on to rape or molest more children. Knowing this, we shouldn't release them at all.

Chances are that of all people who are left handed, some of them WILL go on to rape or molest children. Does that mean we should execute left handed people? No. We don't punish people for crimes they may commit in the future. That is one of the most important tenets of western law.

As far as prevention goes, child molestation has one of the lowest recidivism rates of any crime.

&amp;gt; You can't heal from getting raped or molested as a child. 

This is **absolutely not true**, and one of the worst things you can say to a victim of such a crime.

&amp;gt; I value the life and well being of innocent children more than that of those could harm them.

The law values the lives of all humans equally. Justice does not play favorites. Justice is blind.

&amp;gt; Arguments should address whether or not the rehabilitation and release of sex offenders who prey upon children is feasible or ethical. 

My arguments will address your proposal to execute all child molesters and rapists, which is neither feasible, nor ethical.

&amp;gt; Try to avoid slippery slope arguments because I'm NOT proposing that any other crime besides rape or molestation be punished with life in prison. 

The slippery slope argument holds, because there are many cases of child molestation that have mitigating circumstances. For example, statutory rape cases in which consent was given, but deemed be invalid. There are **many** cases where the victims of such crimes would not want the perpetrator to be executed.

Imagine telling a little girl that you are going to kill her father, whom she loves, because of a single incident that she reported. Imagine the psychological trauma that would occur from her knowledge that reporting this incident resulted in the death of her father. Imagine the chilling effect this would have on children everywhere, would would now be afraid to report minor cases of abuse, for fear of the extreme and barbaric overreaction of the legal system?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cu3zl6y</id>
        <replies>
            <author>DeleteTheWeak</author>
            <ReplyBody>
&amp;gt;The law values the lives of all humans equally. Justice does not play favorites. Justice is blind.

Where are you from? If you're in the US, have you read the news paper in the last 20 years?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cu5aieq</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>This is a somewhat complex issue but I'll try to explain it and my views on what I think should be done.

Some people have an innate attraction towards children. This is sad. They can't act on it without harming someone. Some act on it and rape/molest children. This is also sad and horrible.

So we catch a child predator and put him in prison. As far as I know there is no law allowing for child predators to be put away for life. I know in some states the death penalty can be applied but isn't always carried out.

The child predator gets convicted and goes to prison for however long the sentence is.

There are those who say that people who prey upon children should be rehabilitated and released back into society. I am unaware of any programs that try to rehabilitate pedophiles and child predators. If they do exist and if they have succeeded at rehabilitating people, please tell me since I don't know much concerning that aspect of this debate.

So the child predator enters a program to make sure he doesn't re offend when he enters society. If he shows potential and meets the criteria for being released (Whatever the criteria may be) he gets released in the hopes he can become a productive citizen that doesn't harm children.

This is a good thing on its face, at least to some people. I DO believe that if we are to release people like those who have sex with or molest children, we should at least make the attempt to prevent them from doing it again.

I don't know how successful these programs have been at making sure child predators don't re offend. I don't know the percentage of success vs failure, as in what number of those in the program went on to molest or rape again compared to those that didn't.

However, I believe the margin of error is too great to take the chance to release these people back into society as opposed to keeping them in prison for life or executing them.

By margin of error I don't necessarily know that the percentage of those who will re offend is too high to be statistically feasible, I don't know what the exact statistics are concerning this. I would like to know however.

Let's say that for every child predator that becomes viable for release and is entered into a program designed to rehabilitate them so they don't rape or molest more kids as soon as they leave prison, that out of every 100, 1 or 5 or 10 will re offend and rape or molest AT LEAST 1 child.

I believe that even if the success rate is many times higher than the rate of failure, it is still too high to be  morally feasible or even ethical.

No system is perfect. Chances are that out of all the sex offenders who are "rehabilitated", at least some of them WILL go on to rape or molest more children. Knowing this, we shouldn't release them at all. We should either execute them or keep them in prison until they die of old age.

I value the well being of the victims and the potential victims more than I do that of the perpetrators. Even if a program was created so that 99% of all who enter it never harm a single child again, that 1% is far too high to be allowed to occur.

It isn't high statistically of course. But the human cost is too high. Money can be replaced. Property can be replaced or fixed. If you get beaten up your wounds will heal eventually. You can't heal from getting raped or molested as a child. From that point on your life is changed. You have to deal with those memories for the rest of your life. Your whole life will be a battle to overcome what happened to you. Mentally and emotionally an event as traumatizing as that can be damaging. You can become depressed or addicted to drugs. Living life as a rape victim is not pleasant at all. It's a nightmare. Especially at such a young age to be raped or molested.

If you support this idea, are you going to be able to look into the face of the friends and family of the innocent child/children that was raped or molested by someone who was supposed to be cured or fixed of his/her desire to fuck kids and tell them:

"I'm sorry your loved one was harmed and is now going to be traumatized for life and will have this horrific event in their mind indefinitely. I'm sorry but we had to release these people back into society and make sure they don't harm anymore children. Your case, though tragic, was simply a statistical error that we couldn't account for. Meanwhile we will continue to release people just like the person who raped your child in the hopes they don't re offend"

That's a really cold and fucked up thing to tell someone whose son or daughter was raped or molested. Telling the victim that their tragedy was the result of a 1% chance of failure or a 5% chance in a program designed to prevent children being harmed is just inconsiderate.

It seems like it values the perpetrators and ignores the victims. I value the life and well being of innocent children more than that of those could harm them.

It isn't moral to release 100 people with the knowledge that a small fraction of them will certainly cause more pain and suffering. 

I'm not saying that pedophiles and the like can't be rehabilitated. I'm saying that it isn't a 100% guarantee of success so we shouldn't release any of them, regardless of their chances. The margin of error (A child or children being raped or molested) is too high to be feasible or ethical/moral.

So I suggest either we create a program that can 100% guarantee that those in said program won't rape or molest again when they get freedom (Not likely at all with modern technology) or we keep them in prison for life. Or execute them. I'm fine with any of those options.

Any measure that prevents children from harm is necessary and ethical. Even if it means keeping convicted sex offenders in prison for the rest of their natural lives.

My view can be changed by proving that the pros of releasing child predators back into society after attempting to rehabilitate them is larger than the cons of children being molested or raped by someone who was "cured" or "rehabilitated."

You have to prove that it is worth it morally/ethically to rehabilitate sex offenders and release them back into society even if the chance that they will re offend again is not certain or consists of a small percentage (Lower than 10%)

Edit: Arguments should address whether or not the rehabilitation and release of sex offenders who prey upon children is feasible or ethical. Try to avoid slippery slope arguments because I'm **NOT** proposing that any other crime besides rape or molestation be punished with life in prison. I'm not saying we should put litterers and people who steal candy bars away for life. Don't attack arguments I haven't made by using the slippery slope fallacy.</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
