<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>66</commentCount>
    <id>1xf9jf</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1xf9jf/i_believe_it_is_unjustifiable_to_support_abortion/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>In other words, you believe in moral absolutism, in which circumstance has no bearing on an action. 

Who are you to judge when an abortion should take place? You basically have argued that the life of the child has priority over the life of the mother, because as you say one life is denied either way. In this case, who makes the decision? God? No, that's not justifiable. Nature? Why is that justifiable?

Circumstance matters. Denying the life of a fetus which may or may not even life to become a "life," which may or may not ruin the lives of countless others due to the complications it brings, and which may or may not kill the mother/be born into a life of unbearable pain and suffering/have other impacts that are CIRCUMSTANTIAL is different than arguing certain crimes warrant death.

You can't compare the two as a simple "Denial of Life." Because one is taking away life, the other is denying a potential life. That's completely different. They are objectively different scenarios.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfatfnc</id>
        <replies>
            <author>WolfChrist</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not supporting either, nor am I prioritizing the life of the child over the life of the mother. 
 
My argument is that, as concepts, you can't support one without supporting the other and vice versa. 

In a perfect world where the death penalty is always deserved (as decided by that society) and abortions are always performed safely, something dies either way. The fetus is alive no matter how you look at it, and an abortion kills that mass of cells. The death penalty kills a person. Both result in a loss of life. One denies a chance at redemption, the other denies a chance at living life. 

Of course context matters, but you can't discuss these two things in terms of context because every situation is unique. You can't really compare them equally when looking at context, because no set of extenuating circumstances are ever perfectly equivalent. That's why I'm arguing about them as ideals or concepts, rather than on a case by case basis. 

I don't think 'taking away life' and 'denying potential life' are completely different at all. Either way, there is one less human being in the world, and that means that whatever that human being could have done or become will never happen. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfatjv2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>There isn't one less human being in the world if you have an abortion. You can't definitively prove that any fetus would actually survive childbirth. It's the difference between a potential life and a life spent in prison.

Anyone who would be up for the death penalty will never leave jail. So you are arguing that an unborn fetus is equal to a person in a prison cell for their entire remaining life. I don't see it.

The world isn't perfect. People who deal in absolutes and hypotheticals don't grasp what morality is. Morality isn't absolute or hypothetical. It is circumstantial and subjective.

I could say that those who support assisted suicide cannot morally oppose abortion, because both are the denial of life, but it is a ridiculous stance to take, as they are completely different scenarios. In a perfect world, all abortions are safe and etc, and all assisted suicides are completely on the up and up. It doesn't matter, they are still two different concepts entirely.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfato9o</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>WolfChrist</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You also can't definitively prove that the fetus won't survive childbirth. Either way, you remove the possibility from the equation. 

"I could say that those who support assisted suicide cannot morally oppose abortion, because both are the denial of life, but it is a ridiculous stance to take, as they are completely different scenarios."

Why is that so ridiculous a stance? It doesn't matter how it happens, in all three of these scenarios something/someone is dead. There is no more life. If someone holds life as sacred, then they wouldn't support any of them, because for them it would be wrong to deny any form of life. 

Saying murder, abortion, and assisted suicide are entirely different concepts is like saying that football, soccer, and rugby are entirely different just because they don't use the same rules. They're all still sports. 

Also, this is a little off-topic, but isn't saying "The world isn't perfect. People who deal in absolutes and hypotheticals don't grasp what morality is. Morality isn't absolute or hypothetical. It is circumstantial and subjective," absolutist? </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cfatqs0</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Also, this is a little off-topic, but isn't saying "The world isn't perfect. People who deal in absolutes and hypotheticals don't grasp what morality is. Morality isn't absolute or hypothetical. It is circumstantial and subjective," absolutist?

No, it's not. Are you five years old? "Haha look I got you. You said morality is subjective but you are saying it is objectively subjective which means you're being absolutist!" No. I'm saying it's subjective. Which means it's subjective. 

&amp;gt; You also can't definitively prove that the fetus won't survive childbirth. Either way, you remove the possibility from the equation.

I don't need to. The fact is there is a chance the child won't live, so it's already a different scenario. It just is. If there was a 10% chance the guy would survive the death penalty maybe it would make sense, but even then, no... it wouldn't.

&amp;gt; "I could say that those who support assisted suicide cannot morally oppose abortion, because both are the denial of life, but it is a ridiculous stance to take, as they are completely different scenarios."

Because one has literally nothing to do with the other. One is someone who WANTS to die. Another is something that is arguably even a person. They are completely different scenarios.

&amp;gt; Saying murder, abortion, and assisted suicide are entirely different concepts is like saying that football, soccer, and rugby are entirely different just because they don't use the same rules. They're all still sports.

No, that's not a proper analogy at all. Murder, abortion and assisted suicide are like saying football, the movies, and dancing are entirely different because THEY ARE ENTIRELY DIFFERENT. Sure they all provide entertainment to people but that doesn't give them enough in common to throw them all into the same category. That's asinine.

It's pretty obvious you are just a Christian looking for a way to defend your prolife stance.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfatt70</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>WolfChrist</author>
                            <ReplyBody>"No, it's not. Are you five years old?"

That's uncalled for. I'm not trying to attack you, so please don't try to attack me. You said that people who deal in absolutes don't grasp what morality is. That's an absolute statement, because you're making a generalization about a group of people without taking any individual one of them into account. If someone is a moral absolutist, you can't say they don't know what morality is. Their idea of morality differs from yours, but that doesn't mean that they don't grasp the concept. 

"It's pretty obvious you are just a Christian looking for a way to defend your prolife stance."

No, I'm not a Christian. I'm prolife for my own reasons. I posted this topic to have an interesting discussion about one of my personal views, not make assumptions about the people I'm talking with. 

I want this to be a civil conversation, so please don't make personal attacks. 
</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cfatvee</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>I just find it hard to have a discussion with people who don't understand basic concepts such as: Morality can never be discussed in a vaccuum, as it is never absolute, and is always contextual, circumstantial, and ever changing based on new developments. Morality evolves. 

This is why Ayn Rand is one of the worst human beings to ever live. Her absolutism poisoned a generation.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfatwss</id>
<replies>
    <author>rajeshsr</author>
    <ReplyBody>uh! Seriously, this is completely uncalled for. Even Kant had notion of moral absolutism. Moral absolutism(which i don't subscribe to, as such) is a legitimate theory. You are just talking as if your morality is a religion, especially calling the OP as 5 year old and all. What is obvious to your line of thought need not be to others. That's the point of CMVs, in general -- to make people see the world you see. Your rudeness serves nothing.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cfau2cd</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<replies>
    <author>WolfChrist</author>
    <ReplyBody>You don't believe that morality is absolute. That doesn't make it so. Morality is subjective. Some believe it to be absolute, some don't. You don't get to make universal statements about concepts that are deeply personal and, in your own words, subjective. 

Do I like Ayn Rand? No. Do I have some absolute moral views? Yes. I think that everyone does at some level, regardless of context. 

EDIT: Universal, not unilateral. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cfau2wq</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>9</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>eLinguist</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;That's uncalled for. I'm not trying to attack you, so please don't try to attack me.

Well you sorta tried to pull that over his response and he pointed it out because it was very obvious, I didn't see it as a personal attack. 

Anyways, I also find it difficult to talk to people who are very set with their views in morality like this because it's very akin to how some religions set moral standards because it doesn't make *sense* most of the time when you use logic and think about it. To be honest you can't compare the lives of someone who wants to die, someone who arguably deserves to die and something that is arguably not a person.

&amp;gt;I'm prolife for my own reasons. 

If you are prolife, then you are PRO LIFE. Most people aren't prolife, they are PRO BIRTH. They think that at all costs that thing in the mum's stomach should have the highest priority over something that is actually a person/sentient and not just a lump of cells. (Of course this also depends where along the pregnancy we're talking about IMHO)

Pro birth = Should be born even if the mum's life is in danger

Pro life = Pro birth + the raising of the child

I just wanted to touch on the difference between pro life/birth because way to many "moral" people think they are pro life but in reality they are pro birth and don't give a flying fuck about the kid after it's born, just look at the majority of the republican party and it's members. (This isn't meant to be offensive, I'm just pointing something very obvious that many people tend to overlook)

&amp;gt;If someone is a moral absolutist, you can't say they don't know what morality is. Their idea of morality differs from yours, but that doesn't mean that they don't grasp the concept.

You are 100% right, but the problem here lies that each situation *needs* to be treated differently. If you treat each situation the same with an unwavering stance, especially without logic, then that's literally insane.

You cannot quantify and compare the lives of people already living to a lump of cells/the potential of life. You also cannot compare the life of someone who has destroyed lives of some to someone who wants to die and the potential of life, especially when there's a chance that the potential of life can potentially not even work out or kill the mother.

But this is just my 2 cents.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfaw8ph</id>
<upvotes>5</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>binaryhero</author>
                        <ReplyBody>You say "you can't definitely prove that [a] fetus won't survive childbirth" - that is factually incorrect. There are a number of conditions where the non-survival of a fetus outside the mother's womb can be determined before birth. The other way around is true though, in that you cannot establish with certainty that any fetus will survive childbirth (or the mother, sadly).</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfauuj1</id>
                        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Momentumle</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Would you also say that a murder in cold blood and one in self-defense are the same? They both live up to your criteria, if the relevant fact is that there is one less human being in the world. It seems from your argument that if we accept one as okay, then we have to accept both as okay. Is this a fair representation of your view? If not, why not?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfatu61</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>WolfChrist</author>
                            <ReplyBody>To be honest, this is a difficult one. 

From my viewpoint, a death is a death. If you are in a situation of self-defense where you are forced to kill your assailant, then that's what happens and it is up to the jury in your trial to determine whether it was right or wrong. 

I honestly don't have a good answer to this, and you've definitely made me think about this from a different angle. I'll either edit this post (or reply to your reply) after I've thought it through a bit more. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cfatwux</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>pppppatrick</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; There isn't one less human being in the world if you have an abortion. You can't definitively prove that any fetus would actually survive childbirth. It's the difference between a potential life and a life spent in prison.

Your argument could have ended at the there isn't one less human being portion. If you don't consider 1 week old fetuses as humans you've already have a viewpoint which is justifiable. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cfb49qe</id>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>13</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>25</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>AnonForSenate</author>
        <ReplyBody>What if you don't consider abortion taking a human life? For example one could believe that a sperm/egg combination is only "fully human" after a certain amount of time (maybe once it is self aware or something).

So if you believed that killing self-aware humans is always wrong then you'd be left to conclude that some kinds of abortions are okay and killing criminals is wrong.

I'm not saying I believe that, just that someone could believe that without contradicting themselves.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfatow7</id>
        <replies>
            <author>WolfChrist</author>
            <ReplyBody>The thing is, regardless of what level of 'human' you consider a fetus, if left to its own devices its going to become a human. So, even if the fetus isn't considered a human life, it will become one. Abortion prevents that life from ever occurring. 

Again, I stress that I'm not arguing for or against abortion. I'm only arguing that both it and the death penalty result in a net loss of human life, and therefore you cannot support one while objecting to the other. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfatrtx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>binaryhero</author>
                <ReplyBody>No, it will not become a human 'if left to its own devices'. It requires the support of the mother's body. There are very few instances where we grant an existing life rights over another person's body, e.g. we don't even give the already viable and living (people in need of organs) rights over the dead (potential donors that haven't agreed to donate), much less the potentially, non viable like fetuses. This argument only comes up for abortion.

As for the death penalty, there is no connection between the two issues.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfatyzf</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>WolfChrist</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Granted, my phrasing was poor, but my meaning was clear. 

You make an interesting point, though, with: "This argument only comes up for abortion." Though not on topic, it's interesting to me that we have such a distinction between the rights of the dead and the rights of the unborn. 

"As for the death penalty, there is no connection between the two issues."

I've previously made my argument for why I consider the two connected, so can I ask you to elaborate as to why you don't think they are? </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cfau20w</id>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>9</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>AnonForSenate</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; So, even if the fetus isn't considered a human life, it will become one. 

Not in the case of abortion. If the fetus is aborted it will not become a human life. And if you consider it not-yet-human then no loss of human life has occurred. This is different from capital punishment which does unambiguously end a human life.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfatx14</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>WolfChrist</author>
                    <ReplyBody>If you do not consider a fetus a human life, you at least consider it a potential human life. A fetus that could potentially (and equally) become the next great humanitarian, leader, or tyrant. A fetus has almost unlimited potential in terms of the possibilities of its existence. A convicted murderer, while still in possession of vast potential, does not have those possibilities. I'm too old to ever be an Olympic athlete. Similarly, a convicted felon will never not be a convicted felon. There are still an almost infinite number of things I could do with my life, and so can the felon, but there are some things that neither of us will ever be. 

The fetus has no such limitations. At the risk of hyperbole, how much progress has been slowed or lost because a mother aborted the next great physicist or politician? </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cfau0bz</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>AnonForSenate</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Well at least you know that hyperbole is your problem…

Someone who doesn't exist has unlimited potential. But there is literally infinite people who don't exist. That's why it doesn't matter if we prevent them from coming into existence. There are infinite people who don't exist.

We are passed the point where our species needs to make as many babies as possible. We're at a point now where we can choose to have children if we want. We tend to give those children an excellent shot at doing anything they want with their lives. That's more important than trying to win genetic dice-rolls to get the next Einstein.

Our societies probably produce geniuses more because we have clean water, safe neighbourhoods and good universities rather than luck of birth. It's not a numbers game of producing as many children as possible. It's a game of making society a great place to raise children.

This has gotten a bit off topic though. To get it back on topic, we don't consider things that aren't human as having rights. Just because something may become human one day doesn't have to change that (this can depend on your morality) but the CMV is just about whether it is justifiable to pro-choice (for abortion) and against the death penalty at the same time. And it is.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfau67v</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>WolfChrist</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Hmm...I think you've given the best argument to CMV by far, because you've definitely made me rethink my argument. 

Honestly, I've come to objectively agree with you. Looking at it as impartially as I can, you've changed my view. 

However, it still feels wrong to me to be pro-choice and anti-death penalty. I would need to think about it further, but right now it just strikes me as wrong. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cfau7r2</id>
                            <replies>
<author>AnonForSenate</author>
<ReplyBody>You don't have to think abortion or the death penalty is right. For your view to be changed you just have to think that someone who is pro-choice and against the death penalty *could* be justified in that set of beliefs.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfau9nv</id>
<upvotes>4</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>Momentumle</author>
<ReplyBody>I think a lot of this boils down to what it means to be a moral agent, worthy of moral consideration. I assume that you are not a strict vegan who won’t even take penicillin, because killing anything is wrong. Some things are worth more than others. So we need a way to deferinciate what life is valuable and what is not.

The most standard definition of a moral agent is: A rational being, who can reason and form self-interested judgments. (more or less). I am reading your argument bit Kantian, being able to place morality in a vacuum and focus on potential **human** life. Is this a fair assessment?

A fetus cannot be described as an agent, since it lacks agency in every possible meaning of the word. 

You can’t really assign value to the potential of future persons you are talking about (great physicist or politician) without leaving the vacuum and dipping your toes in a bit of utilitarianism. or at least have to shell out a good reason why its okay to look outside the vacuum in this case.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfaulim</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>11</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>pppppatrick</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; you at least consider it a potential human life

potential human life =/= human life

Same reason why facebook at 2003 isn't worth billions because potential does not equal worth. It **has** worth, but not as an already existing thing.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfb4chb</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ChappedNegroLips</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Chances are that aborted fetus isn't going to be missed because most abortions are unwanted children in the first place aka "future criminals". I just also want to say, I understand your argument but "potential human life" just isn't the same as an actual "human life". One is conscious the other isn;t.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfau2rw</id>
                        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>BenIncognito</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The thing is, regardless of what level of 'human' you consider a fetus, if left to its own devices its going to become a human.

If you remove a fertilized egg from a mother,  does it become a baby?

Fetuses require nine months (give or take) of *constant care* by another human. Don't pretend that fertilization is the only think necessary for a baby.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfav0cd</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>astrangefish</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Abortion prevents that life from ever occurring. 

 Me not having sex on a particular day at a particular time with a particular person also prevents life from ever occurring. A fetus doesn't even have a consciousness until "between the 24th and 28th week of gestation." (http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/when-does-consciousness-arise/)

 A man or woman who can suffer physically and mentally and has relationships and is actually alive in all the ways "alive" can be defined is worth more, to me, than "potential." It's the difference between is and isn't. A fetus isn't. A person is. A person is not just a body, a person is someone who loves and feels and thinks. A fetus is not equivalent to a person. A fetus doesn't even perceive itself to exist. It can't want for existence. It does not know what Red Lobster Cheesy Biscuits are. If it did, if it knew what Red Lobster Cheesy Biscuits were, I'd be pro-life. You might say I'm denying nothing the chance to be something-- but nothing doesn't care. It's nothing! </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfb10de</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfatudq</id>
        <replies>
            <author>stipulation</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; "Potential" means roughly "existing in the Void, at least from the current temporal perspective". There's zillions of humans that will never be pulled from the Void.

To follow up on this idea, every time a man and a women meet and do not have unprotected sex the a potential human stops existing. Sure an abortion stops a potential human from existing, but no more than using condoms for a year does.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfavbh2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>type40tardis</author>
                <ReplyBody>I once tried to calculate the number of "potential" babies that will never be born. Found out how many sperm a man produces in his lifetime and how many eggs women are born with. 

I got an overflow error. The number of possibilities is orders of magnitude larger than the number of atoms in the universe.

This whole premise is bullshit. It's unbelievable that an ostensibly adult person cannot for the life of him understand the difference between a nonsentient, nonsapient bundle of cells and a human being with an actual life.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfb07cf</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>heelspider</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I acknowledge that the death penalty in our actual world is highly flawed, but I do not believe this is because of the idea itself. 

If spitting on children gave them super powers, in an ideal world, I'd support spitting on children.  Why does it matter if someone supports a false ideal?

&amp;gt; Rather, I believe the flaws of the system are a result of human error, which means they are correctable.

Well, one of the flaws of the system is that we can never know with 100% certainty that suspects are guilty.  That's not simply a problem of human error, unless you call an inability to be omniscient a human flaw.  

Of course, another flaw of the death penalty is that it requires the government to kill people.  Is that the result of the human error that we're not immortal?

&amp;gt; I think that abortion, regardless of when performed, robs a potential human being of its life. 

Not having unprotected sex every opportunity robs a potential human being of its life.  Are you suggesting we all quit modern society and do nothing but have mass orgies all day long to ensure that all potential for human life is met?

&amp;gt; Furthermore, a fetus is innocent of any crime

My broken chair is innocent of any crime also.  Am I a bad person for throwing it away?  I don't understand assigning moral blame to something without some level of consciously functioning brain.

I'd turn it around on you.  I don't understand people who claim to be "pro life" but also support the death penalty.  I mean, what does it mean to be pro life and pro killing people?  What does the death penalty accomplish that a life sentence in a super-max prison does not?  Only a barbaric sense of blood lust.  If you have a hard on for killing people, don't call yourself pro-life.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfawhg1</id>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>5510</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Whether you think that a fetus is a human being or not, it is a living mass of tissue that, without intervention, would become a human being with all of the possibilities of happiness and life that we all have.    
    
Honestly, I think this is the part of your view that, at least for now, most needs to change.  There isn't really a way to logically support it.  It's one thing to count the fetus as a person, and that's certainly up for debate.  But you can't really say "even if it's not a person, it's still a potential person."  If you try and start assigning rights to "potential people" it get's ridiculous pretty quickly.     
     
I mean by that logic, every year that a fertile woman spends not being pregnant "robs a potential human of life."  I mean if I'm alone at work with a fertile female co-worker, and we don't have unprotected sex, you could make the same argument that we "robbed a potential human of life."  And even if you do have sex, if a person is made up of a unique sperm / egg combo, then even the act of creating a fetus means millions (billions?) or potential people just missed out on life, because of all the potential sperm / egg combos just from that one sex which missed out.  It's already a basic fact of life than only an astronomically miniscule % of "potential human beings" ever actually become humans.    
    
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sqsmlFjkAu0&amp;amp;t=1m12s    
    
I mean if I seriously believed what you just said, about preventing a potential human life being akin to killing a human, I would go out and start raping girls as often as possible.  Yeah, that's terrible for them, but it's not as bad as killing people, and if I don't knock them up somehow, potential human lives will go to waste.   
    
You could say the difference is "without intervention," but I don't see how that matters.  It's still not a person yet, so I don't see how you can compare it to the death penalty actually killing a human being.  I also don't agree it's accurate to say "without intervention," as huge amounts of intervention from the mother's body are still required for it to grow and live.
    
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfazbm9</id>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>"By supporting abortion, but not the death penalty, I think someone is justifying one denial of life but not the other."

Why is this a bad thing? I'd argue it's the basis of our justice system. I believe it is okay for a police officer to shoot a criminal who poses an immediate danger to others; I do not believe it is right for a criminal to shoot an officer arresting him. I believe it is right for a woman to kill a rapist in self-defense; I do not believe it is right for the rapist to kill the woman. And so on.

There is nothing wrong or unjustifiable in conditionally defining denial of life (it is acceptable to kill in this case but not in this case). Almost every legal or moral framework in history has allowed for it.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb0wyn</id>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>svalbard5</author>
        <ReplyBody>Your argument depends on the several points which aren't correct.

First, that abortion is ending an actual life as opposed to preventing a life from happening.  Those are two very different concepts.  A fetus is not an adult human being.  It is not autonomous.

Second, that the opposition to the death penalty has to do with putting someone to death.   Most people who oppose the death penalty will first point out that we have executed INNOCENT people.  We know we've done it.  I suspect we've known BEFORE HAND and still done it.   Even if you support the death penalty you should agree that using it to execute the wrong person is not a good idea.

Additionally, anti-death penalty people will point out that it is applied WILDLY disproprotionately to blacks over whites... for the same crimes.  A black man who kills a white man is MANY TIMES more likely to get teh death penalty than a white man who kills a black man.   Even if you support the death penalty, you should agree that it should apply evenly across the board.

Lastly, the 3rd major reason to be against the death penalty is about cost effectiveness.  It's REALLY expensive to execute someone.  That's the same issue with abortion - it would be really expensive for this pregnancy to result in someone that I have to raise (or worse, to someone severely handicapped that I have to raise).</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb1jq6</id>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>r3m0t</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;  In the case of a death sentence (again, in an ideal), the victim has done something to warrant the sentence. They have broken the rules of the society they live in so severely that they cannot be allowed to have any further part of that society.

&amp;gt; By supporting abortion, but not the death penalty, I think someone is justifying one denial of life but not the other.

One denial of life (abortion) actually has benefits to people. They can choose to raise kids when they are ready instead of when biology says they should. The other has no benefit. You say, "They have broken the rules of the society they live in so severely that they cannot be allowed to have any further part of that society" but this assertion is completely unjustified. What do I, or "society", care whether a criminal is killed or not? I think life imprisonment is an adequate way of removing somebody from society.

By the way, even a healthy pregnancy is riskier than an abortion (in terms of the chance of the mother dying). There's no such thing as a "safe" pregnancy. So when you want people to forgo abortions, you are asking people to decrease their chances of living due to a biological happenstance.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfavg31</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>awa64</author>
        <ReplyBody>Many people don't believe an embryo composed of human cells qualifies as a human life yet.

&amp;gt;Whether you think that a fetus is a human being or not, it is a living mass of tissue that, without intervention, would become a human being with all of the possibilities of happiness and life that we all have.

I'm pretty sure the life support and nutrients provided by a woman carrying a pregnancy to term qualifies as "intervention."

---

Supporting abortion means not requiring women to bring pregnancies to term that would ultimately rely upon state assistance programs for financial support.

The death penalty is also financially irresponsible. Due to the additional burden of proof placed upon the state, and the additional automatic grounds for appeal, prosecuting for and administering the death penalty will often cost 8x as much as merely convicting for life in prison w/o parole.

From a purely pragmatic standpoint, being pro-abortion and anti-death penalty is easily internally consistent.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfaysn1</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>rocqua</author>
        <ReplyBody>The relevant difference between an abortion and the death penalty is the danger behind the justification.

Abortions justification is really hard to extend to other things. Because few things are like fetuses. There's also the fact that abortion is generally a wholly rational impulse, and is certainly not 'aimed' at the baby.

In this sense, abortion's degradation of the right to live is very limited. It's limited pretty much to abortion itself.

Now compare this to the death penalty. The death penalty is basically stating that, in severe cases, death can be an appropriate punishment. That some-one can lose their right to life by their own actions.

This degrades the right to live much more because the lines are easily blurred. There's also the fact that the death-penalty is a very emotional impulse. It's about vengeance, retribution. As such, introducing the death-penalty can make much more people feel like killing is ok. It harms the 'sanctity of life' much more than abortion. This also has to do with fetuses just being a lot different from people. You don't see them, can't communicate with them etc. This makes it lot harder for people to extend their feelings about abortion to life in general.

Finally I'd like to address abortion itself. Now, I am in favor of women's right to abortion. Not sure if I'd be happy if a women were to abort a baby of mine, or if I'd suggest abortion if I'd have a baby now (I'm most certainly not ready for babies).  
all that said,  
I think that a fetus isn't a full human. It has none of the characteristics that make me care about a person. It doesn't communicate, doesn't interact, doesn't do. Given these things it's probably not very conscious of anything. As such, should it not come to term. I do not consider that the death of a human. It's a tragedy when the parents wanted a child. But because they have been denied something. It's worse to let a child come to parents that can't/won't care for it than it is for a fetus not to come to term.
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfaz7rc</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; To be clear, I'm referring to both in a vacuum and as ideals.

You simply cannot do this with morality. Morality pretty much always depends on context of some sort.

&amp;gt; I think that abortion, regardless of when performed, robs a potential human being of its life.

Potential human != human. Furthermore, one could make a perfectly consistent argument that wasting sperm and egg cells rob potential human beings of their life.

&amp;gt; it is a living mass of tissue that, without intervention, would become a human being with all of the possibilities of happiness and life that we all have.

This is simply not true. There is not a 100% chance that a fetus will be born successfully. Complications in pregnancy exist. Given that complications in pregnancy are definitely a reason as to why some people might get an abortion, you cannot ignore them to make your point. Also, nobody has all of the possibilities of happiness and life, Mr. Wayne, billionaire. Many people are born with developmental defects. Many mothers are substance abusers, which often causes negative outcomes on their babies. Should those babies get automatically aborted? No, it should be the choice of the mother, and her alone.

Given that it is not true that, excluding abortion, all fetuses will become human, and that this fact is also true for both sperm and egg cells, your "potential for life" argument rests on the probability of a "potential human" becoming human. Because of that, you are going to have to provide calculations of such probability and a detailed reason to make a specific cut in probability as to when the probability of a "potential human life" will become human life. If you can't do that, then your argument is invalid.

The death sentence has nothing to do with abortion, as abortion is not done as punishment against a fetus.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb2sx1</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>USSGoliath</author>
        <ReplyBody>There is so many reasons to have an abortion. "Abortion is done for two reasons: either the Mother doesn't want the child or she can't safely have the child." This does not count for all.
Children with displaced chromosomes will come up "retarded". They would never know what life is as they will be a drain to society. Also, many families are broken up because the care for retarded kids are impossible if you are not rich. There are many stories where the woman will have to stay home and would wish the child would die already.  

Impregnate a woman so she has to stay with you for the sake of the baby. Nope. I would rather my mom aborted me if that was true.  

Rape babies. 

Crack babies. 

It is not that the mother doesn't want the child. In some cases, the bad outweighs the good.

  
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb7bby</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>rajeshsr</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; By supporting abortion, but not the death penalty, I think someone is justifying one denial of life but not the other.

hmm, quite recently i started a CMV, where i argued that we should allow euthanizing of kids, if we allow abortion (http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/1whz3u/taking_prochoice_a_bita_lot_further_cmv/).

In particular, i see abortion from a social-contract viewpoint. I don't subscribe to abortion in the sense that baby is a parasite, living inside mom's womb. I see abortion as a mechanism to not entering a social contract with the society that you take up the responsibility of bringing up a kid who will be a responsible citizen of man-kind. And when you enter a contract, it is only fair that you are given some opportunity to see whether you are capable of executing the terms of such a contract. 

Given this view of abortion, treating death penalty and abortion along the same lines is completely moot. So, both the stances -- supporting or not death penalty while supporting abortion is possible as the foundation of reasoning is different.

Personally, I am very unhappy with the current prison system. Rehabilitation is not as paramount as it must be. But things are a lot better than (say) 200 years and we will improve more. In particular, most "sane" criminal are victims of the society. They have lost faith in humanity. It's humanity's turn to restore faith in it, with a genuine attempt at rehabilitation.  As far death penalty itself, i see it as the last resort, mostly as an euthanization mechanism. For example, if the person in question is like Joker from Batman, who after a few "genuine" attempts(which is not happening very well currently) at rehabilitation, shows no sign of change, then may be his brain is hard-wired to be a serial-killer, in which case it may be in society's interest to kill him. But, no, i am not enthusiastic about that. It may be a slipper-slope problem altogether, when we start supporting death, for such cases. But euthanasia may in these cases may be a necessary evil. I hope neurology progresses to such an extent that we will be able to cure such mental disease in future, making the need for this "euthanizing" death penalty moot.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfau88p</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>binaryhero</author>
        <ReplyBody>You have not established the connection, that is what I pointed out. You assert the connection, but that is not the same as actually demonstrating it. Your argument is poorly constructed.

Abortion is a question of a woman's rights over her body (medical emergencies aside, which are even more obvious to decide). The death penalty is a question of society's rights over a person's life, among other aspects that would need to be shown (for instance, that it can be an appropriate response, as you claim, for serious crimes; you seem to be under the assumption the arguments against death penalty are based on practical problems rather than foundational). One deals with stopping support for a potentially viable, completely dependent life; the other deals with taking the life of an independent, existing person. Many implications on the living differ too.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfausqj</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>reetpetite101</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why is it always people barely out of childhood who have the most extreme views on family planning and terminations ? Grown adults have the choice whether to become parents or not. And as for adoption if the people concerned dont want to go down that route its their choice. People who cant have kids, get one from somewhere else, dont use other peoples misfortunes as a vehicle to parenthood.

The death penalty and abortion are 2 separate issues, when you have a 100% perfect justice system debate the death penalty. That wont happen in mine, yours or your grandkids lifetime</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfavhza</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NameAlreadyTaken2</author>
        <ReplyBody>Using birth control may rob a human of its potential to live. How is this different from abortion of a fetus that is not yet consciously aware?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfax2fc</id>
        <replies>
            <author>type40tardis</author>
            <ReplyBody>Worse yet, the body naturally aborts a non negligible number of fertilized eggs with no intervention whatsoever. Hilariously, using the pill stops many of these eggs from being fertilized, and thus stops the body from aborting them. The people against abortion and against birth control really don't have a leg to stand on.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfb0b5g</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>jerry121212</author>
        <ReplyBody>Abortion serves a purpose, the death penalty doesn't. That's why I support only abortion. First of all, while I agree an abortion stops a life from happening, I don't think a fetus is actually alive at that point. Either way, a mother should never be forced to carry a child and give birth to it. I don't think potentially ruining one person's life is worth allowing another life. Honestly though, whether or not abortion should be allowed is a separate issue. All I really want to say is that they're not the same. Abortion, whether or not it's okay, undeniably serves a purpose. The death penalty doesn't accomplish anything that life in high security prison doesn't, aside from making people feel better I guess. But I really don't think we should be killing people because it makes us comfortable. It's just bitter cold blooded revenge. Personally it doesn't even make me happy to know killers and rapists were given the death penalty. It doesn't change the fact that what they did happened. It doesn't solve anything. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfaxwx1</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NinjaPointGuard</author>
        <ReplyBody>What if I'm against the death penalty because it's more expensive than life in prison?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfayy22</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>linxiste</author>
        <ReplyBody>Now I'm pro choice and I think that (given a high enough standard of proof) the death penalty is justifiable. However, I hold these views for entirely different reasons.

In the case of abortion, I see the point as to whether or not it is a human life arbitrary and irrelevant. The crux of the issue is whether or not there is legal or moral precedence to require a person to go through something that is as invasive, dangerous and emotionally trying as a pregnancy to save someone else's life.

I agree with the death penalty because prisons drain resources and people who are incarcerated for life have very little to lose and are thus a threat to prison security.

I don't hold these views because I think death is generally great thing, I don't think anyone does. I hold these views because I think they are beneficial to society and the individuals within it.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb41cx</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>blacktrance</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I think that abortion, regardless of when performed, robs a potential human being of its life.

Saying it robs a potential human being of its life implies that it has a right to life. This needs to be proven - it's not enough to just say that it would have become a person if there were no intervention.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb5jq1</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Unholyhair</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;By supporting abortion, but not the death penalty, I think someone is justifying one denial of life but not the other.

That may be a bit of an oversimplifcation, but true. That does not logically flow into your post title, though. Just because one supports the denying of life in one case but not the other does not make the view "unjustifiable". Arguing as such presupposes that the crux of the issue lay in whether or not denying life is morally justifiable.

This is not the case. For many, maybe even most, there are always situations in which taking life a is acceptable. Likewise, there are situations in which it is not acceptable. It is a matter of context.

To my mind, a mother is no more obligated to support a child than a stranger is to pay for another's life support. Whether or not a human (or potential human) dies in the process is irrelevant. I believe that banning abortion is to force a human being to care for and support another human being against their will.

On the other hand, I do not support the death penalty. It is extremely expensive. It would be much cheaper to simply incarcerate someone for life. Furthermore, if they are innocent (and it is not unheard of for this to be the case), then a human being was killed in revenge for a crime that they did not commit. Finally, in banning the death penalty, it isn't even as if all of those who were sentenced to death would simply go free. They would be imprisoned for life, which still removes them from society.

To reiterate, your argument assumes that they only reason someone might not support the death penalty is because they believe that killing people is wrong. Furthermore, it assumes the only reason that someone might support abortion is if they do not care about the (potential) human life being lost. This is not necessarily the case. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb6afz</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>berrieh</author>
        <ReplyBody>For your view, you have to see an embryo as a person. Biologically, I would argue it is not. Thus, there's the argument. 

If we must make it a person for an analogy (which I think is still wrong... Thus THIS analogy still bad) I would compare an embryo or unviable (without host) fetus more to someone on life support than to a death row inmate. If a person was required to physically give a body part, like a kidney, against their will to a person in order for that person to live, it might be a comparison (though different as a person and a potential are not the same, as others say... But no need to further that argument as it's articulated elsewhere). I'd also be against that. 

Also, "because life" is not the only argument against the death penalty. Other arguments include the financial and the imperfection of our legal society. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb76pk</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Decay153</author>
        <ReplyBody>The difference is in the players: the actor and victim of each procedure.  A person who holds the idea that an early developed fetus is not yet a being and therefore has no natural right to life gives a mother -an actor who is intimately involved in pregnancy- options that may result in termination of the fetus.  The situation is seen as a woman making an intimate choice over her body/the fetus before many believe the fetus is near "life" or natural rights.  The flip side is the idea that the state can determine a criminal has lost their right to live.  This person, while usually guilty of a crime, is undoubtedly in possession of some "right to life" and people are uncomfortable with the state making that choice when life in prison is a fully viable option.

Essentially it's the idea that (1) a fetus at some point is not advanced enough for the right of life (2) a woman can thus make a choice to end a pregnancy during this period. (3) every born human possesses a right to life and (4) the state should not remove that right even through the judicial system.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfb78qw</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>kairisika</author>
        <ReplyBody>If you believe that a human being has no rights until it is a human being, and the point of abortion is before that point, then it's easy to say that you may not kill a human being (as per death penalty), but abortion does not kill a human being, and is thus irrelevant to that issue.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfblvkj</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>GringoDeMaio</author>
        <ReplyBody>One way to look at this is as a question of body autonomy. That is one of the most fundamental rights a person can have: to determine what may or may not be done to their own body. 

A foetus cannot survive independently of it's mother, and so forcing a woman to carry a child to term necessarily involves sacrificing her body autonomy. It's saying "you have no choice as to what happens to your body; this potential person is depending on you and without you, they'll die." If we're going to go down that road due to the sanctity of life, we could just as well say that blood donation or even kidney/bone-marrow donation are mandatory. If we did this, we'd save lives. But we don't, because as a society we hold body autonomy to be a fundamental principle. We take this so seriously even after death that we require consent to harvest organs. A corpse is not even a living thing but we won't violate its autonomy to save the lives of actual living people.

If we had the means to take a foetus and bring it to term outside the mother's body, then and only then can I support a ban on abortion.

Now on to capital punishment. Again, body autonomy is a relevant factor here. Life imprisonment is in some cases a necessary thing due to the danger that someone poses to society, but no matter how heinous their crime, I am against capital punishment because once they are locked up there is simply no purpose served by taking their life. Violating something as sacrosanct as someone's physical ability to go on living is not, in my view, a justifiable way to punish them. Further, even if you could convince me that this person deserves it, I would still be against the death penalty for the following reason (previously given in another thread):

My reason for being against the death penalty isn't about the criminal, or the victim, or the facts of the case. It's about me. I don't want to kill someone. And if a society I'm part of does kill someone, I'm complicit in that. I don't want it done in my name. I'm all for meeting an active threat with force, even deadly force. But once someone is in custody, in a box, under the complete control of society, the thought of marching them to a room, strapping them to a chair or gurney, and methodically taking their life makes me sick. I don't care if it's Hitler, Pol Pot or Hannibal Lector , because it's not them I'm concerned about. It's the rest of us.

I can reconcile the above with my stance on abortion because in the case of abortion that foetus is not autonomous. It cannot live outside its mother's womb, and forcing her to carry the child to term violates her fundamental right to her own body.

And that is why I can be both anti-death penalty and pro-choice.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfbvtae</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>To be clear, I'm referring to both in a vacuum and as ideals. That is, I mean the idea of the death penalty as the harshest possible sentence for a capital crime in a world where the person sentenced to death is always guilty of the accused crime. I acknowledge that the death penalty in our actual world is highly flawed, but I do not believe this is because of the idea itself. Rather, I believe the flaws of the system are a result of human error, which means they are correctable. 

Likewise, I'm referring to abortion in the sense of a safe, professional environment (in other words, no home/amateur abortions). 

I think that abortion, regardless of when performed, robs a potential human being of its life. Whether you think that a fetus is a human being or not, it is a living mass of tissue that, without intervention, would become a human being with all of the possibilities of happiness and life that we all have. Furthermore, a fetus is innocent of any crime or action that would make it deserve death. Abortion is done for two reasons: either the Mother doesn't want the child or she can't safely have the child. In either case, the child is not at fault (I don't think you can blame developmental/delivery complications on the fetus). 

The death penalty is a punishment for something that a society has deemed crosses a very specific line (like murder). In the case of a death sentence (again, in an ideal), the victim has done something to warrant the sentence. They have broken the rules of the society they live in so severely that they cannot be allowed to have any further part of that society. 

By supporting abortion, but not the death penalty, I think someone is justifying one denial of life but not the other.</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
