<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BruinsMurph</author>
        <ReplyBody>I am pro-choice because no one has the right to force a woman to carry a fetus to term and give birth to it. Period. End of story. 

My view has nothing to do with the moral/ethical/philosophical question of whether the fetus is a living a human being. Therefore any comparisons to my position on the death penalty are irrelevant.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qsy87</id>
        <replies>
            <author>scottevil110</author>
            <ReplyBody>While I am likewise pro-choice, I don't believe you can say that it has nothing to do with whether a fetus is a human being.  It's central to taking that stance.

It stands to reason that if you DID believe a fetus was a full human person, deserving of the same rights, then you would not have such a "Period. End of Story." opinion on the matter.  

After all, in no other case do we afford someone the right to take the life of another person (except in self-defense), so why would your position be different regarding abortion?

Again, I'm also completely pro-choice, but I'm not sure how you can say it has nothing to do with your view on the personhood of a fetus.  </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qy8l2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>z3r0shade</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; After all, in no other case do we afford someone the right to take the life of another person (except in self-defense), so why would your position be different regarding abortion?

Sure we do: pulling the plug on someone in a coma/vegitative state.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1r6avi</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>scottevil110</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Hmm, good point, although that's not very cut and dry.  In most cases, we require an advance directive that gives someone else the authority to make that decision, do we not?  </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1r6c3h</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>z3r0shade</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; In most cases, we require an advance directive that gives someone else the authority to make that decision, do we not?

That only matters in choosing who gets to make the decision. If there is no advance directive specifying the person's wishes, then the Next Of Kin is given the authority to make the decision on their own, which can include pulling the plug.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1r6q4x</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>scottevil110</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Good point, very good point.

However, to that I would counter that pulling the plug is not actively terminating someone's life.  It is removing life support, and letting their body shut down naturally.  It would be akin to delivering a fetus pre-term, and seeing whether it survives unassisted or not.

Abortion involves (whether you're for or against it, it's the truth) actively terminating it, not just letting it die.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1r6urd</id>
                            <replies>
<author>z3r0shade</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Abortion involves (whether you're for or against it, it's the truth) actively terminating it, not just letting it die.

To be fair, the term abortion simply refers to any termination of pregnancy before carrying it to term. Whether by inducing, actively terminating the fetus, or prematurely going in and removing it.

That being said, medical professionals can pretty easily tell whether a fetus has formed enough that it has even a chance to survive outside the womb until what is currently referred to as "viability" which is where it gets a bit hazy on whether or not it would survive. 

More than 98% of all abortions happen before the point that it would even be possible for it to survive outside of the womb. It seems ridiculous to differentiate between delivering it pre-term and actively terminating it when you can tell with certainty, in 98% of cases, whether it will survive if delivered pre-term. 

For that last roughly 1.2% of cases which take place after 20 weeks, I would argue that we *should* be delivering it pre-term and seeing whether it survives rather than actively terminating it if the doctors believe there is a chance it might survive. And in fact, in most states of the US you cannot get an abortion for later than 20 weeks.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1r7gil</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>I understand your view, and I want to be able to reach this point. The fetus depends on the woman's body, and thus, I believe she has the right to choose whether or not she has to continue carrying that fetus.

But at the same time, I worry because I don't know if I can objectively separate my moral/ethical views on whether a fetus is a living human being from my views on a woman's right to choose.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qt0w7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>sailorbrendan</author>
                <ReplyBody>It's the famous pianist argument. 

If there was a famous pianist that was very ill and needed to be physically connected to another person, to use that person as a dialysis machine.... can a person be forced to do that in order to keep the pianist alive? 

Can we mandate that one person operate as a life support system for another? 

If yes, ok. If no, abortions are legal. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qv0yq</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>mailmanofsyrinx</author>
                    <ReplyBody>What if the pianist's independence was compromised directly by the actions of some other individual? If that individual could save the pianist's life by being physically connected to them for 9 months, should the individual be expected to make this sacrifice?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qy1jo</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>z3r0shade</author>
                        <ReplyBody>The best example here I could give would be that if you stabbed someone in the lung, you still cannot be legally compelled to donate one of your lungs to them to save their life because we view autonomy to be that important. The same goes with say, donating blood. If you stab someone with a knife and are a compatible blood type, you still cannot be compelled to give them a blood transfusion in order to save their life.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1r69ld</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>sailorbrendan</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I'm sorry. .. I've read this a few times and am not sure I follow your argument.  Could you rephrase it?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qz0ec</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Yellow_Odd_Fellow</author>
                            <ReplyBody>If the pianists life is in jeopardy because of an action person a committed, could you justify person a being forced to keep the pianist alive?

Not the OP, and don't are with that stipulation but that is what they're trying to say.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1r4r7e</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Great, objective argument. Thank you! ∆</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qvmfu</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>jsl4f</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It's not really that great of an argument, the baby starts out connected to the woman, which is a critical difference. A similarly obfuscating example would be If you have conjoined twins, if one can decide to get a surgery that kills the other one unilaterally.  You could do the sciences determine whose body parts belong to whom, but the underlying issue is that one is dependent on the other similar to a fetus.  The given example of the pianist is very misleading.  The truth is there is nothing really comparable to pregnancy.  It is a unique situation.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1rgi0f</id>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>11</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>BruinsMurph</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;But at the same time, I worry because I don't know if I can objectively separate my moral/ethical views on whether a fetus is a living human being from my views on a woman's right to choose.

Well, there is no one objective "truth" with regards to this question. In the face of this uncertainty, I would argue the only just course of action is to favor maximum autonomy for the woman. Whatever an individual's belief on this matter, it is not a sufficient argument to coerce a woman into childbirth against her will.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qtj8b</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>∆ I agree on favoring the autonomy of the woman. They should have the choice to do what they will with their body. They can choose to have sexual intercourse, they should be able to choose whether or not to carry a fetus to birth, using their own body as a host.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qtq26</id>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>z3r0shade</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; But at the same time, I worry because I don't know if I can objectively separate my moral/ethical views on whether a fetus is a living human being from my views on a woman's right to choose.

The easy answer is that even if the fetus is a living human being with rights, it doesn't have the right for continued use of the woman's body without her consent. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1r6668</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>This is true, thank you</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1r76wm</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>RustyRook</author>
                        <ReplyBody>If a user has in some way changed your view, please feel free to award them a delta. You are allowed to award multiple deltas and partial deltas, too, if they've changed just one aspect of your view.

Instructions are in the sidebar - take a look at Rule 4. Thanks!</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1r7u4u</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>spenceast</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Thanks for the reminder, I'm responding to other redditors on mobile, so I'll be returning later to award deltas to those who helped me later tonight.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1r7xik</id>
                            <replies>
<author>RustyRook</author>
<ReplyBody>It's up to you how you do it but there *is* a way to easily award deltas on mobile.

Type "! delta" but without the space in between and include a couple sentences explaining how your view was changed. That's all it takes.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1r83hc</id>
<replies>
    <author>spenceast</author>
    <ReplyBody>Oh, I didn't know that, thanks!</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1r9j5i</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Hq3473</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;  am pro-choice because no one has the right to force a woman to carry a fetus to term and give birth to it. 

Do you think it should be OK for a woman to kill the fetus she is carrying one day before the due date, in a situations with no medical complications of any kind.

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qunkm</id>
            <replies>
                <author>BruinsMurph</author>
                <ReplyBody>Yes, I do. My reasoning is that there is no clear boundary. If we decide that it should not be permissible one day before the due date, then why not 2 days? 3? 4? 180? 

If we decide that it should be permissible with no medical complications then why not "merely" potential medical complications? Minor complications? Moderate complications?

In the absence of clear answers, I support maximum autonomy for the woman.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qvi3n</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Hq3473</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Is not a birth date an equally arbitrary line?

Would you support a right of the mother to kill a baby a day after birth?  What is the big difference with one day before birth and one day after birth?

That would square with maximal autonomy of the woman. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qvlue</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>BruinsMurph</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I would argue that birth is an unambiguous event rather than an arbitrary line. After birth there is no longer a fetus living in the woman but a human being living in the world.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qvvli</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Hq3473</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Bu that being is basically exactly the same on the day of birth as he was a day before.

Why was it OK to kill that being yesterday, but not today?

Sounds pretty arbitrary.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1qvz3h</id>
                            <replies>
<author>BruinsMurph</author>
<ReplyBody>It's not even remotely the same. After birth there is no longer a fetus living inside the woman.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1qw9p6</id>
<replies>
    <author>Hq3473</author>
    <ReplyBody>So?  Why does a physical location of the fetus matters?

Imagine a woman is giving birth. At which EXACT moment is it no longer OK to kill the fetus?

When the labor begins?  When only the head is out?  When the fetus is 50% out? 99% out? 

What is the difference? The being that is being born is pretty much the same.

How can you decide on life or death on such a narrow ground?  All of this sounds extremely arbitrary.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1qwj0g</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>6</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>leftkck</author>
                <ReplyBody>No, but that's because you would have to proactively kill it because it could survive outside the womb</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qv325</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Hq3473</author>
                    <ReplyBody>So, would you be OK with a woman inducing birth on 24th week of pregnancy for no medical reason?

The 23 week old fetus can probably survive, but will experience lifetime of health complications. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qvger</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>leftkck</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Yeah, if the doctors do what they can for the kid since it's their job.

I cannot be forced to give up a kidney, or lung, or any part of me to keep someone else alive. It's the same concept, just because there is an age difference people get all emotional about it.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qw5vn</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Hq3473</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I would say that if you deliberately PUT ME in a position where I need a kidney to survive you should be forced to donate a kidney to me, or at the very least pay for my dialysis forever or getting a kidney transplant from another source. 

Same reasoning should be applied to viable fetuses.   

Would you be OK with a woman who decided to induce on 23rd week old fetus being forced to pay for ALL medical expenses that the fetus will incur during his or her lifetime?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1qwakl</id>
                            <replies>
<author>leftkck</author>
<ReplyBody>But if people get in a wreck they don't force whoever was at fault to donate organs, do they?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1r16ey</id>
<replies>
    <author>Hq3473</author>
    <ReplyBody>I think they should. And at the very least they DO have to pay for medical treatment caused by the wreck.

I would be OK with a law that forced drunk drivers to donate (non essential) organs to the victim of a wreck they caused.

So, I repeat:

Would you be OK with a woman who decided to induce a 23rd week old fetus being forced to pay for ALL medical expenses that the fetus will incur during his or her lifetime due to premature birth?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1r19z4</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>4</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>29</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>3xtheredcomet</author>
        <ReplyBody>This is predicated on the assumption that abortion is murder. It appears that you believe this to be the case, and while there's nothing wrong with that, there's a bunch of people who don't think it's murder, especially for early-term abortions. 

You'll see a lot of people describe a fetus or embryo as "just a bundle of cells," and up to a point, they are right. Nobody (or rather most don't) bat an eyelash at the billions of sperm cells doomed to tissue rags, or egg cells lost in tampons. Even miscarriages, tragic as they are, are never thought of as murder either. 

The moment at which "a bundle of cells" is believed to become human life or attains personhood varies incredibly from individual to individual-- which is exactly why abortion is such a hotly contested issue-- but because some people really do consider it to start much later than others, in their eyes, abortion truly is not murder, no more unethical or immoral than other medical operations where "a bundle of cells" are removed and left to wither.

I can empathize with your internal struggles on this. Maybe it seems like these pro-choicers are just willfully ignoring their own cognitive dissonance and I don't doubt that some probably are. Still, I think that there are many who genuinely believe that at certain stages abortion isn't murder, and for them, it's both possible and logical that they can be anti-death penalty *and* pro-choice.

As far as crafting counterarguments for these folk, I'm not exactly versed in debate/rhetoric/argumentation, but a good start is to probe them on when they think life starts and then to press them on how ambiguous their position inevitably is. For example, if they use Roe v. Wade as a defense, which is predicated on viability (the chances that a fetus could survive outside the womb), emphasize that continually advancing medical technologies will only further narrow that window over time.

Emphasize how it's such a difficult moral quandary that the safe option is to simply assume it starts at conception. (And, if we allow ourselves a bit of near-future sci-fi, it shouldn't be long before a single zygote could be nurtured in a test tube to infanthood.)

If they defend it with brain activity or consciousness... well I'm not sure. Being such a complex organ, again, it's too difficult to even say when life starts and how and what kind of brain activity would qualify as attaining personhood. You may get caught in a god-of-the-gaps style reasoning, that our only limitation for understanding consciousness is purely due to limitations in neurobiology. However, unlike believing or not believing in evolution, *if they're wrong*, then abortion undeniably becomes murder and therefore, it's probably for the best to leave those gaps as they are until the scientific community figures out all the details.



</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qvls4</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>∆ This thread has helped me develop my views better, and your comment in particular was long and well-thought out. Thank you. I appreciate your empathy and I appreciate your explanation on the moral quandaries that follow trying to determine where or when life actually starts.

Also, thank you for your examples about the "bundle of cells" and the death of sperm cells or egg cells. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qvxfg</id>
            <upvotes>5</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>11</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>scottevil110</author>
        <ReplyBody>Pro-choice is exactly that.  Pro-CHOICE.  It doesn't mean pro-abortion.  It means leaving that choice up to the individuals involved.  That's what libertarianism is about.  The government staying out of your business and allowing you to do what YOU think is right instead of what **I** think is right. 

Regarding the death penalty, that's the government putting someone to death.  Ending the life of an unwilling person.  Even if you believe that a fetus is a full person with full legal rights, being pro-choice is not killing that person.  It's allowing someone else to make their own decisions.  

Then, of course, there is the remaining issue of just what counts as a "person".</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qsz63</id>
        <replies>
            <author>mailmanofsyrinx</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; It means leaving that choice up to the individuals involved. That's what libertarianism is about.

The golden rule of Libertarianism is the Non-Aggression Principle: "Every man is free to do that which he wills, provided he infringes not the equal freedom of any other man."-Herbert Spencer.

Abortion may infringe upon a fetus' natural right to life...
The fetus' natural right to life may infringe upon a mother's right to her body.

Of course, if you're a Libertarian, you have to make some decision about responsibilities. When is a parent expected to sacrifice their natural rights for their children?
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qypqo</id>
            <replies>
                <author>scottevil110</author>
                <ReplyBody>Which is why I say that your personal belief about the "personhood" of a fetus is central to your position on this.  If you don't believe that a fetus is a "person" entitled to the same status as a born person, then it's cut and dry, and obviously a woman's right to bodily autonomy wins.

But if you DO believe that a fetus is just as much a person as the woman, THEN you have a bit of a dilemma, because their respective rights are at direct odds with one another.  

One could say that said woman waived her right to autonomy when she allowed that fetus to be created in the first place. At some point, you HAVE to believe that you have a responsibility to that "thing" that trumps your natural rights to do what you want.  After all, we wouldn't say that you have a "right" to just let your children starve.

Not my personal belief, but I don't think it's unreasonable to see it that way.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qytqf</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think that last line is where I get hung up on.

I was having a little debate about this with two of my strict conservative friends last night: I told them that I am pro-choice, because I don't think the government should be involved in whether or not a woman has to carry a fetus to birth. I think that people should be able to do what they want to and they can live with and deal with the consequences themselves. 

Both of their arguments against my pro-choice view were along the lines of "murder" and they say that we might as well "legalize murder and just let it happen and let murderers deal with the consequences of their own actions". That's where I get hung up on this issue, I think.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qt5xv</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qtgdd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I think your claim about the mind being a key component of human life is spot-on. I especially liked your analogy about a man receiving a heart transplant not suddenly becoming two people.

&amp;gt; "the only reason life is even important is to facilitate the mind."

I agree. Your comment was helpful, thank you.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qtln6</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qubzr</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>spenceast</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Yes, i think this will help me with my future conversations.

Here, have a delta ∆</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1quixw</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1quve5</id>
<replies>
    <author>spenceast</author>
    <ReplyBody>I agree, it's hard to talk with people who are so set in their ways. 

When I was defending my stance as pro-choice to my conservative friends, one of them argued: "Well, the woman already *made* her choice! She *chose* to have sex in the first place. If she just wouldn't have had sex, she'd never be forced with the want to have an abortion." I just shook my head. It is frustrating to try and communicate objectively with people who are close-minded to the views of other people, or who don't want to put themselves in the shoes of another.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1qvs8d</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>elcuban27</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Counter-point: if a person is in a coma, do they lose personhood?  If they regain consciousness later, do they regain it?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1rgizg</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1rkxkf</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>elcuban27</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I think for us to be able to say that an unborn life *does not* have a mind, we have to at least know what level of mental activity is present during a coma and at various stages of development.  To fail to do so is to act out of ignorance to lethal effect.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1s7x7l</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1sridf</id>
<replies>
    <author>elcuban27</author>
    <ReplyBody>Do you know how early in development the nervous system starts to develop?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1sssqk</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>scottevil110</author>
                <ReplyBody>Well, this is a complicated issue, because it has no clear answer.  Whether or not a 15 week fetus is a "person" is entirely up to one's personal opinion, because science offers little in the way of a definitive answer.  It's up to what "counts" to you. 

And if you believe that that thing is a person, then it makes perfect logical sense to say that abortion is absolutely murder, and that it absolutely should be banned entirely.

The thing is...I can't tell them they're wrong.  We just disagree.  I certainly can't say that they're being illogical, because if, in your mind, that fetus is just as much a person as you or I, then it makes perfect sense to call it murder.  </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qt9ti</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Yeah, it is a very complicated issue. It boils down to each person's opinion and at that point I just kind of take the stance of "to each his own".</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qtcci</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>scottevil110</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Me too, which is exactly what "pro-choice" means.  But I honestly don't blame the pro-life people for thinking I'm deplorable for it.  The way they view things, being pro-choice IS pretty equivalent to saying that I really don't mind if people just murder each other in the streets.  

But I don't see my stance, even in THAT light, as being contradictory to being opposed to the death penalty.  Allowing people to make their own choices is very different than the state taking an active role in killing someone.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qtfxi</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>spenceast</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Thank you, I see your point. That is helpful. ∆</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1qti3e</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Clockworkfrog</author>
                <ReplyBody>Would these anti-abortion people call for criminal investigations of every miscarriage to determine whether or not the miscarriage was the result of intervention by the woman or not?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qti9f</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Great point! </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qtndq</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>elcuban27</author>
                <ReplyBody>Hmm.  I think that the points being directed towards you are being shaded a bit.  There is a lot of *opining* going on that say that the unborn is not yet a person and/or doesnt have rights and/or that a woman's right to choose supercede's the right to life (a very untenable argument in and of itself).  I think they arent giving you enough credit in how well your analogy holds up.  If the person on death row were instead allowed to live out the rest of their life in prison, this places a considerable burden on the taxpayer.  Why should the taxpayer be *forced* to either subsidize their continued existence, or allow them to run amuck?  If one values the life of a human being (even a heinous criminal) enough to take away society's ability to *choose* to terminate the guilty, then one could hardly justify the killing of the innocent (particularly when 99% of the time the one being killed is put into that situation not through any fault of their own, but from the decision [consensual sex] of **the very person who gets to decide to end their life**).  This would be more akin to dr evil offering for a homeless guy to stay for free at his evil lair that happens to be situated atop an active volcano with a helipad as the only means of egress, then raising the rent to one hundred million dollars and "evicting" him when he cant pay.  Since the homeless guy has no helicopter, he will be made to jump into the magma.  Now this isnt "murder" its just dr evil exercising his "rights" as a "landlord" to "evict" him into molten hot "magma."  Or, maybe dr evil should be made to provide safe transport himself or wait until such a time as the hobo is able to arrange for a chopper.  

Still, the whole argument hinges on the perceived moral value of the unborn; if they are "just a clump of cells," then its no big deal. The *real* and very piercing question is: if you *decide* to view it that way, are you being objective or merely interpreting it that way to abate your nagging conscience harping on about all that cognitive dissonance?  Given that textbook definitions of "human" and "alive" seem to imply valued personhood, what can we come up with to convinvlce ourselves otherwise?  Is it worth it?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1rel07</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>9</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NaturalSelectorX</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Because I argue with myself: "well, if a woman should have a choice to kill the fetus inside her, shouldn't anyone have 'the choice' the kill any other human being?"

The *only* reason a woman can kill the fetus inside of her is because the fetus is inside of her. Realistically, she's not "killing" the fetus so much as evicting it from her body. If there were an artificial womb, I'd fully support requiring fetal transplants instead of abortion. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qsw08</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>I agree with you about the artificial womb point. If that were the case, I would have no qualms with fetal transplants and I suspect many pro-lifers would be fine with it too.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qt211</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>redvblue23</author>
        <ReplyBody>I am against the death penalty because it is unnecessarily expensive and can lead innocent people to being executed.

I am pro-choice because I don't believe a fetus to be considered a human being. It's a clump of cells that slowly grows to be a person that will grow, walk, talk, etc.

The main sticking point for the abortion debate is whether you believe a fetus to be a human being that the killing of constitutes murder. 
I don't, so there's really no inconsistency in my death penalty and abortion beliefs. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qt38r</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>I guess I need to continue thinking about this and decide for myself what I believe a fetus to be.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qt9b4</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>forworkaccount</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I am against the death penalty because it is unnecessarily expensive 

What do you think about this viewpoint I have (might not be correct I'd like to hear an opinion about it)? When you're keeping someone in prison for life, they're wasting resources (you have to kept him fed). While legal fees for the death penalty is going to a lawyer, a functioning member of society, therefore the death penalty 'wastes' less money for society net overall.

&amp;gt; can lead innocent people to being executed.

I can't argue with this. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qvsb9</id>
            <replies>
                <author>redvblue23</author>
                <ReplyBody>Death penalty costs more than life imprisonment when accounting for costs like court time due to the appeals

http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/costs-death-penalty

http://www.forbes.com/sites/kellyphillipserb/2014/05/01/considering-the-death-penalty-your-tax-dollars-at-work/#494fe1c217f0

http://deathpenalty.org/article.php?id=42</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qy1ns</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>forworkaccount</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Yes I am aware of that. What I meant was, the fees goes to a lawyer, who is a functioning member of society. While keeping a prisoner alive is *literally* throwing taxpayer money down the shitter.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qzmrk</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>redvblue23</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Ah.

But what does it matter if the fees go to someone who is a functional member of society? By that standard, we could pay the lawyer to play Candy Crush for me. But that wouldn't be a good use of his time, therefore a waste of money.

Wasting time that could be better spent doing anything else is time that can't be brought back.

Also, by keeping a prisoner alive, you are paying multiple people to keep them there, who are all functional members of society.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1r1as6</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>forworkaccount</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; But what does it matter if the fees go to someone who is a functional member of society? 

Because the taxpayer is paying for these. I want to see parts of society benefiting from it.

&amp;gt; Also, by keeping a prisoner alive, you are paying multiple people to keep them there, who are all functional members of society.

Yes, but the food to upkeep an inmate is literally wasted. Society benefits zero from that. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1r1iyn</id>
                            <replies>
<author>redvblue23</author>
<ReplyBody>So is the work that a lawyer and judge have to do to execute someone. Society doesn't benefit from having someone killed; they're already out of society forever.

The more money that is used= the more money that could be spent elsewhere. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1r1s0z</id>
<replies>
    <author>forworkaccount</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Society doesn't benefit from having someone killed; they're already out of society forever.

Yes they do. They save money on having to spend resources of keeping somebody alive that will not give back to society.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1r1tfa</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MrGiggleBiscuits</author>
        <ReplyBody>The most obvious difference for me is that a fetus is not human. It has no higher thinking capabilities and it would be ridiculous to claim a single cell is a human, so the starting point of life cannot be conception. The fetus lives within the woman, and is entirely reliant upon her, while doing damage to her body. It is essentially a parasite, and so the woman should have the choice to not support it any more.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qt4az</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>I like the last line that you used:

&amp;gt; It is essentially a parasite, and so the woman should have the choice to not support it anymore. 

Curious, when do you believe the starting point of life to be?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qtb06</id>
            <replies>
                <author>MrGiggleBiscuits</author>
                <ReplyBody>I am not a qualified biologist, so I can't give an exact answer. The start point for life seems to be birth, as its the most straightforward answer and the clearest cut off point.

The question ends up similar to the old paradox about how many grains of sand are necessary to make a heap, there isn't a set point. I would say that late term abortions are probably less acceptable than early ones, since the fetus is more human, but from a legal perspective birth is the logical place to put it, with perhaps some restrictions on reasons for late term abortions.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qthmd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Safari_Eyes</author>
                    <ReplyBody>of course, looking at the actual statistics, late-term abortions are almost universally due to unexpected health complications for the mother or fetus, such as discovering that the fetus is horribly malformed and has little to no chance of life once it is born.

Oddly enough, women almost never go through months and months of discomfort and the hormonal and physical changes of pregnancy, only to change their minds at the last minute.  In fact, if abortion access was -easier-, more of them would happen even earlier in the process, in the first month or two at most.  Stupid abortion laws delay abortions, but they sure as hell don't stop them!   

Putting restrictions on "late-term abortions" only harms the would-be parents, who are often already devastated to discover that their -wanted- child has little to no chance at life, or may be critically endangering the mother and making her choose between her fetus and her own life. (and up until at least 26 weeks, the fetus is almost sure to die if removed, so the loss of the mother would likely mean the loss of both.)</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qudoa</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>MrGiggleBiscuits</author>
                        <ReplyBody>The restrictions I referred to would certainly not deal with cases where the fetus was unlikely to survive or where there is a serious risk to the mother. I only really suggested those as a conciliation to those who argue that the beginning of life is before birth. It's unlikely that they should be necessary, but it curbs fears of "baby killers" as the anti-abortion people would say.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qulhi</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Safari_Eyes</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Of course the beginning of "life" is before birth.  It's before conception, too!  Both the sperm and the egg are alive, and that unbroken chain of life goes back literally -millions- of years.

That's one of the things that gets me most about the "when does life begin?" debate.  It's an unbroken chain, not a series of sudden events, and the people who claim "life" begins after the fusion of egg and sperm are just picking an arbitrary point.  Something like half of fertilized eggs are spontaneously aborted, so if life begins at conception, that makes God (if S/He existed) into the most prolific abortionist in history!

We've got a perfectly good threshold to use instead - Birth.  At that point, the infant is no longer a parasite in the mother's body.  No more worries about the bodily autonomy of the mother, the infant can breathe and survive without using the mother's body.

</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1qvt04</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I agree with late term abortions being less acceptable, but birth is a very logical place to put it.

Liked your grains of sand into a heap analogy too. ∆</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qtn19</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>cramopener</author>
        <ReplyBody>Part of the issue comes down to whether or not you view a fetus/zygote/embryo as having the same moral weight as an already-born human. Usually, we look at this as the right of the human in the womb to live vs the bodily autonomy rights of the person carrying it. In this case, pro-choice people will typically rule in favour of the person who has already been born, which means it is a bit odd to say this contradicts anti death penalty views, as they also deal with the rights of people who are already born. It's also important to note that there are multiple reasons to oppose/support either issue, not all of which are about ethics. Someone could conceivably be pro-choice because they feel teen pregnancy has a negative effect on the national economy, and oppose the death penalty because it can cost more than prison.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qtq35</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>I heard an analogy that was something like: "Imagine that a hospital is on fire. There is a cooling container of 100 fertilized eggs and next to it, a three year old child. You only have time to save one, are you going to grab the 100 eggs or the living, breathing child, begging you for his life?"

I find it unbelievable that anyone would pick the fertilized eggs over an actual child in that situation, and I can connect that to being pro-choice as well. The woman's life is more valuable than the cells developing inside her womb.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qtv5p</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>dangerzone133</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'm pro choice because I believe we can't truly end oppression of women unless women have the right to control their reproductibe choices. And I know that in countries where abortion is illegal, women will still try and get abortions, and these illegal abortions are much more unsafe than an abortion obtained through a licensed physician. There are practical reasons to be pro choice that you can't ignore.

Ending the death penalty also has practical considerations for physicians, who ethically cannot give someone a lethal injection. This means that, again, we are having people who aren't well qualified, performing a medical procedure, which can have consquences. Here are some botched executions that have taken place:
http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/some-examples-post-furman-botched-executions

I'm against the death penalty because we can't guarantee them a quick and painless death. The botched executions are barbaric and not something I think has a place in the US. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qwjv2</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>renoops</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's important to remember that the legality of abortion isn't about a woman's right to kill a fetus, but a woman's freedom from being forced to keep it in her body. 

That said, I'm not sure the leap you're making between abortion and the death penalty make all that much sense. Why should we *have* to kill convicts simply because abortion is legal and he's locked up? I don't see the link between the two. 

You seem to be suggesting that we should put him out of his misery because he's locked up anyway, but being locked up for a long time is precisely the point: it's his punishment for having committed a serious crime.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qt0pq</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>That makes sense. I guess I just connected the two as in: a fetus is "trapped" inside a woman's body (though I understand that it's not there "as a punishment"), and a prisoner is "trapped" in prison. Neither really has much freedom. So isn't killing a prisoner taking away their right to life, just as much as aborting a fetus would be taking away that right as well?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qt8bk</id>
            <replies>
                <author>renoops</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;So isn't killing a prisoner taking away their right to life, just as much as aborting a fetus would be taking away that right as well?

Well, I think that the death penalty is wrong, but I think that abortion should be a legal option for women. 

I think that the death penalty should be abolished for a variety of reasons, including false convictions, lack of deterrent, and a general interest in humanity. It's true that convicts' rights are restricted, yes, but the thing about a fetus is that they don't have rights. The legality of abortion is actually a way of preserving the pregnant woman's right to her own body. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qtit2</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I agree with you, on all points. Thank you</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qto46</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>renoops</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I'm glad I could help! Care to grant me a delta if that's the case? </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1qts79</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>spenceast</author>
                            <ReplyBody>∆ Thanks again!</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1qtw6f</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Targren</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Can anyone help me understand how someone could be both pro-choice and against the death penalty? 

A murderer or traitor is already a person at the time the crimes are committed, so a moral prohibition against killing people is in play. If that person rejects the idea that "personhood begins at conception", then supporting the choice to have an abortion doesn't bring that same prohibition into context until after whatever point that person considers the fetus "a person". 

Alternately: A person may have no philosophical opposition to the death penalty, but also pragmatically recognize that their particular judicial system is too broken, corrupt, or incompetent to be allowed to make irreversible judgements. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qtanb</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>∆ Thank you for your alternate view and explaining how you can pragmatically recognize the incompetence of the judicial system.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qtdr3</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>DrWhiskeydick</author>
        <ReplyBody>Well, I think if you don't consider early term fetuses to be 'alive' then it makes perfect sense.  The struggle is convincing people that fetuses aren't alive and at what stage it's acceptable.  And that's a very tricky thing to do.

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1ququq</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>That is very tricky. I think for me, a fetus is not a human being because it does not have a mind of it's own. It doesn't think for itself, act for itself, or do anything for itself. It depends entirely on the woman during the pregnancy, and I don't think it's right to mandate that the woman do that.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1qvpg4</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Scolias</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; That is very tricky. I think for me, a fetus is not a human being because it does not have a mind of it's own. It doesn't think for itself, act for itself, or do anything for itself. 

Neither does a 2 year old. Should we abort them too?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1qxeav</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>spenceast</author>
                    <ReplyBody>They're already born, so an abortion would not be possible.

But I see your point.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1qy0tw</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>PaulyChirch</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I think the point has been lost, actually. Full mind development is not gained until after year 1 - memories, complex meaningful thought, higher functions. So until the mind develops, why wouldn't it be okay to end/kill/abort the "thing"?  After all, you can't be a human until you have a mind?  I ask as a thought experiment since almost all defenses to prochoice in the thread has hinged on when life starts. Which is a valid argument.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1r2rz4</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>spenceast</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I guess what you bring up is an important argument. Something for me to think about further. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1r53g9</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Clockworkfrog</author>
        <ReplyBody>I am not in favour of the death penalty but definately pro-choice and there is no conflict because whether or not death should be used as a penalty has nothing to do with the fact that a woman should have more right to her body then something with the potential to become a person.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1r3n85</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NoneApplicable</author>
        <ReplyBody>Here's an interesting thought that sounds awful but is technically true. The 14th amendment says that all people born and naturalized in the us are citizens and thus are guaranteed equal protection under the law. A fetus is not yet born and therefore by the letter of the law cannot be considered a citizen</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1r6wjx</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>You're right, sounds awful, but absolutely true when it comes legality of it. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1r77j6</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Coollogin</author>
        <ReplyBody>You can be against the death penalty for reasons that have nothing to do with being pro-life/anti-murder/whatever.  I think there is an entirely sound argument that the death penalty is ineffective and ultimately accrues no positive value for society. More costly than life in prison without parole and in no way an effective deterrent. So why even bother? 

That reasoning is completely unrelated to anyone's views on abortion, which frees you to consider your opinion on abortion completely separately from your position on death penalty.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1r7jsb</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>wekulm</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'm anti death penalty and pro choice.   My pro choice stance is probably different, that is that laws against will only create more problems than it solves.  Too many (not all) cases are important medical decisions.  Inflexible laws create big problems.  Morally, as a libertarian, I view it as the baby has no autonomy until it's born.  The solution (to less abortions) is a cultural shift, not laws.  Laws don't have to fix all our problems.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1rcctd</id>
        <replies>
            <author>spenceast</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is a smart answer !delta. Thank you. I agree that laws can frequently solve more problems than resolve them. 

 I'd love to chat more with you about other issues, and see where you stand as a libertarian and what your arguments are.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1req68</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>CurlyFern</author>
        <ReplyBody>People who are pro-choice often make the argument that the fetus is not a person so it is not murder. A felon is a person, so killing them requires different moral considerations potentially than killing a non-person. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1rgv8m</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>goldandguns</author>
        <ReplyBody>On one hand there is a procedure and the individual is getting a fair trial, they did something wrong (presumably terrible) and their death will serve as a deterrent for those who want to commit similar crimes and gives peace and closure to victims of serious crimes. 

On the other hand, a single individual killing a perfectly Innocent humanoid who has no say in the matter 


I don't see how they can be even casually compared. 
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1rmp75</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>AutoModerator</author>
        <ReplyBody>**Note:** Your thread has **not** been removed.

Your post's topic seems to be fairly common on this subreddit. Similar posts can be found through our [wiki page](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/abortion#link) or via the [search function](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/search?q=abortion&amp;amp;amp;amp;restrict_sr=on).

Regards, the mods of /r/changemyview.

*I am a bot, and this action was performed automatically. Please [contact the moderators of this subreddit](/message/compose/?to=/r/changemyview) if you have any questions or concerns.*</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1qspfd</id>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
