<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>120</commentCount>
    <id>2sbfi7</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2sbfi7/cmv_there_is_currently_no_humane_form_of_capital/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>natha105</author>
        <ReplyBody>The problem is quick and painless, yet not messy and palatable to the public.  A crown of hand grenades with a synchronized pin system would do the trick with 100% reliability yet it would create a ghastly mess.  This is the same problem with a dozen computer controlled guns pointed at a person's head.  Or we could do a guillotine where instead of a blade there were a twenty ton weight and instead of the neck it landed on the head.  None of these methods could possibly go wrong in a way where the person would have time for their brain to perceive pain.  

The problem is the mess.  The public likes things clean: an injection, a gas, a drop and a little tug, a buzz and its over.

I think the real problem is that society cares more about their own feelings than the feelings of the condemned.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnzdyz</id>
        <replies>
            <author>blazingscience</author>
            <ReplyBody>Years ago, I had a minor surgery done. they numbed my hand, put an IV in it, and then put me to sleep. I felt no pain at all.

We could easily give someone whatever drug they gave me or something similar, and then kill them by any "clean" method while they're asleep. Hell, a large enough dose of an anesthetic would probably do the trick painlessly and cleanly.

I actually prefer brutal methods for executing people though. Use the crown of grenades. If we're going to allow the state to kill someone, I don't want to pretend like it's not nasty just because there isn't any blood.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno9az7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Carlos13th</author>
                <ReplyBody>The people making the decisions wouldn't be the one cleaning up the blood or performing the execution though sadly. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnoamgb</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>pppppatrick</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Why can't we hire people who aren't phased by these things to clean up? I mean there are professional crime scene cleaners aren't there?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnp55hs</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>hexane360</author>
                <ReplyBody>For lethal injection, they use three drugs, the first of which is a pain killer. The problem is that these are administered by prison guards, who often give incorrect doseages, leading to some cases of excruciating prolonged pain.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnoikrc</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>KittehDragoon</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;administered by prison guards, who often give incorrect dosages

It's not just that. These people are so untrained that there are numerous documented cases where they had to delay an execution for hours because they had trouble sticking the needle into a suitable vein or where they went all the way through a vein, and even one case where they stuck it into an artery by mistake. 

If they inject the cocktail incorrectly, which would have happened if these mistakes hadn't been noticed (and I suspect that occasionally they aren't), you're in for a slow and miserable death. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnoj9tm</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>meatwad75892</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; We could easily give someone whatever drug they gave me or something similar, and then kill them by any "clean" method while they're asleep. Hell, a large enough dose of an anesthetic would probably do the trick painlessly and cleanly.


Anyone know if the costs for that be higher or lower than typical drugs used for lethal injection? What about availability? I recall Texas and Ohio coming under fire for using cocktails of random or unauthorized drugs; can't remember if it was for lack of other drugs' availability, skimping on costs, legality, or other. Then again, I guess if you're carrying out capital punishment and the end result will be no more expense on that person's life.. The cost of the drug to get you there should be trivial, even if it's "pricey" because it will ultimately save money. That felt awful just typing that, but there's nothing glamorous about capital punishment.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnofvwy</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>whaaatanasshole</author>
                    <ReplyBody>They switched to different drugs because the previous cocktail could no longer be imported for the purposes of killing people.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnoh7md</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>22</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>whaaatanasshole</author>
            <ReplyBody>I agree with almost all of this. I think there are clean and palatable methods.

1) [Exit bags](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suicide_bag). Painless, no mess, cheap as free. No one talks about it, maybe because they think we'd get more suicides instead of painless and clean suicides.

2) The [orally](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z7BVLSC7YF4) [administered](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l-_uEmdmSsY) methods used for assisted suicides by Dignitas and other organizations. It's cheap, yet a billionaire chose this way out. Is this too *nice* for capital punishment?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnoh6tv</id>
            <upvotes>12</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is a pretty good point. I'd agree that the main reason we use the methods we use is because they're "clean". Using other methods would most likely be more humane. On top of that doing it other ways would be way more cost efficient. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnzsn0</id>
            <upvotes>7</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>walruz</author>
            <ReplyBody>No, it's not. There is exactly zero benefit to a death penalty being "palatable". If you use your democratic system to vote for people who wants to *kill their citizens for sport*, then you'd damn well look at the gruesomeness of the state that you've created. 

"But capital punishment isn't killing for sport, it's justice!" No, it's not. There is literally no benefit to capital punishment apart from sick amusement when compared to life imprisonment without parole. It is trivial to build a prison that is impossible to escape from. It is cheaper to keep someone locked up than to have a trial for death penalty under any semblance of judicial fairness, and it is trivial to make life in prison as painful and boring as any quick death - not even vengeance for its own sake is a good reason to have capital punishment. The literally only reason to ever institute capital punishment in a first world country is that you like watching people die. And if so, the least you can do is to own that shit. 

And since how sanitary the death penalty *looks* is not a concern, there are loads of humane execution methods. A helmet made out of C4 will kill instantly. A guillotine is  impossible to botch if the blade is heavy enough. However, the head might conceivably be alive for some short moment, which would be frightening and painful, so I propose a guillotine with a block instead of a blade. The block weighs something on the order of 50 tons, and is dropped - free falling - from a height of 10 meters on to the head of a prone prisoner. It would crush his head instantly (or near enough), extinguishing consciousness as fast as possible. Since the block crushed instead of cutting, it doesn't have to be aligned properly, and as such doesn't need to be guided by anything analogous to the wooden parts of a guillotine - hence it can't get stuck anywhere and hence can't perform a half decapitation or something. Further, since the blocks weight is so exaggerated, it will kill purely by force of gravity. Hence, the only way it can fail is if the dropping mechanism fails (in which case the prisoner could be retrieved for a second go) or if gravity stops working (which doesn't seem likely). </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnoiu5x</id>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>BeefPieSoup</author>
            <ReplyBody>Best way would be to slowly suffocate in laughing gas. You'd pass out in a delious happy stupor and then die when you are unconscious. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnohlxy</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>rtechie1</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Or we could do a guillotine where instead of a blade

In practice, regular guillotines are extremely fast and reliable. They're still too "messy" as you state. Even a firing squad is pretty reliable. 

As you say, the methods chosen aren't about reducing pain for the convict, but making the executioner feel better.

Though I would point out that most prisoners would strongly object to your proposed methods (and beheading) as it would mutilate their bodies. Given the choice of methods, most prisoners would probably choose lethal injection or firing squad (mainly because the firing squad is seen as being an "dignified" method of execution). 

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnpnqn5</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>71</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Revvy</author>
        <ReplyBody>Nitrous oxide asphyxiation. You get pleasantly high, at ease. A few seconds later, passout, and cleanly, quickly painlessly, and cheaply, die from the lack of oxygen.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno16mf</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>That is an interesting idea. Sadly it's not used today. Would the individual suffer if they tried to fight against it, as with the current system?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno1j4y</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>If the human body is asphyxiated without Co2, they do not feel put of breath. They just fade away.

IMO pure nitrogen asphyxiation is the way to go.

Cheap, painless, easy, peaceful.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cno9tkd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>8549176320</author>
                    <ReplyBody>And safe also, since escaped nitrogen rejoins the 78% nitrogen already in room air. This is the way to go, and I don't see any downside at all.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnob71y</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>MEGA_MEGA_SLUT</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I don't think nitrous oxide is what you think is is</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnodz8t</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>pween</author>
                            <ReplyBody>he was responding to "If the human body is asphyxiated without Co2, they do not feel put of breath. They just fade away.

IMO pure nitrogen asphyxiation is the way to go."

not nitrous oxide.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnohv9j</id>
                            <replies>
<author>8549176320</author>
<ReplyBody>That's what I meant. Thanks for the clarification. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cnokvno</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>12</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>blazesquall</author>
                <ReplyBody>There's a great Frontline about using helium as a suicide device, if you wanted some perspective of a similar approach.

http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/suicide-plan/
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnocw3e</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>ddrluna</author>
                    <ReplyBody>With everyone talking about there being a helium shortage, though, I suspect this wouldn't be the ideal gas to use when there are other, more accessible options with generally the same effect. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnoenvi</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>insaneHoshi</author>
                        <ReplyBody>There is no shortage, the reserves are low since helium has not been produced in 50 years or so</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnoizw4</id>
                        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>DBDude</author>
                <ReplyBody>Put the person in a chamber with a set humidity and temperature, and the regular oxygen (about 20%) nitrogen (about 80%) air mix. Keeping humidity and temperature steady, start replacing the oxygen with nitrogen over the course of a couple minutes. The person notices no change in his environment, but passes out, and brain stem death is 100% assured within maybe ten minutes of a pure nitrogen atmosphere.

The feeling of suffocation is not caused by lack of oxygen, but by a buildup of carbon dioxide. Breathing nitrogen does not result in a buildup of carbon dioxide, since it still gets exhaled, so there will be no feeling of suffocation. A lot of people have died due to accidental nitrogen asphyxiation because they didn't realize they were suffocating. 

The problem with drug-based execution is that no doctors want to be involved, creating a problem of competent delivery. Running a nitrogen asphyxiation requires no real skill, and the HVAC people necessary to set it up don't take the Hippocratic Oath. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnp3bqx</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>rtechie1</author>
                <ReplyBody>This method is not reliable. There are documented cases of people surviving this type of asphyxiation after very long exposure (over an hour). 

This creates the messy situation of "almost" killing a prisoner, rendering them "brain dead" but not completely dead. So the procedure has to be done multiple times. 

Making execution quasi-medical is a problem because actual doctors (and all medical staff) refuse to be involved. This means, by definition, these methods will be used by incompetent staff. 

Stuff like hanging, beheading, and shooting is a lot harder to screw up. ISIS even has little kids doing it. 
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnpntn8</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>11</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>kingpatzer</author>
        <ReplyBody>I have spent time doing research in anesthesiology at one point in my life. 

We were improving the pharmocology of drugs used for anesthetics for full heart/lung replacements. 

Our subjects would go under almost immediately, and they'd be so far under, that the surgeons could then do a full double lung and heart replacement procedure. 

Now, I think it goes without saying that when you take out a person's heart and lungs, they're more or less effectively dead. 

Our patients routinely did not feel pain or discomfort. 

And the tipping point from under sedation to dead isn't a wide area. 

Honestly, we have the drugs to kill people quite painlessly and frankly, nearly instantly. Why they aren't using modern anesthetics is a mystery to me. My guess is the drug companies don't want the same drugs used in putting people down as they use in operating rooms for marketing reasons. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnod9om</id>
        <upvotes>11</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>garnteller</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's hard to have this debate without getting in to the morality of the death penalty.  The reason is that one could argue that state-sponsored execution are inherently inhumane.  That's one end of the spectrum.  The other end is to argue that it's humane for the prisoner to suffer at least as much as their victims did.

It's sort of like the rules of war - "it's ok to use bullets, but not gas".  "You can carpet bomb a city, but not a tent with a red cross".

Bringing morality or humaneness into either situation borders on the absurd.

Our sentencing is more or less predicated on the idea that murder is the highest offense.  Torture would receive a shorter sentence.  Therefore, once we've decided that it's ok for the state to kill someone - ending their life and potential forever - it's pretty absurd to say, "but not if it hurts them a little".

It's not really a question of gas vs. injection.  As long as there is no gratuitous suffering, does it really matter? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnxp2e</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;It's hard to have this debate without getting in to the morality of the death penalty

I actually agree with this, I just don't want it to be the main argument being held here

&amp;gt;It's not really a question of gas vs. injection. As long as there is no gratuitous suffering, does it really matter?

The problem is in many cases there are gratuitous suffering. According to this [site](http://deathpenalthy.info.org/executions-year) 39 people were executed last year, and based off of the botched execution link above, 3 were botched. That's 8% of executions, a number that, in my opinion, isn't exactly great. That doesn't take into account that when it is botched the pain they feel is immense. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnny9bx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>garnteller</author>
                <ReplyBody>That's cheating a bit with your statistics.  If you'd picked 2013, 2012 or 2011, you'd have zero percent, since there were no botched executions.

Also, in the first case, it wasn't botched - they just didn't like the procedure that was following.

The second one was a shitstorm, no doubt.

In the third, there's no proof that the inmate was aware of any pain, it could have just been their body reacting.

In any case, I should have been clearer in how I meant gratuitous - not without pain, but not without more pain than is needed.  

By your rules, we need to assume that the death penalty is humane.  Granted that, why does it need to be completely painless?  We're already granting that murder can be humane, but somehow only painless murder is ok?

Moreover, if the method that millions choose to use on their beloved pets is inhumane to use on humans, does that make it an inhumane way to put your pet to sleep?  How are they different? </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cno11k4</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You are correct the year I used had botched executions, the problem is I'm sure there were botched executions on years that weren't listed. This is the only article I found, but it claims to only list some of the executions. I could be wrong though

This is a pretty good argument though. I would argue that the potential pain these individuals can potentially face is extreme. I would not be as opposed if the pain they might experience would be much less

Animals are a different story though. They are already treated differently then humans (whether right or wrong).</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cno1qhg</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>garnteller</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Animals are treated differently - but in this case it's the opposite of what you're arguing.  

Pet owners would do almost anything to prevent their pets from suffering.  If you asked pet owners whether they care more about whether their pet or a death row inmate suffers at their death, I suspect 90% would care more about the pet.

For that matter, a significant number would choose their pet over an innocent child they didn't know.

My point is that people wouldn't euthanize their pets through lethal injection if they didn't think that it was the most human option - not most humane for pets, but for anyone.  This, despite the fact that there are botched euthanizations as well.

Lethal injection was also the method of choice of Jack Kevorkian in his "Physician-assisted suicides".  

Clearly, it's used by those who are trying to be as merciful as possible.

Again, if we're granting that the death penalty is moral, using the method those those would use to end their own life, or that of their beloved pet, seems to clearly fall within the bounds of humane.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnonalo</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>dehshadow</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I would concede that lethal injection would most likely be humane if the way in which it was carried out was improved. The current methods used on humans are actually less [effective](http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/all-dogs-go-heaven/201112/animal-euthanasia-and-capital-punishment-some-uncomfortable-compariso) then those used on animals. Different medications are used despite the advice given by medical professionals. As I learned from /u/stratys3 the government also tends to use medications that are less effective due to restrictions placed on them by pharmaceuticals.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnontiv</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>11</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>SOLUNAR</author>
        <ReplyBody>Firing squad?

Surely with enough shooters, and changing the aim from the body to the head, we can get some nearly perfect executions.

None of the listed botched executions that i could find had any mention to firing squads.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnwnun</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>There are two issues I have with the firing squad. The first is that they can and have missed. In this case the prisoner is just left to sit there and die. Even when they do hit the heart (which is marked and identified by a doctor), the prisoner still is in pain and only dies from shock and blood loss. 

The other issue is less for the prisoner and more for those committing the act. Only one blank is given out, so odds are your going to be shooting the guy. This brings up some long term mental and emotional issues for those doing this killing. This argument isn't really as concerning or relevant though though.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnwt47</id>
            <replies>
                <author>SOLUNAR</author>
                <ReplyBody>I agree, unless we were to set the rules for the shots to be aimed at the head, i can see this missing.

Too bad we dont have the guillotine as an approved method... I cant think of a reason the guillotine wouldnt work!</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnnx190</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Even with shots to the head I'd feel that you would need to stand really close to the victim to be accurate. When shooting the head it needs to be done very precisely as to kill certain parts of the brain, rather then just causing brain damage. It's why there are many suicide attempts that don't go quite as planned. 

I actually couldn't find anything going against the guillotine. There are plenty of reasons to not use axes, swords etc..., but besides improper assembly there weren't many issues. It's not considered a legal way to execute someone though</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnnx8f3</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SOLUNAR</author>
                        <ReplyBody>haha i know, i didnt want to break the rules as you do say current approved ways.

But dang, the guillotine would be great! Except the whole decapitating someone... part</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnnxf9f</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>stratys3</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Get a big gun, that's mounted and aimed for 100% accuracy. Hell, get 10 of them, just to make sure. Get 10+ people to press the red "FIRE!" button at the same time.

Problem solved.

The point is: You can create a mechanical system that effectively guarantees instantaneous death.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnnxpwf</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>dehshadow</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I mean of course that would be ideal, but actually carrying that out is the thing. There's tons of other factors to be considered there including the state of the body (prisoners do get funerals with family members), cleaning the room, as well as the mental state of the executioners and the witnesses.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnnyh8b</id>
                            <replies>
<author>stratys3</author>
<ReplyBody>I'd get rid of funerals. People who get the death penalty should have their corpses owned by the government.

The room would have an automatic sprinkler system that cleans by itself. Alternatively, I'm sure you'd be able to find a few crazies who actually enjoy the cleaning. Either way, not a big deal.

As for executioners and witnesses - just like the above - I'm sure you'd find some volunteers that have no objections to it.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cnnzbfv</id>
<replies>
    <author>dehshadow</author>
    <ReplyBody>Where the body ends up depends on how you view the criminal, which comes back to more where you fall with the death penalty. I believe that the victim and their family should have a right to have a funeral

I mean from what I understand the witnesses are very often family members of the criminal as well as the victims family.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cnnzmhw</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<replies>
    <author>rtechie1</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I'd get rid of funerals. People who get the death penalty should have their corpses owned by the government.

This is the definition of "adding insult to injury". The man's dead. It's just being petty to insist on desecrating his corpse. 

</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cnpnvz3</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Alex470</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I had an old coworker who was just recently shot in the head during a robbery. The bullet went into the eye socket and managed to travel down through the neck and off his shoulder. He managed to survive it, too. Bullets can be pretty unpredictable is what I mean to say.

Using a pneumatic spike like they do with pigs in a slaughterhouse would likely be a better plan than a firing squad. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cno0gj6</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Raborn</author>
                <ReplyBody>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captive_bolt_pistol

The ones used for euthanasia. 2 of them, one through each front lobe via some kind of helmet device + suction.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cno4u1x</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>tymiller1218</author>
        <ReplyBody>I agree that lethal injections can be inhumane if done incorrectly, but if done correctly it shouldn't really be an issue. I would propose bleeding the condemned out under anesthesia, seems to me like it would be neither cruel nor unusual.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnyenp</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;if done incorrectly

That's the biggest problem with lethal injection. There are a lot of factors that come into play when carrying it out. Determining the correct dosage is based off of a number of factors including age, weight, gender. A small error in this can have large consequences. Administering the drug can also go wrong and in many cases the training by the executioner is less the what should be required. The problem is finding a properly trained person that would be willing to be an executioner. 

&amp;gt;bleeding the condemned out under anesthesia

This in theory could work and I actually think this is a better idea then our currently lethal injection. Despite this I can see some problems with it. It would be kinda horrific for those watching and the process would be very time consuming and therefore costly. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnytoh</id>
            <replies>
                <author>stratys3</author>
                <ReplyBody>You can have drugs that won't "go wrong". Those can be used instead.

If the person has no veins, then knock them out using inhaled gas, and then kill them some other way (doesn't really matter how).

It's a myth that drugs "don't always work". In high enough doses, it will work, guaranteed (just ask an anesthesiologist). The problem is that the government is restricted into using really shitty drugs, instead of the more effective and reliable and painless ones.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnnzxle</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I mean that doesn't eliminate injection in the wrong place, such as muscles, by non-properly changed staff. Is the government really restricted to using shitty drugs? I didn't know that.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cno1gcw</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>stratys3</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Well properly trained staff should do the injecting, obviously. That's not a flaw of lethal injection, but a flaw with the system that could more easily be corrected.

As for drugs - yes. Many drug companies will refuse to provide effective drugs to the government for executions. So they have to make do with shitty drugs that may end up torturing people instead... </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cno1w47</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>dehshadow</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I mean but isn't the executioner part of the process. It's a flaw that I don't think can be easily corrected because medical experts will most likely not want to be executioners. 

That is interesting and I would say that you've changed my view on the drugs used, but the problem is those aren't the drugs being used today. As far as my view on the lethal injection process itself though I feel like that concept has slightly altered my perception. &amp;amp;#8710;</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cno2cpb</id>
                            <replies>
<author>stratys3</author>
<ReplyBody>Thanks for the delta.

I think that if you pay experts enough, they'll be willing to do it, to make sure they get a "clean" death instead of a painful and gruelling one. Sure, it's an extra cost, but it already costs an unbelievable amount to execute someone today, and this would be a small addition to that cost - and I don't think it would be unreasonable.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cno790k</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>DeltaBot</author>
<ReplyBody>Confirmed: 1 delta awarded to /u/stratys3. ^[[History](/r/changemyview/wiki/user/stratys3)]

^[[Wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/deltabot)][[Code](https://github.com/alexames/DeltaBot)][[Subreddit](http://www.reddit.com/r/DeltaBot/)]</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cno46bg</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>cfuse</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; It would be kinda horrific for those watching and the process would be very time consuming and therefore costly.

Give them a massive dose of warfarin and they'll bleed out internally instead.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnoir7u</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>cfuse</author>
            <ReplyBody>The issue that can and does arise in these cases is that prisoners can be hardcore injecting drug users, and thus their veins can be totally useless.

I recall that in one case it took them an hour to find a usable vein using a scalpel and the active assistance of the prisoner himself.

&amp;gt; I would propose bleeding the condemned out under anesthesia

I would stop their heart chemically after they've been put under. Anesthesiologists can do that quite simply.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnoiq5u</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>midnightyeti</author>
        <ReplyBody>It may not be so humane, but the guillotine would be the easiest and quickest way out of those methods you mention.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno4vhs</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>I agree that the guillotine would probably be very effective. There have been no reported problems with this method in the past. The problem is the public view this form of death as gruesome and therefore it is no longer allowed in the United States.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno9z6i</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>L34der</author>
        <ReplyBody>You could inject them with morphine and then guillotine them.Morphine can kill almost any pain and instant decapitation would only cause a moment's suffering. I find it hard to imagine that you'd even suffer that long because the shock and confusion would pass in a second and then....you're dead.

It wouldn't be too messy either, just take care of the blood and the head. If you think i'm a sociopath for writing this then do note that a decapitation is 100% foolproof. Lethal injection is a fucked up way to kill people, there's no guarantee it's painless or not excruciatingly painful, it paralyzes you so there's no way to tell if the condemned feel as if they're drowning or suffocating. 

If putting down people like pets is supposed to be modern and decapitating them is barbaric then maybe western civilization has outlived it's usefulness.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnom9e2</id>
        <replies>
            <author>beardedheathen</author>
            <ReplyBody>I completely agree. Decapitation might be a bit messier than necessary though. Just putting them to sleep like for standard medical procedures (except you don't really need to worry about an overdose) and then cutting the throat. No pain, body is still in one piece, can be done above a drain or just thrown in a pig sty for easy cleaning. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnpdao8</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>67thou</author>
        <ReplyBody>Interesting. Ignoring the possibilities of false convictions (which is a real problem) im not too convinced we should be worried about being humane when it comes to executing criminals who have committed heinous crimes.

That being said, i do feel it is a waste to simply kill them, and it offers little in return to society as a whole.

I would prefer we use a form of lethal injection, or an anesthesia to knock them out then harvest usable organs to save other peoples lives if possible. This of course could open a whole other can of worms but i wish their deaths could be of some usefulness to innocent and sick people in the world.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnwr43</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is slightly going to get away from the view I'd like to debate, but I believe the reasoning behind the humane treatment of prisoners is that these are still people and citizens and that our government shouldn't be inflicted pain or unfair treatment upon these individuals.

I would actually agree with you that a prisoners organs could best be used to help out those less fortunate. I feel like that would still need to be granted by the prisoners consent. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnwzvc</id>
            <replies>
                <author>67thou</author>
                <ReplyBody>Sadly i feel that harvesting organs would definitely constitute "unusual punishment" and violate the Bill of Rights.

I am not convinced though that simply executing someone would constitute cruel or unusual punishment. I may be wrong but i do not think there is any part of the constitution that mandates we must be humane with how we execute? I could be wrong though.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnnxfwt</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>ryan_m</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;i do not think there is any part of the constitution that mandates we must be humane with how we execute?

That's the cruel part of cruel and unusual.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnnxnby</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>67thou</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Is it cruel to execute someone convicted of capital crimes? When that law was written executions were certainly carried out by most governments. I guess i would assume the spirit of their words was not an avoidance of executions due to being too cruel?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnnxqzu</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>ryan_m</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I'd argue that the state shouldn't be executing people in the first place, but if we have to execute them, that we have a duty to do it in the most humane way possible, no matter the crime that has been committed.

The spirit was (likely) to avoid people being tortured and then killed (drawn &amp;amp; quartered/various medieval punishments) because that has no place in civilized society.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnny0ty</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>THE_LAST_HIPPO</author>
                            <ReplyBody>ryan_m was answering "with how we execute?" not "whether we execute." As to the question of if the constitution mandates whether we execute: No</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnocib4</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>stratys3</author>
                    <ReplyBody>What's wrong with executing them first, and then harvesting their organs 2nd? Once they're dead, they have no rights anyways.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnnxmhj</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>dehshadow</author>
                        <ReplyBody>That's the way I actually would support. This method would need to have prisoner consent though. I feel like this might actually happen in some situations though.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnnxtxn</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>67thou</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Oh im not saying for me personally. I would have no issue taking every last part of them that was useful to save lives. Im just theorizing what a counter argument would be.

When the law was written, the idea of organ transplants was probably not even considered possible. So it could definitely be seen as an unusual form of punishment to kill and harvest.

Again, im all for it. You kill someone, we will use your body to save 5 others. Seems fair to me. The only real dilemma would be false convictions would be fucked.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnnxuhn</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>stratys3</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The only real dilemma would be false convictions would be fucked.

Well if you're gonna execute them anyways, then this actually makes things *better*... because the mistake is now partially offset by the fact that 5 lives were saved.
</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnny4uv</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>huadpe</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;What's wrong with executing them first, and then harvesting their organs 2nd? Once they're dead, they have no rights anyways.

The same thing that's wrong with doing that with the corpses of non-convicts.  Once they're dead, the state has no further interest in punishing them, and their next of kin should decide how to deal with their affairs.  The relatives of the convict are not guilty of a crime, and should not be treated as having less say than other relatives because of the crimes of a now dead man.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cno3n3g</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>stratys3</author>
                            <ReplyBody>1) It's not about punishment, but about restitution, which is a legitimate demand.

2) The relatives may get their feelings hurt, but that's irrelevant, since their feelings didn't play a role in the convicts sentencing in the first place, and should have no role to play after the convicts death. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cno7gg9</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Movements towards more humane forms of punishment were actually based off of the section of the Eight Amendment you just quoted protection against "cruel and unusual punishment". The Supreme Court ruling on Capital Punishment didn't ban it based off of this amendment, but did state that certain procedural aspects must be considered when carrying it out [[1]](http://law.cornell.edu/wex/death_penalty)
</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnnxr4v</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>67thou</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Ah, would they have expected a 100% assertion of a painless death or just as much of an effort to ensure a painless death as possible within reason?

I've always felt a firing squad was the most likely to be humane. Lethal injection was a nice "idea" but as you've shown in practice it's proven to be far more complicated. I feel an assurance to a quick and as painless as possible death would be the most humane. There may not be a 100% sure fire way to offer a pain free death, but limiting suffering should be considered, preventing any form of suffering for any amount of time seems a bit harder to accomplish and maybe not what was intended by that ruling?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnny5w8</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>dehshadow</author>
                            <ReplyBody>The most reasonable qualifications I believe that we can expect is within within reason, but, in my opinion, it falls short. As I wrote above [[site]](http://deathpenalthy.info.org/executions-year) 39 people were executed last year, and based off of the botched execution link above, 3 were botched. That's 8% of executions.

I'd actually agree that firing squad is the "most" humane, but like you said it falls short. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnnyebr</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>cfuse</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; im not too convinced we should be worried about being humane when it comes to executing criminals who have committed heinous crimes.

What we do and do not do speaks to our principles and who we really are.

Can we execute people without concern for them? Of course. *Should* we do so? Probably not. Making decisions where your principles are tested and hold true is important. Do we think some criminals deserve (a painful) death? Of course we do, we're human. *Should* we ignore our principles to satisfy that urge? I think not.

My thinking is that if we are going to execute people it is because they are irredeemable. It's like if you have a dangerous animal - you put it down for the safety of all, not because you're trying to punish it.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnoivv4</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BaylorNinja</author>
        <ReplyBody>What about firing squads a bullet to the heads pretty painless.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnzb3d</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>The problems with the firing squad I listed above. It would currently be my personal choice, but you can miss the heart, and even when you hit you die of shock and blood loss</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnzizm</id>
            <replies>
                <author>BaylorNinja</author>
                <ReplyBody>True but you could always go point blank.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cno02oj</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>It's very messy and difficult to have four people shoot someone at point blank</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cno23mp</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>BaylorNinja</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Their are ways to fix that</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cno2ju6</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I would submit that the most humane ways to execute a person have a strong correlation with the methods people use to kill them selves.

According to [this list](http://frater.com/suicidelist.html) gun shot, drugs, and hanging are the top three. They do involve some pain and may involve some cleanup but I would submit that an execution need not be perfectly painless or clean for it to be humane. It is more of a sliding scale and am arguing that these methods are most humane because they are the methods people most frequently select for them selves. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno0e10</id>
        <replies>
            <author>cfuse</author>
            <ReplyBody>Using a list of options selected by people so mentally unstable that they are killing themselves isn't a very sound procedure.

I have a mental illness and I go through periods of suicidal ideation. Part of my coping strategy for that was planning my suicide - I wanted one less thing to have to worry about. I did a lot of research. Here's my recipe:

1. Use a depressant, like alcohol.
1. Put a plastic bag over your head with a reasonable seal.
1. Run a pipe from a helium or nitrogen tank into the bag and turn it on.
1. Die painlessly.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnoiyyc</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Would you consider that a humane way to execute those guilty of capital crimes?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnone70</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>cfuse</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I consider capital punishment to be inhumane by definition.

Regardless of whatever physical measures you take to make execution painless, you are only able to mitigate physical pain - what about psychological pain?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnp6tkr</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Why do you consider pain to be an evil to be avoided? Merely because the person in paid does not desire it?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnp7ab8</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>cfuse</author>
                            <ReplyBody>If I willingly cause another torment, what does that make me?

People often don't understand the costs to *themselves* in these cases. It's not just about what happens to the prisoner, it's about what you'll let happen to them in your name.

Rotten human beings are still human beings, and they still have all the rights that human beings have - including the most basic right to live. If we hold human life as being valuable as an ethic, then I would consider that rule to be inviolate rather than mutable. The second we consider it mutable we open ourselves to the question of "Which lives are more valuable?". I think we all know that those kind of situations don't end in egalitarianism.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnprway</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; If I willingly cause another torment, what does that make me?

Are you going to go down that road? There are lots of legitimate suffering you can inflict on another. Parents do this to their children. Coaches to their athletes. Police to criminals when they make arrests.

The question shouldn't be about pain but rather if the pain is due to the person for their acts? And if the person assigned to the task has legitimate authority delegated by society or nature.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cnqtoue</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>How would you be able to enforce suicide in this way? Plus I can't see mass public support for suicide in this way.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno1hsr</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>I am not supporting suicide as a means of capital punishment. I am only making the argument that we can know what methods are most humane by the rate of use by people for themselves. 

We could move the argument further by narrowing down the population analyzed by only looking at those who are mentally ill and who are assisted by a physician.

My argument is only that whatever these persons find suitable and humane for their end should be considered for that which is humane for the state to use in executions.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cno2uoo</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I feel like this is hindered because most individuals killing themselves using methods that are avaliable to you. Not everyone has access to guns or drugs. Also the use of electrocution or gas chambers cant be tested because no one has access to these things. Using these methods might be more effective, but would rarely be used because of avalability.  </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cno30ws</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>looklistencreate</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why should the complications be the deciding factor here? Should we label something inhumane if .01% of the procedures go wrong? There's error in everything. Should we ban all elective medical procedures that have had anything go wrong? I'd go with lethal injection because at least there are medical experts trying to get it to go right and using their extensive knowledge of the human body.

If you are executed by hanging or firing squad in the US, you chose it. They aren't the primary form of execution in any state.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno1dij</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>The error rate of capital punishment is much higher then .01%. The problem with lethal injections is that very often it isn't medical experts who carry out the execution. You have to consider that well trained doctors and medical experts are unlikely to take a job as an executioner. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno21dw</id>
            <replies>
                <author>looklistencreate</author>
                <ReplyBody>I thought it was required that a doctor was present for the execution.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cno5ete</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>cfuse</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; You have to consider that well trained doctors and medical experts are unlikely to take a job as an executioner.

Any ethical medical board should strike off any doctor that participates in an execution. It is unreservedly against their professional ethics.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnoizne</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>beardedheathen</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Preventing someone who has proven to be a danger to others from hurting others seems to be pretty ethical. To me this is the same as saying any doctor who is willing to kill cancerous cells should be struck off by an ethics board. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnpdeir</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>cfuse</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Doctors are not part of the judiciary or penal system, their role is to provide medical aid based on need. Killing someone is neither medically necessary nor ethical practice *for a doctor*^(1).

IMO, you can either be a doctor or you can be an executioner but you can't be both. The roles are mutually exclusive.

Human rights don't stop simply because someone is awful, and the most basic of rights is to live. The test of ethics is not in doing what's right in an easy situation, but doing so in those edge cases when your emotions are telling you to do something to compromise your principles^(2). There will always be those that deserved to live, and those that deserve to die, but if we put ourselves in the role of arbiter of life and death then we are opening an ethical can of worms that is more costly to us than putting prisoners in jail for life.

You don't need to kill a person to curtail their risk of recidivism. That is kind of the whole point of prisons in the first place. Additionally, there's the issue that the criminally insane are (usually) not subject to execution - so it's not like there isn't precedent or skill in incarcerating dangerous criminals who would otherwise be executed.

---
1) What sort of trust would colleagues and patients put in a doctor that intentionally kills people? 

Hell, would you want to even live next door to that kind of a person? I sure wouldn't.

2) America kills completely innocent people every single day as a matter of SOP. It is nothing to use a drone to blow up a gathering of people on the grounds that a target *might* be there. Extra-judicial killings are SOP. This is what happens when you deviate from your principles - that which you decried as evil becomes normal to you.

Principles are important because they stop you from becoming the kind of thing you don't want to be. Principles are a safeguard - if we ignore them we are walking into dangerous territory.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cnprjha</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>beardedheathen</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I dispute that the role of doctor and executioner are exclusive. If a person has show that they are a threat to those around them removing them is the logical thing. It protects those that deserve protecting.&#xD;&#xD; Criminals are routinely stripped of their human rights. As part of the social contract inherent in civilization you are required to respect the rights of others. When you break the law by intruding on the human rights of another person the collective will of the people, the government in this instance, will remove a portion of your rights. Whether that is property, freedom or sometimes life depending on the seriousness of the infraction. This is logical and I hope to live close to people who think this same way. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cnpszlv</id>
                            <replies>
<author>cfuse</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I dispute that the role of doctor and executioner are exclusive. If a person has show that they are a threat to those around them removing them is the logical thing. It protects those that deserve protecting.

My point is simple: it is not a doctor's choice to decide who lives and dies based on anything other than medical criteria.

The point of being a doctor is to preserve the life of the patient, and reduce pain, not to triage society as a whole (because a compelling argument can be made for killing anyone, up to and including genocide^(1)).

The other issue here is that who decides who lives and dies? Executing criminals is a nice emotive decision, but it can be demonstrated to be foolish even without ethics merely using logic: how many people can a criminal kill compared to a burger chain or a tobacco company? If we're going to be neutralizing threats to society then there are way bigger ones than even the most prolific serial killer.

&amp;gt; Criminals are routinely stripped of their human rights.

No, they are stripped of their *agency*, in much the same way children, mentally ill people, elderly people, etc. are. When the government or other appointed agency or person takes over the agency for an individual, that individual becomes their *responsibility*.

We feed, clothe, house, medicate, educate, supervise, etc. prisoners because they are our responsibility, because we as a society deem that necessary as part of the judicial process. They don't stop being human and having human rights, we simply take over the administration of their agency - they don't get to make choices about their lives other than the ones we deem appropriate (because what made them a criminal in the first instance was abuse of their own agency - they freely chose to do wrong).

&amp;gt; This is logical and I hope to live close to people who think this same way.

I hope that I live close to people that understand that how we treat those we revile and despise is a measure of our own worth and character. Of course we can kill those that we would be better off without, but if we want to be better than those we judge the only way to achieve that is by *not* killing them.

---
1) Killing all the gypsies is a no-brainer, nerve gassing the entire Middle East, wiping out Africa, giving the Indians blankets with smallpox, gassing the Jews, etc. You get the point.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cnqgt9s</id>
<replies>
    <author>beardedheathen</author>
    <ReplyBody>The doctor doesn't decide who lives or dies. That is the purpose of a judicial system. I personally believe that we should hold burger joints and tobacco companies responsible for the lives they have ruined (with the provision that there is choice in that matter) in their pursuit of profit. So the answer to your question is pretty simple: the judicial system decides. People that are chosen to represent society as a whole because we can't all stop every time a criminal does something and decided what we are going to do to them. 

No we are removing their rights. They lose their right to be free. They lose their right to own property. They sometimes lose their right to be alive. Don't try to sugar coat it. When a criminal is punished we remove their rights up to a certain point based on the seriousness of their crime. We are telling them: "what you did was an inhuman act." Some people can't be reasoned with some people just need to be put down. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cnqhotm</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>619shepard</author>
        <ReplyBody>Asphyxiation due to breathing nitrogen is painless and maybe [even looks a little fun.](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZpLi67NdD4w)</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno74qi</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>Agreed, but this currently isn't the way it's done. I would probably agree that this is a much more effective method. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno9xzj</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>funchy</author>
        <ReplyBody>You forgot firing squad.  Instant,  inexpensive,  pretty darn impossible to mess up.  A clean shot would kill the person instantly, which is about as "humane" as you're going to get. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno7a45</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Trenks</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's a nice thing in society when we think about humane ways to kill our worst humans. The question could be asked: why should we be humane as possible? I mean death by firing squad would work, but there would be a small amount of pain. Why is that small amount of pain the worst thing in the world for a mass murderer?

But I would say they aren't all as humane as humanely possible, but they're humane enough (without getting into the whole innocent people being put to death so don't have a death penalty at all argument). We could knock them out with anesthesia then shoot them in the head and heart so they'd feel no pain, but that's a whole to do. If you agree that these people did wrong, I think a slight amount of pain isn't all that upsetting. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno8yoh</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>It's not always a slight amount of pain. If you botch lethal injection the pain is supposedly excruciating. If the gas chamber goes wrong the and the patient doesn't pass out he can slowly choke to death, something that isn't exactly painless. Firing squad can lead to an individual sitting in pain while they bleed out. Electrocution can lead to pain without death.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cno9wxp</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Trenks</author>
                <ReplyBody>True, but how much pain did these folks inflict? I'm not saying we torture, but if their execution is botched (which I have to assume is a pretty low rate overall) it's really not the end of western civilization. They should get firing squads. They die quickly. It isn't painless, but it works. Why we have to let people gracefully die on a pillow-ey bed of our thoughts and prayers is beyond me.

Personally, I say abolish the death penalty all together and let them live out their days in prison. But if we're gonna kill rapists and murderers, we should do it quickly as possibly but we don't need to treat these people like hero's to go out with dignity and reverence. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnp4n8r</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>AsterJ</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's pretty easy for an execution to be cheap and painless.

[NSFW example](http://i.imgur.com/GDRyh4Z.gif)

Personally I'd be a fan of nitrogen asphyxiation</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cno9ehp</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>Sure there is. You could shoot them while they sleep with a .50 BMG in the brain stem. Guns could be automated. The execution could take place on an unspecified date or one the condemned chooses</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnodbm2</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>You can't feel pain if you don't have a brain. However that would make a bit of a mess on the floor, walls, and ceiling.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnokovi</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>c-fox</author>
        <ReplyBody>Hanging, if done correctly, is both quick and painless.  It is worth reading about http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Pierrepoint who executed over 400 people with no fuss.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnomhw4</id>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>Of course any of the processes done above, if done correctly, are relatively painless. The problem is that they're not always done properly. In cases where the neck doesn't snap an individual can be left there till asphyxiation.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnonkur</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>Opiate overdose. I've done it. It feels great and you pass out and stop breathing. I got hit with narcan so I came out of it. Before I passed out it was the best thing I ever felt. I have no idea why they don't do this. Put that confiscated heroin to use.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnow9iu</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnowfdv</id>
        <replies>
            <author>garnteller</author>
            <ReplyBody>Sorry Enchanted_Bunny, your comment has been removed: 

&amp;gt; Comment Rule 5\. "No low effort comments. Comments that are only jokes or 'written upvotes', for example. Humor and affirmations of agreement can be contained within more substantial comments." [See the wiki page for more information.](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules#wiki_rule_5)

If you would like to appeal, please [message the moderators by clicking this link.](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Fchangemyview&amp;amp;subject=Removed+Comment+Rule+5+Post+Appeal&amp;amp;message=Enchanted_Bunny+would+like+to+appeal+the+removal+of+[his/her+post](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/2sbfi7/cmv_there_is_currently_no_humane_form_of_capital/cnowfdv\))</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnowlzh</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>The main argument for capital punishment is that some crimes are so horrendous, that the criminal loses his/her right to life. 

I would argue that the fact that they are receiving capital punishment, confirms that these people don't deserve to be treated humanely. No whether that is true is debatable.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cnnwort</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Pipstydoo</author>
            <ReplyBody>It doesn't matter what you *feel* about it though.  We've all agreed (in terms of the modern social contract) this type of justice should be carried out swiftly, cleanly, and outside public spectacle.  Much of history demonstrates why we prefer this to the alternative.

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnxrxk</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>dehshadow</author>
            <ReplyBody>I mean this would go back to debating whether or not capital punishment is just, which isn't really the opinion I wanted to talk about. As I replied below though I believe the reasoning behind the humane treatment of prisoners is that these are still people and citizens and that our government shouldn't be inflicted pain or unfair treatment upon these individuals.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cnnx1an</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Have you found any more humane alternative than the ones you are criticizing?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cnnxq5x</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>dehshadow</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I mean I don't support capital punishment, but that isn't what I'm trying to have my view changed though. We currently use these methods of capital punishment and they are supposed to follow a guideline that states that they're humane. I want someone to try to convince me that the methods we currently as of (1/13/15) follow this requirement, or change the way in which I view humane. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cnnxzql</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>I had a lot of fun with this yesterday so wanted to give a different, more serious, type of topic a shot.

--

If capital punishment is to be carried out, it is supposed to be carried out in the most humane way possible. I feel that the current methods do not fulfill this requirement. The main reason behind my thinking is that, when looking at each method of capital punishment there are ways it can be botched. It would take a while to go through each one, but some examples are:

Lethal Injection: injection of a muscle can cause extreme pain, wrong dosages of medication can cause patients to be unable to move, but still feel the pain
Electrocution: First charge of electricity failing to kill
Gas Chamber: Death due to slow asphyxiation instead of passing out from gas.

This [link](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/some-examples-post-furman-botched-executions?scid=8&amp;amp;did=478) shows many examples of botched executions that have occurred in the United States. I feel like there are way too many examples, especially when you consider the number of inmates that are executed a year. These botched executions lead to immense pain and suffering for the clients. 

**I don't want to discuss whether or not the death penalty is morally just or under what type of crimes it should be granted.** The question here is whether or not any of the current methods of legal execution (Lethal Injection, Electrocution, Gas Chamber, Firing Squad, Hanging) can be considered humane. My current belief is that due to all the complications, that can and do occur, there is currently no method.
_____

&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
