<submission><id>0</id><identifier>1evztt</identifier><title>I believe Obama should be impeached and tried in civilian court for the unlawful killing of US Citizens in drone strikes. CMV.</title><commentCount>205</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1evztt/i_believe_obama_should_be_impeached_and_tried_in/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>As the title says, I think President Obama (and any others directly involved) should be impeached by Congress, subsequently removed from office, and tried in civilian court for (at the very least) murder for the killing of US citizens in overseas drone strikes. 

It has been well known for quite some time that the Obama administration has used drones overseas to kill certain targets, and that some of those killed were United States citizens. This is no longer something that people discuss and the government doesn't comment on; the administration has now admitted to the killing of four **US citizens** in drone strikes, three of whom were not targets.

Sources: 

http://www.aljazeera.com/news/americas/2013/05/2013522204811334806.html

http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/05/22/american-citizens-drone-strikes_n_3321950.html


My main argument stems from a reading of the Constitution. The Constitution represents a contract between the Government and The People. I find the following excerpts to be particularly important in this case (listed in order of applicability, with emphasis added):

~~Amendment XIV, Section 1, Paragraph 1:

&gt;**All persons born or naturalized in the United States, and subject to the jurisdiction thereof, are citizens of the United States** and of the State wherein they reside. No State shall make or enforce any law which shall abridge the privileges or immunities of citizens of the United States; **nor shall any State deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; nor deny to any person within its jurisdiction the equal protection of the laws.**~~

Amendment V:

&gt;**No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury**, except in cases arising in the land or naval forces, or in the Militia, when in actual service in time of War or public danger; nor shall any person be subject for the same offence to be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb; nor shall be compelled in any criminal case to be a witness against himself, **nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law**; nor shall private property be taken for public use, without just compensation.

Amendment VI:

&gt;In all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy the **right to a speedy and public trial, by an impartial jury** of the State and district wherein the crime shall have been committed, which district shall have been previously ascertained by law, and **to be informed of the nature and cause of the accusation; to be confronted with the witnesses against him; to have compulsory process for obtaining witnesses in his favor, and to have the Assistance of Counsel for his defence [sic].**

Article III, Section 2, Paragraph 3:

&gt;The **Trial of all Crimes**, except in Cases of Impeachment, **shall be by Jury**; and such Trial shall be held in the State where the said Crimes shall have been committed; but when not committed within any State, the Trial shall be at such Place or Places as the Congress may by Law have directed.

Article II, Section IV:

&gt;**The President, Vice President and all civil Officers of the United States, shall be removed from Office on Impeachment for, and Conviction of**, Treason, Bribery, or other **high Crimes and Misdemeanors.**

(Online source for quotations: http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution.html)


In my understanding of the Constitution, ~~all four~~ three of the fatalities were unlawful. ~~The killing of Anwar Al-Awlacki should be classified Murder in the First Degree, as it was clearly premeditated and he was not tried, so the killing cannot be deemed capital punishment.~~ The killing of Al-Awlacki can be justified by saying he was an enemy combatant, the capture of whom would have been infeasible. However, if the three were accidental as claimed, they are still felony manslaughter. Such felony level offenses are gross abuses of power, and must fit the definition of a "high crime". This, in my understanding, makes it obvious that impeachment is an appropriate course of action, and, if the Senate finds the defendants guilty, they should then be tried in civilian court, since the offenses are against other citizens of the United States.

Change my view.

**EDIT** /u/Jazz-Cigarettes changed my view on Al-Awlacki, but I remain unconvinced that the other three deaths are not impeachable offenses.

**EDIT 2** As /u/Tyrelxpeioust pointed out, the XIV Amendment applies only to the States (and so is irrelevant here), while the V Amendment is relevant.

</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>1</id><identifier>1tu7ff</identifier><title>Abortion is socially-accepted killing. Where human life begins is a moot point. CMV</title><commentCount>164</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1tu7ff/abortion_is_sociallyaccepted_killing_where_human/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I see abortion no different than capital punishment or killing in combat. As a society, we have accepted the right to kill someone for acts of violence, while at war, and during pregnancy. We have also outlined rules for when it is socially acceptable to kill animals or people in pain.

However, the argument I always see around abortion is "where does life begin". Who cares where life begins in regards to abortion? We only care about the quality of life of the mother and unborn child. Leave your opinion on where life begins out of the abortion debate.

I believe if Pro Choice folks (including myself) addressed the actual issue (the society-accepted killing of a fetus) head on, we would have a much more valuable &amp; honest conversation about this topic. For example, "yes, abortion is killing, but like other forms of killing (capital punishment, war, euthanasia, the meat industry), it creates more productivity and higher quality life in our society."

Change my view.

Edit: to clarify, I am discussing the argument of where human life begins. I consider it killing a fetus because the fetus is alive (composed of cells, uses energy, grows, different levels of organization, adapt to environment).

Edit 2: it may help to clarify that I believe the personhood argument is also non-valuable in the abortion discussion</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>2</id><identifier>1klx2i</identifier><title>I believe that capital punishment is necessary for violent crimes such as murder,mass murder and acts of manipulation that result in murder. CMV</title><commentCount>156</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1klx2i/i_believe_that_capital_punishment_is_necessary/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Living in Canada, we do not have capital punishment. At most, murders get multiple life sentences without the possibility for parole. There have been cases where people not only murdered, but raped and manipulated others into murdering women and or children. There are some seriously sick people out there and I believe that we waste millions upon millions of dollars housing, feed and even educating these people that have willingly taken another human life and sometimes even enjoyed doing so. Why? Why do we continue to provide these certain types of people the ability to take another breath. 

*[Example](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Pickton)

*[Example2](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Bernardo)

*[Example3](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell_Williams)

*[This example really gets under my skin.](http://news.nationalpost.com/tag/guy-turcotte/)
</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>3</id><identifier>4qg83u</identifier><title>CMV:I am Pro capital punishment.</title><commentCount>157</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4qg83u/cmvi_am_pro_capital_punishment/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I believe there are certain people who commit crimes so terrible the only logical way to deal with them is execution, if a dog mauls a human, we put it down, if a bear attacks/kills a human we put it down, if a cougar attacks a human we put it down. 

I don't think it should be any different for multiple murderers/rapists/serial killers who show no remorse what so ever for their crimes. 

I'm sure people are going to cite that it costs more to execute a person than it does to keep them incarcerated for their entire life but that's a systemic/political issue that could be easily rectified. 

Don't get me wrong I don't think we should make their exit cruel or unusual, while lethal injection is the most "humane" way to kill someone presently it is also costly and complicated.  Suffocation via pure nitrogen is literally painless and incredibly cheap.  

My main opinion stems from the fact that there are people who are beyond rehabilitation and by locking them in a box with other equally disturbed people no only are you opening the doors for the to continue committing crime while they're incarcerated you're opening up all of the men and women who are employed as correctional officers to a lot of hazards as well. 

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>4</id><identifier>4ltthr</identifier><title>CMV: The death penalty, as a concept, is moral</title><commentCount>141</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4ltthr/cmv_the_death_penalty_as_a_concept_is_moral/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>To be clear, I'm not interested in debating any specific application of a death penalty, what crimes it should or should not apply to, how much it costs, or how we can deal with the problem of innocent people found guilty of capital crimes. Let's assume, for the purposes of this discussion, that the particular case in question showed incontrovertible evidence condemning the accused; say they murdered 50 people with a machine gun in front of a crowded stadium filled with people, caught on camera, etc. 

I believe that in these instances, capital punishment is absolutely justified and moral. I'm specifically looking for counter arguments holding that capital punishment is immoral in and of itself.

Edit: a word

Edit 2: To address a point that seems to be coming up a lot: I really do mean that what I'm talking about is the concept of a death penalty, not any specific application. I believe that the death of a person in certain circumstances is justifiable and moral *in and of itself*. To put it another way, I believe in the concept of "justified vengeance." Please limit your arguments to this concept, I'm not interested in debating the merits of the death penalty as it is in America in 2016. That has been talked about *to death*. (Spoiler: I'm *against* it, in nearly every application.)

Edit 3: Lots of good responses while I was sleeping, I'll try to address them later today. Thanks for your patience!</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>5</id><identifier>1kkupx</identifier><title>I think that the War on Drugs could be won (nearly non-existant drug use) if we got very serious about it; CMV</title><commentCount>121</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1kkupx/i_think_that_the_war_on_drugs_could_be_won_nearly/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>When having arguments with others about legalizing drugs, one point often brought up is that the War on Drugs is impossible to win and therefore is a wasted effort.

While I would agree under the current policy that this is true, I think that it could be won if we were willing to get very serious about it.  

Specifically, if we made drug offenses (both felonies and misdemeanors) into capital crimes, then people would either stop using/selling/manufacturing drugs or the ones who didn't stop would be eliminated through execution.

Implementation of this policy would coincide with a grace period of several months and free access to rehab, counseling, and other services for addicts who need help quitting. 

Now, I will fully concede that this is mostly hypothetical since the US would never undertake such a policy (and it might require constitutional changes to even allow), but I think that it is an option that would be successful at winning the War on Drugs.  

Winning is defined as little to no usage of illegal drugs within the country. Quantitatively, if [around 9% of Americans currently use illegal drugs](http://www.oas.samhsa.gov/NSDUH/2k10NSDUH/2k10Results.htm), winning the war would be something like &lt; .1% using drugs.

As an aside, this solution would also nullify arguments about problems with the prison system, since we would no longer have to worry about overcrowding, recidivism, etc.

**TL;DR: The War on Drugs could be won if we made the punishment for drug crimes an automatic death sentence.**

*EDIT: I should mention that I do think drugs should be legalized purely on the merits of individual freedoms, I just mostly take issue with people who say that they should be legalized because the War on Drugs can't be won or because of problems in the prison system.*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>6</id><identifier>2sbfi7</identifier><title>CMV: There is currently no humane form of capital punishment.</title><commentCount>120</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2sbfi7/cmv_there_is_currently_no_humane_form_of_capital/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I had a lot of fun with this yesterday so wanted to give a different, more serious, type of topic a shot.

--

If capital punishment is to be carried out, it is supposed to be carried out in the most humane way possible. I feel that the current methods do not fulfill this requirement. The main reason behind my thinking is that, when looking at each method of capital punishment there are ways it can be botched. It would take a while to go through each one, but some examples are:

Lethal Injection: injection of a muscle can cause extreme pain, wrong dosages of medication can cause patients to be unable to move, but still feel the pain
Electrocution: First charge of electricity failing to kill
Gas Chamber: Death due to slow asphyxiation instead of passing out from gas.

This [link](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/some-examples-post-furman-botched-executions?scid=8&amp;did=478) shows many examples of botched executions that have occurred in the United States. I feel like there are way too many examples, especially when you consider the number of inmates that are executed a year. These botched executions lead to immense pain and suffering for the clients. 

**I don't want to discuss whether or not the death penalty is morally just or under what type of crimes it should be granted.** The question here is whether or not any of the current methods of legal execution (Lethal Injection, Electrocution, Gas Chamber, Firing Squad, Hanging) can be considered humane. My current belief is that due to all the complications, that can and do occur, there is currently no method.
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>7</id><identifier>4du1rv</identifier><title>CMV: The primary method of capital punishment should be death by gunshot</title><commentCount>112</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4du1rv/cmv_the_primary_method_of_capital_punishment/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>**Let me start this off by establishing the following:**

* I support capital punishment for crimes that deserve it **(this is not the view that I am arguing or trying to change)**

* This view is for the United States. I don't really care what other countries do. As for which state, it is for any state that has death penalty laws.

* When I state "death by gunshot", I mean 1 executioner and 1 gun (live ammunition). Not a firing squad (multiple people).

* This is all assuming that the criminal is guilty without a reasonable doubt.

Currently, most executions (death penalties) are done through the method of lethal injections. I am aware of some states that have multiple methods, some of which allow the criminal to choose, but I disagree with all of them as well (electricity / gas inhalation / firing squad / etc.) I believe that the best way to execute would be a simple bullet to the head.

The following arguments are against lethal injection, but if needed to I can elaborate on why gunshot &gt; the current methods.

I've heard before (no sources, sorry, but I'm sure someone can dig it up) that lethal injections cost more than keeping someone for life in prison (this may be completely incorrect, but does not invalidate the following argument). That's honestly pretty silly. If executions were carried out with 1 executioner firing a shot (a rifle preferably, to be sure) at the criminal at a close enough range such that missing is virtually impossible, it would be the most efficient. The only cost would be the few cents that the cartridge of ammunition was worth (also, you have to pay the executioner, but isn't that already a cost with lethal injections?).

Lethal injections also take too much time. Why go through the process of strapping the person in place, inserting needles, injecting chemicals one at a time, and then waiting, and then removing the body? You can simply just shoot them in the head and maybe get some mess but obviously you'd put them in an area where clean-up and body transportation would be very easy.

It makes no difference for the person that's about to die. They are going to die anyways. It's pretty quick too.

As for why not firing squad, instead of having multiple people firing blanks with only 1 true shot, it should just be one person. Why waste the resources of gathering a bunch of people? It shouldn't be hard to find an executioner who will blow off someones head for money. Hell, I'd do that job. A machine that does this would be even more efficient, but the cost may not be worth it.

Executing someone by firearm straight to the head is by far more efficient than death by lethal injections.

Reddit, CMV!

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>8</id><identifier>4vuxcq</identifier><title>CMV: Capital Punishment is never justified.</title><commentCount>118</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4vuxcq/cmv_capital_punishment_is_never_justified/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I think that the state executing a criminal for their crimes cannot be justified. First, the criminal could be proven innocent after the time in which they are executed, and constitutes for around 4% of those criminals that are executed. If capital punishment was not enforced, these people would have been able to live out their lives with government compensation.

Second, it's an easy way out. Some criminals may commit their crimes and regard death as preferable to life in prison, and therefore do not suffer the punishment of their crimes in terms of being held in custody for the rest of their lives - whereas killing these criminals does not allow them to suffer any form of punishment. (We are unaware of what happens in the afterlife, if there is one at all.)

Lastly, what if these criminals have a specific cause? The state killing them merely makes them a martyr to their cause and may encourage others to follow the same cause likewise. Even if their cause does not spread, then dying for their cause is their desire regardless and do not suffer for this.

However, I believe the state does possess authority to kill (such as in wartime), and have no issues with this. But I do not believe that criminals should be killed due to the reasons of uncertainty of guilt, a desire to die rather than be imprisoned, and martyrdom.

**EDIT**
3am here, will reply more tomorrow.
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>9</id><identifier>1zxn5g</identifier><title>I believe those who are "pro-life" but support capital punishment don't care about the sanctity of life, just controlling people's sexuality. CMV.</title><commentCount>101</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1zxn5g/i_believe_those_who_are_prolife_but_support/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Pro-life rhetoric is mostly based on the idea that a fetus is a human being and should therefore be untouchable by anyone, including the woman carrying it. If pro-lifers really are in it for humanity, wouldn't the logical conclusion be for them to be against all killing? Why should it matter what a person has done with their life? Are they still not human? Can someone stop having thoughts or a soul after committing a heinous crime? No, obviously not. So why is it that fetuses are seen as sacred little balls of "life" but once its out of the womb and has been around for a while it's ok to kill it in (up until recent years) the most horrific ways possible? 

*Update*; I changed my mind, you guys. I guess in the "protecting the innocent" line of thinking, opposing abortion and supporting death penalties would make logical sense. 

*Edit*; /u/DevilishRogue expressed interest in whether or not my views on the death penalty and abortion have been changed by this thread. The answer is no, not really. My views on those who are against abortion but support the death penalty have changed. I still believe safe abortions are just one aspect of ensuring women are equal, successful members of society who have every opportunity available to them, and that bodily autonomy is the most basic human right. I also am still on the fence when it comes to capital punishment. On one hand, you have dozens of people who very well deserve to die for their horrific crimes, but on the other hand you have dozens of people who are wrongly convicted. Do we take this imperfect system as it is? Is possibly killing hundreds of innocents an acceptable means to kill those hundreds who deserve it? I'm not sure. For those of you who wish to discuss these topics more, I could make a separate thread upon request. Thank you guys for all your responses.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>10</id><identifier>24hkwe</identifier><title>CMV: I think the death sentence should be abolished</title><commentCount>98</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/24hkwe/cmv_i_think_the_death_sentence_should_be_abolished/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Hey, I'm from Germany and my English is not so good so ill just work with bulletpoints. This is why i think the death sentence is wrong and should be abolished:

* Innocent people have been convicted and executed. 

* The death penalty is incompatible with human rights and human dignity (Even the guilty have a right to life)

* Killing is wrong

* There is a better way to help the families of murder victims (executions do not help these people heal nor do they end their pain)

* Capital punishment goes against almost every religion.

Thanks for all the comments ins advance :)
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>11</id><identifier>41a86a</identifier><title>CMV: Why don't we conduct state-sanctioned capital punishment (death penalty) by the use of a gun?</title><commentCount>98</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/41a86a/cmv_why_dont_we_conduct_statesanctioned_capital/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Currently the primary method to execute the death penalty on a convicted felon is to use lethal injection. There has been a lot of controversy in the recent years surrounding failed attempts in which the person to be executed suffers for hours in tremendous pain. Either due to the drugs being incorrect, the IV being incorrectly played; or any number of other reasons.

It seems to me that this is an extremely inhumane method of killing someone. 

And it goes deeper than the possibility of failure. For my own personal opinion of it, lethal injection would be utter **horror**. I have a serious phobia of needles and drugs. I'd rather die burning alive than receiving a lethal injection. The thought of it, being strapped to a table with an IV jammed into my vein and lethal drugs pumped into my system.. I feel light headed just typing this. 

So the question is, why don't we use a method that is 100% fatal and completely humane, namely a high-powered gun attached to a mechanical trigger (so no one has to hold it manually to fire it) aimed at the back of the neck to sever the spinal cord instantly. 

This would be instantaneous and without any pain for the death row inmate, and far easier to prepare and enact for the prison. 
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>12</id><identifier>1ryer5</identifier><title>Capital Punishment Needs to be Abolished. CMV</title><commentCount>97</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1ryer5/capital_punishment_needs_to_be_abolished_cmv/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>My name is Jared and I am a 10th grader who wrote a research report about capital punishment. In my research, I found that by abolishing the death penalty, states would be able to save money, the innocent wouldn't be killed and our values of what truly is justice would be better served. [This is a serious topic, hateful, ignorant and inappropriate comments will be removed] Here are some of the main points I conveyed in my paper.
I am not asking for people to help my paper. I am asking for your opinions. 


1.People who have been convicted of crimes have to go through endless court appeals, analysis of evidence, and re-trials. This clogs our judicial system with unnecessary paperwork and expenses.

2.Endless appeals combined with the re-trialing of cases cost state and local taxpayers "1 billion dollars in funds" (Deathpenaltyinfo.org)

3) Acts such as mass murders are carried in emotions of anger and retaliation. By funding the death penalty, we create a perpetual cycle of such attitudes which exemplifies that we should murder people to show that murdering is villainous

4) State governments can channel their money towards more beneficial causes such as preventing crime from happening in the first place.


1) As a nation, we have prided ourselves for practicing the values of justice and liberty. However, how can we call are government fair if we still use barbaric measures to justify adequate punishment for criminals?

2) Murder by a citizen would have severe consequences. However, a government-sanctioned murder is not only socially acceptable but “enforceable”

3) However numerous studies have justified that the death as a punishment is no “bigger of a deterrent than throwing someone in jail

4) We send an appalling message to the American people and other countries of the world that we are a nation that uses archaic ways to punish criminals.


2) If we are to advance as a society we must move away from the “eye for an eye mentality". Life without parole is a better alternative than the death penalty because there are no issues regarding morality and doesn't spread hatred

3) People have the ability to change, one such example is Shaka Senghor, who at the age of 19 shot and killed a man. During his incarceration in prison, Shaka Senghor developed a passion for writing and wrote six compelling novels depicting his life growing up on the ghetto streets of Detroit.

4) Shaka lives by the mantra that the actions of his past do not define the person who he is today. In part of his work, Shaka has received numerous accolades from various colleges including the University of Michigan and Wayne State University. He hopes that the victim’s family will forgive him for the actions he had caused when he was younger

Conclusion The lessons of Shaka Senghor, give us greater understanding that the value justice is not the death of criminal but realization of one’s past actions. 

Please remember to be nice when commenting. I am only doing this to see your opinion not cause hatred. 

If you want to see my full essay click here file:///Users/JaredSherman/Downloads/deathpenalty.pdf
</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>13</id><identifier>2265kk</identifier><title>CMV: I think that Capital Punishment requires a level of certainty unachievable by any justice system and should be scraped</title><commentCount>91</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2265kk/cmv_i_think_that_capital_punishment_requires_a/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>In a typical judicial system has punishments ranging from minor to severe that are scaled to specific crimes committed, the highest of these is capital punishment which is execution.

As concepts, ten years of incarceration is ten years of punishment, and two years of community service is two years of (minor) punishment. However death is an infinite punishment (from a secular view point) thus mathematically requiring an infinitely heinous crime of which you are infinitely sure that the accused has committed. Of course this is impossible and therefore the death penalty can never be warranted.

Change my view.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than just downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>14</id><identifier>2bk0qs</identifier><title>CMV: I believe that, in certain cases, capital punishment shouldn't have to be humane.</title><commentCount>89</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2bk0qs/cmv_i_believe_that_in_certain_cases_capital/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>It probably goes without saying that I support capital punishment, if not in practice then at least in principle.

More than that, I find the outcry sparked from the botched executions of rapists and murderers to be somewhat ridiculous. I find nothing ethically wrong with subjecting a condemned man to some measure of suffering before his death. If someone has killed another person by, say, raping and then burying their victim alive, what makes an hour or two of suffering on their way out so unacceptable?

Since Reddit is largely liberal, I'd expect a healthy response, but let me clarify my position before rebuttals are made:

1. My issue is with the ethics of inflicting pain before execution. I'm perfectly aware and agree that according to law anything more than a swift and painless death would be inhumane and therefore illegal.

2. I'm also assuming that such additional suffering would be administered to admitted and unapologetic killers whose crimes were heinous enough to warrant such action. The uncertainty surrounding most court trials would be enough to keep me from supporting any actual policy for this. This is purely meant to discuss the ethics of the "ideal situation".
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>15</id><identifier>2p13uo</identifier><title>CMV: If you knowingly wrongly accuse someone of a crime, you should be exposed to the same minimum and maximum sentence the accused would have been exposed to.</title><commentCount>81</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2p13uo/cmv_if_you_knowingly_wrongly_accuse_someone_of_a/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Everyone, whether they are being truthful or not, knows the consequences of accusing someone else of a crime. You know that they will probably be charged, and you know the order of magnitude of punishment they will receive.

Take a scenario where you knowingly wrongfully accuse someone of murder, and they get the death penalty as a result. I would say that you *murdered* this person and therefore should be exposed to the death penalty yourself in trial. 

This seems to especially apply in cases of rape. While there are no doubt actual rapes that do occur. False accusations of rape have been used as a tool to destroy the lives of others going all the way back to the Jim Crow South, where black men were hung on frivolous rape accusations.

This tradition continues today with cases like the University of Virginia and (this is what I believe, and not the subject of this post) Bill Cosby. 

A person making a legitimate accusation has nothing to fear, but people would think twice before wrongfully accusing others.

I have predicted the generic responses to my argument and will respond to them here.

**Rightful accusers would have something to fear, if the person who victimized them gets away with their crime, they will now face prosection**

This is a good point, but I think that this can be solved by rethinking the way we choose juries. Jury selection in this country is effectively a rigged process, regardless of the location of the trial, the makeup of juries is almost always a homogeneous group of white suburbanites with predictable opinions. This makes it very difficult to convict criminal archetypes like the college rapist, or the malpracticing doctor. By introducing higher racial and socioeconomic diversity into juries, we can eliminate the predictability of verdicts.

**The punishment is harsher than the crime.**

No it isn't. Killing someone is no different than setting a machine in motion that will result in them dying. Tricking the government into locking someone away for 40 years is surely a capital offense, and should be punished as such.

**The perjury charge handles this**

I believe that this is too weak, it is not a capital offense, and it should be.

I am willing to change this view, but it will take some level of convincing. I am eager to hear the responses.  

MODIFICATION OF MY VIEW credit to /u/AMereRedditor:

I now believe that the minimum sentence for the crime that the accuser was accused of is inappropriate, but that the maximum sentence for the attempted version of the same crime is still very much appropriate. (If you are found guilty of knowingly, wrongfully accusing someone of murder, your sentence should be the maximum for attempted murder)
 
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>16</id><identifier>2vsvys</identifier><title>CMV: Capital Punishment should be abolished in the United States</title><commentCount>78</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2vsvys/cmv_capital_punishment_should_be_abolished_in_the/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>The death penalty is an archaic, immoral, and cruel form of punishment. Yet, capital punishment is still a legal practice in 32 U.S. States, and has been used to kill over 1,200 accused criminals since 1977. A fundamental topic that must be assessed when judging the usage of the death penalty is the morality of the practice. Ultimately, the moral question encompassing the practice of capital punishment has less to do with whether those convicted of heinous crimes deserve to die than with whether the government deserves to kill those who it has imprisoned. The government does not have the right nor moral justification to execute criminals. The greatest achievement that comes from the usage of the death penalty is retribution, an achievement that compromises the core of our criminal justice system, which is a system meant to be used primarily for rehabilitation. To kill the person who has killed someone close to you is simply to continue the cycle of violence which ultimately destroys the avenger as well as the offender.

When looking at the statistics of capital punishment, one concept becomes clear: those without the capital, get the punishment. Capital punishment perpetuates social injustices by disproportionately targeting people of color and people who cannot afford good attorneys. The rich simply do not get the death penalty, which is why you’ll never see a person like O.J. Simpson sitting on death row. Death sentences are imposed in a criminal justice system that treats you better if you are rich and guilty than if you are poor and innocent.

However, unlike other sentences which leave room for absolution for those who can prove their innocence at a later date, death is unusually severe in its finality. Once it is taken, a life cannot be given back. The finality and enormity involved with the punishment of death are particularly important to take into consideration when looking at the errors that are made in the conviction of innocent people in the criminal justice system. Since the reinstatement of the modern death penalty, 87 people have been freed from death row because they were later proven innocent. That is a demonstrated error rate of 1 innocent person for every 7 persons executed. An error percentage of this size may not be significant in some cases, however, in the case of capital punishment, where the consequences are matter of life and death, such mistakes cannot be taken lightly. 

The only way to ensure no error is made and innocent people are not killed is by not allowing the practice of capital punishment to occur in the first place.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>17</id><identifier>1xf9jf</identifier><title>I believe it is unjustifiable to support abortion but not the death penalty. CMV</title><commentCount>66</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1xf9jf/i_believe_it_is_unjustifiable_to_support_abortion/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>To be clear, I'm referring to both in a vacuum and as ideals. That is, I mean the idea of the death penalty as the harshest possible sentence for a capital crime in a world where the person sentenced to death is always guilty of the accused crime. I acknowledge that the death penalty in our actual world is highly flawed, but I do not believe this is because of the idea itself. Rather, I believe the flaws of the system are a result of human error, which means they are correctable. 

Likewise, I'm referring to abortion in the sense of a safe, professional environment (in other words, no home/amateur abortions). 

I think that abortion, regardless of when performed, robs a potential human being of its life. Whether you think that a fetus is a human being or not, it is a living mass of tissue that, without intervention, would become a human being with all of the possibilities of happiness and life that we all have. Furthermore, a fetus is innocent of any crime or action that would make it deserve death. Abortion is done for two reasons: either the Mother doesn't want the child or she can't safely have the child. In either case, the child is not at fault (I don't think you can blame developmental/delivery complications on the fetus). 

The death penalty is a punishment for something that a society has deemed crosses a very specific line (like murder). In the case of a death sentence (again, in an ideal), the victim has done something to warrant the sentence. They have broken the rules of the society they live in so severely that they cannot be allowed to have any further part of that society. 

By supporting abortion, but not the death penalty, I think someone is justifying one denial of life but not the other.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>18</id><identifier>22ss7b</identifier><title>CMV: The death penalty can be justified, but the standard of who deserves it should be raised.</title><commentCount>65</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/22ss7b/cmv_the_death_penalty_can_be_justified_but_the/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>There are some crimes so vile, so reprehensible, that those who choose to commit these are often, in my opinion, beyond rehabilitation. The only course of action for these criminals is capital punishment.

However, even the slim possibility of accidentally killing an innocent is something which I cannot abide. What makes us better than the people we're condemning if we accept that collateral damage is a possibility?

I would suggest the following requirements:

- The accused must be over 25 years of age (the median age at which many neurologists say your brain stops developing).
- The accused must be a repeat offender of violent crimes.
- The accused must be declared sane by a neutral, respected psychologist.

I feel that these requirements would all but eliminate the possibility of accidentally killing an innocent, while keeping the death penalty as a possibility for those that truly deserve it.
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than just downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>19</id><identifier>1uh0ln</identifier><title>I believe official misconduct (such as political corruption, accepting brides, judicial or prosecutorial misconduct,police brutality etc) should be capital offense because they undermine the rule of law and breed contempt for modern society, deteriorating the lives of all. CMV</title><commentCount>63</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1uh0ln/i_believe_official_misconduct_such_as_political/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>* Modern society provides great benefit to humanity, therefor I do not reject the imposition of state power.
* Certain values are held as critical and assumed values of the system : Fairness at trial, use of state violence only when necessary, loyalty to the people instead of profit or political interest groups etc
* These values are critical to the acceptance of both the rule of law and the system itself to the individual.  Since no one would accept a system which  acts with indiscriminate indifference to the values of fairness.
* Society requires that the ruling class act blindly to the persuasion of popular or profitable political interests and act in the interests of society and the general population.
* A republic is designed in such a way that a fraction of the population controls the entire population.
* To violate these rules and to act in self interest against principles of fairness, instead of the interest of society causes contempt for modern society because the system becomes unjust.

Therefor it goes to reason that these offenses are of the most serious.  This is the state's version of treason.  It is an act of war against the people.

Objections

 &gt;If people in these positions had to worry about the possibility of constantly being accused of a capital crime, nothing would get done.  No one would become public servants.

I believe instead the best people would become public servants.  Only those with the highest ethical integrity and confidence in their abilities would serve.  And they would do so with little to no rational fear of being accused of such conduct, because they are of sound moral principle.  It is only a person who believes they are incapable of absolute morality and professionalism that would worry about such a thing.  I argue that any efficiency lost (if there was any) would be at great social benefit.

&gt;Murder is a more serious crime because it is direct.  Even if these issue affect millions, no one is directly and physically hurt.  

True, but the same could be said about treason, yet it is a capital offense.  The reasoning being is that it threatens the integrity of the system.  It is therefor one of the most serious and egregious offenses.   This is not to say that I believe that removing the capital offense status of treason justifies these offenses as being non capital offenses. 

&gt; Someone who is innocent could have their lives put in jeopardy, all because they want to serve the public.  They could end up in jail for life or worse.

This is a critique on the justice system.  Your problem is with a system that is capable and often does subject innocent people to unfair punishment and sometimes death.  In a world where justice is truly blind, fair and all people who are innocent are exonerated with little effort needed to prove their innocence, this objection carries no weight.  

&gt;We hold that these people should be held to a "higher standard." 

 I reject this notion and replace it with "the highest standard."  If the continuity of the system is the highest priority, people who serve it, should be held to the highest standard.

*For the sake of clarification I do not believe in the death penalty, because it is impossible to know with 100% certainty the innocence or guilt of someone, I believe it is immoral for the state to execute even one person.  It also does not act as a deterrent and lowers us to the level of condoning state sanctioned murder.  This argument goes only so far as to state that I believe these offenses should be capital offenses, and are treated in manners similar to other capital offenses.*

</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>20</id><identifier>46pqyr</identifier><title>CMV: Most people who have committed a serious crime (e.g. murder) are just ordinary human beings who briefly lapsed into a dark, impulsive state of mind beyond their control - and we are all capable of experiencing this same phenomenon under the right circumstances.</title><commentCount>66</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/46pqyr/cmv_most_people_who_have_committed_a_serious/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Neuroscience tells us that everything *psychological* is *biological*. This obviously extends to murderers, rapists, and other people who commit heinous crimes. And sure, you have your garden-variety sociopaths and sadists, the ones who either don’t care about the pain they cause others or otherwise relish in it, but I don't think they are anywhere near as common as people tend to think. No, I strongly believe that many of people in prison or on death row experienced something along the lines of severe dissociation, or a psychotic break. But regardless of what terminology you apply to it, my point is that almost nobody in their right mind would violently rape or murder anyone.

To put things in layman's terms, there is sometimes a different person "at the wheel" when such a crime is committed (in a figurative sense). The one who’s being convicted and sentenced is receiving punishment for something that was literally beyond their control at the time. It's like a real-life Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, except that everyone's hatred is being directed at the former for crimes that were committed by the latter. And unlike Dr. Jekyll, it was never their choice to transform into a monster.

This is why I am so uncomfortable with the idea of capital punishment, and why I have empathy for those on death row. When I hear people talking about how they want criminals to be put to death, I essentially hear them saying that they want *me* to be put to death. In an abstract sense, I *am* that inmate on death row. Most of them are no different from the rest of us. And I do not have one iota of faith in our ability to discern the “normal” defendants from the genuine sociopaths. If someone does not display any remorse, it could well be because they have none – *or* it could be because the defendant (rightly) believes that no amount of remorse could ever redeem them in the eyes of their victims for what they’ve done, and outwardly showing compassion would only add another layer of complexity to their suffering. Society does not give much credence to insanity defenses, but even if they did, it wouldn’t make any real difference. The defendant would still wind up institutionalized, deprived of virtually all privileges that ordinary people enjoy, and left with no prospect of ever leading a normal life. Whether they are actually convicted or acquitted by reason of insanity, the most important thing in everyone’s mind is that the person is made to suffer. I honestly don’t think anybody really cares about how the brain factors into the equation.

**Edit** - I've changed the wording slightly. I shouldn't have said that the *overwhelming majority* of people in prison or on death row are there because they had a psychotic break, but I'm sure a lot of them are. Also, this is less to do with serial killers or other genuinely bad people, and more to do with those who committed one-off "crimes of passion".</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>21</id><identifier>1ogb47</identifier><title>I hold no value for human life and believe that no single human life or death holds any significance. CMV</title><commentCount>60</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1ogb47/i_hold_no_value_for_human_life_and_believe_that/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>For as long as I can remember I have been completely desensitised to death. I don't cry at funerals and I don't really mourn, not because I didn't love the person but because I think that all human beings are unimportant. I think the reasoning behind this is basically that over 180 billion people have died over time and only a tiny portion of those are remembered and even fewer are cared about. Ultimately we are all going to die and yeah people will mourn but when they also die, no one will care about us anymore. Me feeling like this is why I am for capital punishment and don't get shocked by murders or war. A lot of people think it makes me coldhearted or just a bastard. So CMV</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>22</id><identifier>2nxt7j</identifier><title>CMV: It is hypocritical to be both pro-gun and staunchly pro-life.</title><commentCount>56</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2nxt7j/cmv_it_is_hypocritical_to_be_both_progun_and/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Edit: "Pro-gun", as I'm using it, is a stance supporting personal gun ownership on the basis of the 2nd Amendment and personal protection. This topic isn't about moderates who only support gun use for hobbies and recreation.

**tl;dr, or the way I should've phrased the thread initially: CMV: Abortion is a form of self-defense. Those who believe you have the right to use deadly force in self-defense should also support abortion in at least some cases, if not all.** 

The main justification for being pro-gun is that people need guns to defend themselves. Unique to arguing that people should carry guns as opposed to pepper spray or other self-defense tools is that guns are used to kill, not incapacitate. By being pro-gun, you are pro-giving people the right to choose to kill another person. A circumstance in which you would be allowed to do so under the castle doctrine, stand your ground laws, etc. would be that the other person is threatening your property or body. Pro-gun activists can't really argue that you have to know your attacker intends to kill you, as by the time you know they mean to kill you (as opposed to rob you, assault you, etc.) it's likely too late for your gun to be effective. Ultimately, the pro-gun argument relies on one ordinary person being given the power to decide to end someone else's life, without the need for lengthy deliberation that state-administered capital punishment requires.

Next, the main justification for being pro-life is that fetuses have "personhood" and deserve the same rights as people. If you're pro-gun, however, you're arguing that someone has the right to kill another person if that person is intruding on their property or threatening their body. This definitively rules out cases where the mother's health is at risk and the mother would choose to preserve her own life first, as in [the infamous recent case of a woman dying in Ireland of medical complications after being denied an abortion.](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_of_Savita_Halappanavar) However, it can be more broadly applied to other, less critical abortions. For the same reason you would be justified in shooting to kill someone who is assaulting you or entering your home, you should be justified in killing someone who is literally occupying your body for months. At the very least, abortion must be legalized in cases of rape, as you never consented to even the possibility of having a person invade your body/property. 

This doesn't mean pro-gun people are in any way obligated to personally prefer abortion for themselves (just as they may not choose to shoot an intruder within their home), but they should support legal abortion on the basis that others should be given that choice. 

A counterargument I can foresee is that to someone who is pro-gun, an attacker forfeits their right to life by being a criminal, and fetuses are innocent. However, this argument doesn't really fly. Firstly, there's no way of knowing why an intruder has entered your home - maybe they were forced to by someone else or coerced into it. Secondly, even if a fetus has technically not consciously committed a crime, it is still by its very existence invading another person's body/property if that person did not consent to it being there. If you invite a person/fetus into your home/body you don't have the right to kill them, but in order to remain logically consistent you should be able to remove them with deadly force in both cases.

Finally, there's no corollary here - because pro-choice arguments don't rely on personhood, there's no hypocrisy in being pro-gun rights or pro-gun control because it's a completely separate issue.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>23</id><identifier>1pflp3</identifier><title>I believe we must remove countries, and establish a global state is essential to our species advancement and survival. CMV.</title><commentCount>52</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1pflp3/i_believe_we_must_remove_countries_and_establish/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>*My view is not whether this is possible, or to do with the logistics required; my view is that this "Global State" is preferable (even necessary).*

My belief is not to put one man, or one party into power over the Globe. It would be to consider Earth as a single nation;

* **Equal Universal Healthcare**
*This would ensure no human dies from an illness, that, perhaps a in country more advanced, would be considered treatable and/or reversible. The quality of healthcare no longer depends on your insurance or financial situation*

* **Equal &amp; Free Education**
*Every human has the same opportunities at expanding his understanding of the Universe, thus further helping advancement. No longer would your family's financial situation, environment, race, creed, etc. determine your knowledge or chances.*

* **Equal food, clothing, shelter**
*The nutritional quality of what you eat and drink, how warm or cold you are during the seasons would not depend on what social class you were born into.*


* **One set of laws, constitution, etc.**
*No man would be sentenced to death for a crime when, in a different nation, he would be given a fine and let go. Capital punishment would be abolished.*

With this system, people are seen as such; not American, Canadian, Chinese, Russian...we are seen as Humans, and no other denomination. 

It has been stated that the survival of our species depends on colonizing other planets. There would be one space program, and it would be of high importance in the scientific field. No longer will people work against each other to be the first nation to explore the cosmos.

Disputes among nations would end, and different nationalities and religions would, over time, live in harmony as opposed to war.

As we settle the problems we face on the Global Stage, we prepare for the problems we face on the Interstellar Stage.

[I invite you to challenge, and change my view](http://i.imgur.com/1o5QhuH.png)</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>24</id><identifier>1q2av0</identifier><title>I believe that capital punishment is a just punishment for people who have committed a murderous crime. CMV</title><commentCount>52</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1q2av0/i_believe_that_capital_punishment_is_a_just/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>  This topic for me has been a debated one when i mention it to people i know.  I think for acts such as pre-meditated murder, murdering someone in the heat of another offence such as theft or rape, and murders committed through gang on gang violence and such should be eligible for capital punishment.

  My reasons for thinking is are because while the offender has ended someones life and hurt many other people in the process, the consequences for their actions is a roof over their head, a meal every day and resources, completely off of society's back.  Coming from the UK this might seem a tad strange but when i look at america's system, so much money is funneled into keeping these people alive, when there are honest people at the bottom scraping along.  Why should someone who believed they had the right to end someone elses life take priority over a good citizen.

  One thing i have taken into consideration is the fact of what if they get it wrong, and that 1 wrong sentence is 1 too many.  I see that argument and i just see the statistics and, however horrible it may be, i think the pro's out way the con's in that respect.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>25</id><identifier>4w37jf</identifier><title>CMV: A government has no right to kill its citizens i.e. capital punishment</title><commentCount>55</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4w37jf/cmv_a_government_has_no_right_to_kill_its/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I'm from Australia and we don't allow the legal system to kill those who are deemed 'unworthy' or 'unable' re-enter society as moral humans. The usual *folk* story for this is that the last man who was hung was for abducting and murdering a man who was later found healthy and un-harmed. This forms the basis of my belief, the legal system is not infallible and has often passed wrong or biased judgements, thus, shouldn't have the ability to pass absolutely final rulings. Also, I believe that if a life is worth more than any amount of money so financial reasons will not move me.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>26</id><identifier>2kje1f</identifier><title>CMV: I Believe the Death Penalty in the United States Should Be Abolished</title><commentCount>48</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2kje1f/cmv_i_believe_the_death_penalty_in_the_united/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>3,049 inmates are currently awaiting execution in the 32 states that still allow capital punishment in the United States, why is this the case? Trials seeking the death penalty often cost anywhere from four to ten times the amount than a trial that does not seek the death penalty (and results in life imprisonment instead), and the taxpayers are held responsible for these costs. States that have abolished the death penalty are able to use these funds to support local police, fire departments, schools, etc. instead of deciding whether or not a crime is punishable by death. 
I have seen arguments stating that the death penalty serves as a deterrent for the heinous crimes punishable by death, but this is simply not the case. According to the FBI crime reports, the Southern United States has the highest average murder rates, even though 80% of executions take place there. While the northeast, which accounts for less than 1% of all executions, had the lowest murder rates.
 In regards to the rest of the world, the UN secretary general, has called on member states that still use the death penalty to abolish this practice, stressing that the right to life lies at the heart of international human rights. I believe this is the case, despite how terrible the crime is. It isn’t like they won’t be spending the rest of their lives in a monotonous routine behind bars anyways. Change my view.


_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>27</id><identifier>1m2ysl</identifier><title>I believe that morality is subjective, and that right and wrong is simply up to the opinion of the majority - CMV.</title><commentCount>46</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1m2ysl/i_believe_that_morality_is_subjective_and_that/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I think that what we view as right and wrong is simply what the majority of society views as views as right and wrong, which we are then taught.

* If there were some objective moral standard, there would be little to no debate over things like abortion, capital punishment, etc. because everyone would be able to agree that those issues are either right or wrong.

* What is right and wrong changes over time. 200 years ago in the US, it was okay to own a slave. Some people viewed this as immoral, but were a minority at the time. Looking back on it now, we say that it is immoral, but that is casting our current standards of morality on a previous time. If you were born in that time (or perhaps an earlier one when it was even more accepted), you would not think it was wrong to own a person.

* Different areas have different standards of morals. In some Middle-Eastern countries, it is okay to stone an adulteress. In Western countries, the majority says that this is wrong, so we think it is immoral. In those countries however, this is not necessarily true. You cannot say that we are right and they are wrong without presupposing that there is some objective standard that we can compare it to.

* Things like murder, robbery, etc. are almost universally accepted as wrong because everyone can agree that it is detrimental to society. Just because almost everyone agrees that something is bad does not mean it is objectively bad, just that the majority consensus is that it is immoral.

I hope one of you can CMV!</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>28</id><identifier>1fzlwq</identifier><title>I believe that the use of capital punishment is a viable punishment for heinous crimes. CMV</title><commentCount>43</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1fzlwq/i_believe_that_the_use_of_capital_punishment_is_a/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>The use of capital punishment is the ultimate incentive not to commit crimes. Being from the United States, it is not, in my opinion, a form of cruel and unusual punishment and should be allowed to continue.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>29</id><identifier>1ek9g7</identifier><title>The death penalty should be WIDELY implemented for repeat offenders- people who have demonstrated time and time again that they cannot operate within society. CMV.</title><commentCount>39</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1ek9g7/the_death_penalty_should_be_widely_implemented/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>To set some background information (please note that the following idea is not up for CMV, at least for purposes of this discussion):

I do not believe in universal human rights. Rights are the precious product of civilization. They are protected and granted by members of a society coming together, forming a mutual contract that seeks to serve in the best interest of all by demanding a small sacrifice and obedience from behalf of all. As gifts of society, rights can, at any moment, be taken away by society.

Country of residence: United States, which has capital punishment laws, but are rare and difficult to carry out.

Rehabilitation is good, IF the cost to society is outweighed by the potential gains. For criminals who have committed a single deplorable act, rehabilitation SHOULD be the first consideration. The value of a human life is its utility to society. If there is a potential utility that can be re-accessed without too much cost in terms of resources and personnel, then I am all for rehabilitation. 

However, not all criminals are able to benefit from rehabilitation into society, as our prisons filled with repeat offenders demonstrate. For these individuals, who have demonstrated time and time again that they are utterly incapable of changing their ways, the most logical choice is immediate summary execution (preferably mandatory organ donation). Humans who cannot exercise the ability to control themselves within a society should not be treated as humans, but as the lower functioning animals that they are. These are the cancers that eat away at the whole- unable to be cured, a burden to maintain, and of absolutely no utility to society. 

To increase the rate of capital punishments, repeat offenders should not be given the same level of trial time and consideration. They are not worth the resources. The justice system is already capable of making mistakes, and that is why the limited resources that it has should be spent on those who have committed only limited offenses, since their guilt is much less certain then those who already have been convicted multiple times. Also, there should not be a separate trial to determine guilt, and another one to determine eligibility for the death penalty, which greatly increases cost (United States).

</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>30</id><identifier>4a527w</identifier><title>CMV: Politicians Evolving On Issues is Not a Good Thing</title><commentCount>38</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4a527w/cmv_politicians_evolving_on_issues_is_not_a_good/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Disclaimer: this is not meant as a semi-veiled attack at Hillary Clinton, though it may certainly apply.

_____

Often, we hear about politicians "evolving" on issues, which is really just a code word for "changing their mind." They may be against abortion or capital punishment or gay marriage at one point, and be convinced of the opposing point of view at a later one.

By itself, changing your mind is not a problem. I respect people who can consider other points of view and adjust their own views accordingly.

However, the purpose of a political candidate is to be a proxy for their voters' opinions. When you vote for a political candidate, you are (ideally) aware of their issue positions and feel like they best represent you. You make the informed decision that electing that candidate is the best way to advance your personal political agenda.

When politicians evolve on issues, they may no longer represent the opinions of those who elected them. That, in turn, defeats the purpose of electing them to begin with. In a representative democracy, a politician supposedly represents the views of those who elected them. The mechanism for change isn't changing your mind, it's electing a new candidate.

By changing their views on important issues, politicians may in effect be saying that they don't care so much about representing a particular set of views as they do about being elected again. But even if you remove that bit of cynicism, it's simply risky to vote for a politician that may change their view (for whatever reason, good or bad), because they may not represent you properly.

**TL;DR**: people changing their views is admirable. Politicians changing their positions is bad for representative democracy.

_____

Edit: I'm heading out to watch the Sounders game, but I'll try to get some more debating in during halftime. I'll certainly respond to everybody who comments after the game is over.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>31</id><identifier>3vg5ow</identifier><title>CMV: Capital Punishment is consistent with the way modern nation states claim sovereignty over the life and death of their citizens, and in special cases such as in war, of non-citizens. Capital punishment isn't cruel and unusual; it's a logical extension of the powers granted to nation states.</title><commentCount>29</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3vg5ow/cmv_capital_punishment_is_consistent_with_the_way/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Some things to consider: 

* If killing an enemy combatant is morally or legally permissible, then shouldn't capital punishment also be morally or legally permissible? If I agree in principle that the State I belong to has the authority to claim the life of another human being, say an Iraqi or an Afghani, how can I argue that it does not have that authority in my home country? Is the life of an Iraqi or Afghani somehow less valuable than mine? 
* If a State can draft its citizens and throw them into the firing line (with legal justifications), and if a State requires soldiers to obey commands that may lead directly to their deaths (also with legal justifications), then shouldn't that same State also have the authority to kill its citizens (with legal justifications) in criminal courts? If I grant that a State may kill its citizens with legal justifications in some circumstances (in war), than how can I argue that it cannot do so (again with legal justifications) in others (in criminal courts)? Why the artificial border? </selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>32</id><identifier>3ccpvj</identifier><title>CMV: Countries should not strip people of their citizenship except in cases of fraud.</title><commentCount>31</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3ccpvj/cmv_countries_should_not_strip_people_of_their/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Recently, a number of countries such as Canada, the UK, and Australia have seriously proposed or enacted laws which would strip certain persons of their citizenship for various acts, usually related to terrorism or supporting foreign governments.  For instance, [Canada recently passed such a law](http://www.ctvnews.ca/canada/what-dual-citizens-need-to-know-about-bill-c-24-the-new-citizenship-law-1.2426968) and has begun using it.  Since it's the one I'm most familiar with, my argument will focus on it, but is I think fairly generic.

I think such laws are bad for the following reasons:

1.  They violate core norms of liberal democratic states.  It is a core principle that no matter what you have done, your civil rights are not stripped from you entirely.  Even the worst criminals have the right to be presumed innocent, to due process, and to re-enter society if and when their sentences are up.  Stripping someone of their citizenship violates this norm by openly attempting to strip core civil rights, including the right to re-enter society after their sentence is done.

2. If someone is such a danger to society that they need to be banished, then they should be sentenced to life in prison, or to death.  And if they are sentenced to life in prison or to death, then stripping their citizenship doesn't accomplish anything meaningful, except possibly denying them the right to vote.  If the crime of which they have been convicted is not severe enough to merit a sentence that never lets them free again, then by the own admission of the law, that person should be allowed to reenter society, not be banished from their country.  Treason is, as far as I am aware, a capital offense in nearly all countries.

3.  In most cases, these laws are being applied ex post facto.  Banishment is a criminal punishment that dates back a very long time.  Stripping citizenship amounts to banishment, and is a criminal punishment.  You can't add ex post facto criminal punishments onto crimes.  Indeed, the new Canadian law is already being used [in just such a fashion](https://news.vice.com/article/canada-puts-new-law-to-use-moves-to-revoke-citizenship-of-convicted-terrorist).

4.  By stripping only those with a second citizenship, as Canada's law does, the law does not provide equal protection to all citizens.  Some citizens are subject to the punishment of citizenship stripping, and others are not, often due to circumstances wholly outside their control such as who their parents are.  That's a massive equal protection problem.  And to apply it equally would be to make stateless persons with no citizenship, which is also a huge human rights problem.

5.  Removal of citizenship normally requires mutual consent, and it is hypocritical for the government to not require that.  If, for instance, I were to unilaterally declare myself not a citizen of my home country, have that declaration rejected by my home country, then engage in an act of treason, my unilateral unaccepted declaration would provide me no defense.  Likewise, a government should not be able to do the opposite and deprive people of their rights as citizens even where those citizens do not consent to be deprived of those rights.

I think it is appropriate to nullify citizenship which is fraudulently obtained.  In those cases, the person would not be a citizen but for fraud, and never legitimately had a claim to be a citizenship.  But once someone's a citizen, it should be permanent.

Also, the question of what to do about citizenship in areas that break away (such as Scotland or Quebec might have) is very interesting, but not really what this is about.  This is about stripping individuals based on their behavior, not entire peoples based on forming a new nation.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>33</id><identifier>3wpctt</identifier><title>CMV:I believe the Death Penalty should be legal BUT only for those who are dangerous to society.</title><commentCount>30</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3wpctt/cmvi_believe_the_death_penalty_should_be_legal/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I have read the arguments against the death penalty in general, and I understand it, some sentenced to death are mentally disabled or wrongly accused, and that is horrific. However, the death penalty is also important to keep the public safe, and I believe that we should legalise the death penalty to those who put the public at risk: For example serial killers, Cartel leaders who escape prison(one of my main reasons for this point of view) or repeat offenders of *serious* crimes.

I believe most top tier crimes should have life imprisonment as a maximum, however if a convict has proven to be especially dangerous and there is potential for them to escape and further harm the public, they should be killed to prevent it from occuring.

Just to clarify, I believe these people must have conclusive evidence against them before escalating to the capital punishment, so this punishment is a rare one that isnt lazily thrown out and used.

NOTE: Im in England so forgive me if I am not aware of US specific points.
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>34</id><identifier>1blyvc</identifier><title>I believe that Saudi Arabia has a just legal system. CMV</title><commentCount>29</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1blyvc/i_believe_that_saudi_arabia_has_a_just_legal/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Many "human rights" groups attack the Saudi Arabian laws for their discrimination of women and homosexuals, and use of corporal and capital punishment (beheadings, amputations, and stonings), but I believe that the Saudi Arabian legal system is just. If the people of Saudi Arabia were entirely free to opt-out of this legal system, I believe that the Saudi Arabian legal system would be the most just possible.

While my ideal society would not bear the same intolerant features of Saudi Arabian society, I believe that the Saudi Arabian legal system's dedication to the Quran shows true legal integrity. Whereas in the United States, we are constantly having our constitutional rights trampled by representatives of the majority, the legal system of Saudi Arabia is static and respects the rights and founding principles elaborated in the Quran.

You might argue that Saudi royals and other elites are given unfair treatment by the courts, but to me this is a petty concern when compared to the violation of constitutional rights in the USA that affects hundreds of millions of people. What's more, high-ranking politicians and other elites receive similar unfair treatment in the democratic West as well.

You might also argue that certain legal and fact-finding procedures are shaky, but such is the case for all legal systems of the world. Science and epistemology are not to the point of sophistication that we can presently convict every criminal with 100% certainty. The fact that we don't presently have a perfect technology of justice does not show a flaw in the Saudi Arabian legal system that cannot also be seen in any other legal system.

To summarize, I believe Saudi Arabia's legal system is just only because of its dedication to its founding documents, i.e. the Quran, sunnahs, etc. Western democracy has allowed representatives of majorities to trample the constitutional rights of minorities, and in many cases majorities as well, and I believe that this is unjust. Whatever deficiencies the actual legal system - not laws specficially - might have, I believe most Western countries share these as well.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>35</id><identifier>29xqzm</identifier><title>CMV:I belive that men over the age of 30 who have sex with a minor should be castrated.</title><commentCount>26</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/29xqzm/cmvi_belive_that_men_over_the_age_of_30_who_have/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I know this is a touchy subject and most people will go with the capital punishment law, however I currently believe that we let these guys off too easy and they will think it's okay to do again and again Honesty if some sicko did this to your child and caught them what would you do? I'm only 23 and this subject angers me greatly

I chose the age of 30 because I believe the age gap between 30 and 17 (or younger) is too big

I feel like this should be only done for sexual crimes because I don't think anybody could possibly get turned on by murder I could be wrong though.

I belive castration would be a suitable punnishment because you wouldn't really be able to rape a minor with out a penis.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>36</id><identifier>23rt7y</identifier><title>CMV: I view the recent killings by a mob in China as citizens exercising a lost natural right</title><commentCount>26</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/23rt7y/cmv_i_view_the_recent_killings_by_a_mob_in_china/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>First time posting here and terrible title I know.

Anyways, this is the incident that made me think about this: http://tyger.ac/posts/3196/frame. **Edit: WARNING. THERE IS GORE IN SOME OF THE PICTURES AFTER THE ARTICLE.** Didn't see the album originally. Sorry. The series is so morbid but I'd recommend powering through if you have the stomach. Well moving on...

A mob in China killed 4 police after the cops beat a man's head in with a sledge-hammer, killing him, for filming them harass some woman vending on the street.

As I understand John Locke's theory of a social contract, when society is in a "state of nature", delivering justice for crimes falls to the aggrieved party and this is a natural right. Unfortunately, the punishments are *hugely* prone to bias, error, and are often unusually cruel. When a state forms a government, this natural right is transferred from the populous to the government. This should be a good thing. The government is bound to provide unbiased and fair protection and justice to its people.

So what happens when the government fails to uphold its duties? The police killed by the mob otherwise would have certainly gotten away with their crimes as they have in the past. Also, (slightly contradictory) China has a 99.9% trial conviction rate which is so high I doubt little if any justice is achieved.

Although I feel that all parties acted with disgusting excessive brutality, I also feel that the people in the mob were in the right when they killed the officers. They took back one of their natural rights which had been not upheld by their government for some time now.


Lastly, my answers to some arguments I anticipate receiving so please also address them if you'd like to bring the topics up:

1) This mob is hardly comparable to KKK lynch mobs.

2) While protests can change the hearts and minds of people in addition to potentially influencing future state policy, just remember how well the Tiananmen Square protests worked out.

Change my view! Political philosophy is not one of my strong suits and I'm sure you guys have some interesting thoughts! And before I get any hate mail, I'd like to mention that I am against capital punishment and am a pacifist. Hate on me for that if you'd like hah.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>37</id><identifier>1jdx7b</identifier><title>In principle, I am not against the death penalty. CMV.</title><commentCount>23</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1jdx7b/in_principle_i_am_not_against_the_death_penalty/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Let me begin by stating that I am against the death penalty for practical reasons, i.e. that it is cheaper to keep a prisoner in jail for life than to deal with the issues, such as appeals, that surround the death penalty. I am also a pretty liberal person overall, and I am not necessarily supportive of the death penalty either.

That having been said, in a hypothetical case in which someone is guilty beyond doubt of a horrible crime, I cannot see a reason to be against capital punishment. But I am open to changing my mind. Reddit, why is it philosophically wrong for the state to kill people?</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>38</id><identifier>28964m</identifier><title>CMV: Against Capital Punishment</title><commentCount>23</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/28964m/cmv_against_capital_punishment/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I am generally against the use of the death penalty on moral reasons for practically every reason other than crimes against humanity, as I think killing another person is an issue that concerns humanity in general. I don't think it has moral use for other heinous crimes such as murder or rape in practically every circumstance. I can see why people here have the opposite opinion and so I'm willing to change my mind. I'm hoping to hear something new though, and not just an argument saying how bad some examples are.

Edit: My moral reasons rest in the fact that killing a person is against humanity. Therefore capital punishment should be used for something that goes against humanity itself.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>39</id><identifier>25l2yq</identifier><title>CMV: It is not hypocritical to oppose abortion but support the death penalty.</title><commentCount>22</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/25l2yq/cmv_it_is_not_hypocritical_to_oppose_abortion_but/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>The standard pro-life argument is that a fetus is a person with the same moral status as any other human, and that killing one is therefore murder. Inversely, a murderer has voluntarily given up his right to life by choosing to kill someone else. I don't believe that killing a convicted murderer and killing someone who has literally done nothing are morally equivalent.

Note that I am pro-choice and oppose capital punishment; I just don't think people who disagree with me are necessarily hypocrites.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>40</id><identifier>20tr54</identifier><title>CMV: No argument for death penalty is moral or logical and it should be replaced by full Life Without Parole (LWOP)</title><commentCount>21</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/20tr54/cmv_no_argument_for_death_penalty_is_moral_or/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I do not see any arguments for the death penalty to be moral and logical.  If you can come up with logical and moral argument please let me hear it. Outside of no moral or logical argument I also have other issues which I will list than give further detail after:

1. Innocence 

2. Cost 

3. Morality 

4. Victims family

5. Attorney skill

6. Deterrence. 

7. Future Technology

	
**Innocence**: 
People are convicted  of crimes and sentence to death, sometimes for crimes they didn’t commit. When DNA testing came out, it helped prove 18 people were actually innocent. However, that doesn’t mean new cases, even with DNA testing are 100% accurate. The last exoneration was March 11, 2014 
[SOURCE](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/innocence-list-those-freed-death-row). That was a week and a day ago. However, he was convicted 30 years ago, on 1984. He was the first man to be exonerated this year.  Now, it was great that he *didn’t* get killed. He was innocent. However, think if just a few more years went by and he *did* get killed. Is it worth killing people who are convicted of a crime when you may end up killing an innocent person? (Many people will claim that killing innocent people is morally wrong)

**Cost**: 
It can cost about 70% more than cases in which LWOP is sought. The median cost is $1.26 million, and LWOP cost had a median cost of $741,000. Tennessee has an average cost of 48% more than the average cost of LWOP, Maryland death penalty cases cost 3 times more than LWOP, and California spends $137 million per year, when it could spend $11.5 million if all cases were LWOP.

[SOURCE](http://www.kslpa.org/docs/reports/04pa03a.pdf).

So not only might you be killing an innocent man, tax-payers (you and I) are spending a lot of money on holding these “dangerous criminals” (Yes, some are indeed dangerous, but you can’t tell which ones are) for their execution. 

**Morality**: 

Many people will tell you that killing someone is wrong. How can you morally justify the murder of someone who is convicted of murder? If killing someone is wrong, why are we killing people? Not only is this a morality problem, it’s also illogical. If something is wrong or bad, we should not do it. This is holding a double standard. 

**Victims Family**:

Obviously the loss of a loved one is very painful and not something anyone wants to experience. However, when on death row you have countless and long trials and appeals. The family must be reminded of this horrific event over and over during this period of time, making the pain fresh every time.

**Attorney Skill**: 
A skilled attorney may be able to negotiate LWOP for his client, however, not all attorneys are good enough to do this. This means that someone may live or die based on how skilled their attorney is, and makes it rather random. 

**Deterrence**: 

&gt;It is very clear that deterrents are not effective in the area of capital punishment," said Dr. Jonathan Groner, an associate professor of surgery at Ohio State University College of Medicine and Public Health 
If the death penalty was used to try and stop people from committing violent crimes, it isn’t working. The old saying is to not fix something that isn’t broken. Clearly it is broken and does not work, and therefore, should be fixed. 

** Future Technology** 
DNA testing came up and proved the innocence of 18 people. Who knows when, or what the next technology will come up that can prove the innocence of even one single person. As long as technology is always advancing, we always will have new ways to prove someone is innocent. 


</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>41</id><identifier>38iyph</identifier><title>CMV: Capital punishment is ethically untenable and should be abolished where it is currently practiced</title><commentCount>24</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/38iyph/cmv_capital_punishment_is_ethically_untenable_and/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I am basing this opinion on several points. 

To begin with, my view is a natural consequence of my personal belief that **every human being has a right on living**, a principle that is listed in [Article 3](http://www.claiminghumanrights.org/udhr_article_3.html) of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights - which has been signed by the United States of America, where Capital Punishment is legalized in some states -, [Article 2](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Article_2_of_the_European_Convention_on_Human_Rights) of the European Convention on Human Rights) and more. 

The death penalty is strictly opposed to this tenet. While some people may agree, that by commiting certain crimes such as child molestion, mass murder, et al. forfeit their basic human rights, this is a highly subjective point of view that cannot be unambiguously established, as opinions regarding this topic vary  between the various religions, cultures and nations.

Another reason why Capital Punishment should be abolished, is that it is not a punishment in real terms, but merely a "solution", to satisfy the immediate need for equal retaliation according to the principle of "an eye for an eye". By punishing murderers or similar offenders with murder, the judicial system essentially lowers itself to an ethical level akin to that of said offenders. While this is technically a kind of punishment, it is not the one we should advocate, as it conflicts with the moral principles we have determined for ourselves.

Furthermore, the fact that death is a final event - an irreversible one - means, that juridical mistakes have a much bigger consequences. If an innocent is erroneously put under arrest for years, he can still be released and even compensated once his innocence has been proven, but you cannot revive an innocent who was killed for something he did not commit.

Additionally, Capital Punishment is even [economically](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/costs-death-penalty) more unfavorable than imprisonment, mainly due to higher defense costs for a death row candidate.

Resting upon these aspects, I hold the firm belief that Capital Punishment is ethically wrong and unjustified, while also being more of an economical burden than imprisonment.

(Note: Because English is not my native language, parts of my reasoning may be wrong or not make any sense. Thank you for your understanding.)

EDIT: I would like to add, that I am in favor of deliberately ending your own life and consensual suicide. Inmates should have the right to end their life, if they voice their opinion in a stable, mental state.
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>42</id><identifier>3f73cy</identifier><title>CMV: Constitutional "originalist" interpretation of the Eighth Amendment cannot justify taking inflation into account, and thus any bail or fine that the Framers and/or Americans in general would have considered excessive in 1791 should be considered unconstitutional by originalists.</title><commentCount>21</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3f73cy/cmv_constitutional_originalist_interpretation_of/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Originalism is a constitutional interpretive doctrine in which one reads the provisions of the Constitution to retain the meaning that they had when they were originally adopted.  Thus, an originalist (such as Justice Scalia) would say that if the First Amendment was not understood to prohibit public school prayer in 1791, it should not do so today; and if the Fourteenth Amendment was not understood to guarantee a right to same-sex marriage in 1868, it should not do so today.  The rationale for this is that the people, through their representatives, only actually properly ratified those original meanings, so those are the only meanings that should be considered law.  I take no position, in this post, on the correctness of this general originalist philosophy or its underlying justification, except that at the very least I don't think it's blatantly *un*-reasonable.

In interviews and concurrences/dissents, Scalia often brings up the Eighth Amendment in explaining his philosophy, and his frustration with the idea that current Supreme Court precedent applies the "evolving standards of decency" test, which he passionately opposes. As I understand it, the standard originalist argument against the extension of the Cruel and Unusual Punishments clause of the Eighth Amendment to, say, the death penalty, goes something like this:

* The people adopted the Eighth Amendment in 1791, and thus forbade "cruel and unusual punishments".  
* Another amendment (the Fifth) adopted at the same time specified some rights of a defendant charged with a capital offense.  Captial offense means one you can be executed for.
* Moreover, they kept on executing felons afterwards, and no one really thought this was incompatible with the Bill of Rights they had just passed.
* Thus, the Eighth Amendment can't possibly prohibit the death penalty.

Of course, this is entirely correct, assuming principles of originalism.  So, thus, the originalist-interpreted Eighth Amendment prohibits only those punishments that were considered "cruel and unusual" in 1791.

Now, I think it has to go the other way, too.  So if, hypothetically, the modern government wanted to torture someone as punishment, I think any originalist would have to call that unconstitutional as well, even if there was popular support for it, since that was clearly one of the things the Eighth Amendment proscribed when it was adopted.  

So, it seems to me that the proper originalist reading of the Eighth Amendment is one where it prohibits some discrete set of punishments (such as those involving torture), a set whose elements are defined as those punishments that the Framers and/or American society would have found "cruel and unusual" (compared to the crime) in 1791, and that set cannot ever change, regardless of how society or the Supreme Court or anything else changes.  Nothing can be added to or removed from that set without a Constitutional amendment.  

Fine.  But what basis is there, then, for not using the same rule when interpreting the *other* provisions of the Eighth Amendment?  If the same logic is used, the Excessive Bail and Excessive Fines clauses should be interpreted as forbidding a discrete set of bail amounts and fines (paired with certain crimes) that were considered "excessive" by the Framers and/or American society in 1791.  **And that set can never change, regardless of how society or the Supreme Court or anything else changes.**

I can't think of any reason why inflation, which I think can be fairly described as "evolving standards of currency", should be seen as fundamentally different from the same "evolving standards of decency" factor that Scalia and other originalists object to so strongly.  During oral argument in *Hollingsworth v. Perry*, Scalia asked the respondents' attorney when prohibiting same-sex marriage became unconstitutional.  Scalia's own answer to that, of course, would be "not in 1868, obviously, which means never".  In that same vein, though, when did it *cease* to be unconstitutional to set bail at $1 million, which would surely have been considered ludicrously excessive for *any* bailable offense in 1791?

I don't think most originalists actually hold this view, but I really don't see a principled reason why not, and so as a result, this is my view.  That said, I honestly do believe there likely is such a reason, and that I just haven't thought of it.  So, CMV.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>43</id><identifier>4h4pgb</identifier><title>CMV: Batman should kill the Joker.</title><commentCount>22</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4h4pgb/cmv_batman_should_kill_the_joker/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>This CMV has come through the subreddit many times, but I am still unconvinced. My arguments for this position come from a slightly different angle, and I feel there has been no CMV that adequately addresses them.

The main gist of the argument is similar to the others: All the evidence available to Batman points to the facts that the Joker will escape Arkham (or any other prison he is put in (maybe not, maybe he should ask Superman to send the Joker to the negative zone, but that's a CMV for another day) and he will kill again. Batman's failure to kill the Joker when he knows this is as good as allowing the Joker to kill again.

Now, Batman has many times been legally empowered to kill the Joker. Assuming Gotham has laws similar to the rest of the United States then Batman could have killed the Joker any of the numerous times that he posed a serious threat to the life of Batman or of innocent bystanders. Here he would have had an affirmative defense to the charge of murder. (And to pre-empt the slippery slope argument, I think Batman should kill villains every time he is legally empowered to do so and never when he isn't. That means if Two-Face or the Penguin are threatening innocent people's lives, and Batman can kill them, he should.)

As for other heroes capable of killing the Joker (or their own villains), I think they have the same responsibility, but this CMV isn't about them.

As for the courts, I say the same thing, if the laws in Gotham allow capital punishment, then they too should execute the Joker, and their failure to do so is a moral failure. But again, this CMV isn't about them.

One thing that is not mentioned enough when we talk about Batman is that he does not really have a no-killing rule, what he has is an I-dont-want-to-see-somebody-I-killed-die-in-front-of-me rule. How many times has Batman beaten somebody up badly enough to send them to the hospital? How many times has he given somebody a terrible concussion or a sever case of internal bleeding? I don't think Batman is stupid enough to think that none of these people end up dying as a direct result of his actions, and the fact that he continues to be a vigilante seems to me to mean that he considers this to be if not morally acceptable, then a risk he is willing to take. On the other hand, he is so invested in the Joker's life that not only will he not kill him, not only will he not allow him to die, but he will risk his own life to prevent the Joker's death. What exactly is the logic behind this?

Now finally, to the argument that Batman is too mentally unhinged to be able to handle the Joker's death: I don't buy it. In Batman: In Darkest Night he was chosen by the green lantern. This is an indication of a great degree of willpower. He manages to not go completely insane after inhaling a great deal of Fear Toxin in Batman Begins. In fact, take a look at [this](https://www.reddit.com/r/BatmanMegaRT/comments/3m38gq/willpowertelepathy_resistance/) thread and tell me that Batman is incapable of dealing with killing the Joker (especially since, as previously mentioned, he is capable of dealing with killing henchmen).

Throughout this CMV I've used the term kill exclusively, I think he could also incapacitate him but I also think the only effective incapacitation for the joker would be something like a quadruple amputation followed by glossectomy and possibly lobotomy. Such an incapacitation is to me worse than murder, but I think is the only thing short of murder that would stop him from killing again.
_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>44</id><identifier>1syr1z</identifier><title>I believe sex offenders should receive absolutely no protection in prison. CMV</title><commentCount>20</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1syr1z/i_believe_sex_offenders_should_receive_absolutely/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>This is from stories that I've heard about sex offenders having guards or other forms of protection inside prison from other inmates who may wish to do them harm. My main problem is that this kind of treatment is pretty common knowledge and should act as a deterrent to possible sex offenders from commuting  sex crimes. But for prison officers to give additional protection to someone simply because they're in danger seems wrong to me. This is my only really opinion that doesn't side with human rights (capital punishment, abortion etc). So Reddit, kindly CMV</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>45</id><identifier>1ege7e</identifier><title>I think capital punishment is always wrong. CMV</title><commentCount>19</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1ege7e/i_think_capital_punishment_is_always_wrong_cmv/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>And the reason I am against it is because I think it is not enough punishment for the murderer.   I don't believe in an afterlife, and therefore once their life is over, that's it, no more suffering for the murderer.  If he/she spends the rest of their life in prison, that is a much greater punishment.  If you believe in an afterlife, then they will still be judged eventually.  

Also, a significant number of innocent people have been executed, and I think the risk of this outweighs any benefit to society in executing murderers. </selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>46</id><identifier>37gakh</identifier><title>CMV: I've frequently seen images shared on Facebook that call for the death penalty for 'paedophiles and child killers'. This seems insane to me.</title><commentCount>19</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/37gakh/cmv_ive_frequently_seen_images_shared_on_facebook/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I'll preface this by saying I'm from the UK, so we don't have capital punishment whatsoever. I'm also against the concept of the death penalty regardless so I'm undoubtedly biased in this case.


Firstly, I don't think this approach is logical at all, it seems to be completely reliant on knee-jerk emotional reactions to an abhorrent crime. Why are padeophiles and child killers specifically being targeted? I agree that sexual abuse or murder of children is a horrendous crime, but what is it that elevates these above other serious crimes? Are these people proposing a system in which someone who sexually abuses a child is executed, but a mass-murderer or mass-rapist is not?


If the reason is that these crimes are against children, we then come to the issue of where the line is drawn. What is a 'child' under these terms, and would the definition apply to both crimes? If someone runs over and kills a child who ran out in front of them and gave them no chance to stop, should that driver be executed? If a 17 year old girl has sex with a 15 year old boy (age of consent is 16 in the UK), does this statutory rape now mean that she should be put in the electric chair? Would you give the same answer if the genders were reversed?


Don't get me wrong, I understand the strong emotional reaction to this, especially from parents (I'm not yet one, more bias perhaps), but I feel that this is extremely poorly thought out, and the people who are sharing it think that it'll deter people from committing these crimes and ensure that those who do never re-offend. While I obviously can't argue the latter, I've seen absolutely no evidence to suggest that the death penalty reduces crime.


I'd really like to hear some civil discussion from the other side of this, I'd have tried to do so on Facebook but the comments sections of these shared images are 90%+ in favour of the OP and anyone who comments with a view like mine gets torn to bits with personal attacks without actually addressing the argument.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>47</id><identifier>3687xo</identifier><title>CMV: why euthanasia and the death penalty are not ethical in current society</title><commentCount>16</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3687xo/cmv_why_euthanasia_and_the_death_penalty_are_not/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Hello! I'm submitting my views on the ethics of the death penalty and physician assisted suicide on the cmv subreddit. I consider myself well informed on this subject, especially concerning the current method of both death penalty and euthenasia, which is accomplished by administering "Nembutal" which is known as "sodium pentobarbital" In short, i believe that euthenasia in the healthcare system and the execution of criminals is NOT ETHICAL! Adding to that, even if it was legal, I do not believe that the current molecule we use “pentobarbital” is extremely unethical. My reasoning behind capital punishment being unethical is:

 First, one can remove capital offenders from society by placing them in prison for the extent of their lives, which would equivocate the intentions of the death penalty. Second, the legal system is fallible, which presents the possibility of killing an innocent human being who is wrongly accused. Third, Capital punishment does not deter new crime, and may actually increase it by hardening the hearts of civilization. 

Also while I am in support of euthanasia, mandating that hospitals honor euthanasia requests is not ethical because the most ethical approach is to honor the rights of people, with can be done by recognizing a few certain rights that people innately possess. The first certainty is that human beings have the freedom to end their own life at their choosing. The second certainty is that no organization (which is a group of people) is obligated to assist that person in their decision to die. The third certainty is that the healthcare system is founded on the maxim “do no harm,” and should not violate this maxim. From these three premises, one can conclude that it is the responsibility of the organization to decide which euthanasia requests to honor or deny. Even with this freedom to honor requests, the healthcare system cannot honor euthanasia requests while observing its own maxim. Therefore euthanasia may be ethical when provided from an organization, but it cannot be ethically provided for by the healthcare system, if the healthcare system is to honor its maxims as absolute. From this, the ethical solution must be an accountable, third party euthanasia provider who is allowed honor the rights of euthanasia to those who are ruled “sound of mind” and "fit to die" by a jury of their peers 

Finally The reason that the acts of mandating euthanasia in the healthcare system and capital punishment are currently unethical in the united states is because we use “Nembutal/Sodium Pentobarbital” to obtain these goals. Pentobarbital is unethical because it will indeed put the subject into coma in small doses, but in large doses may actually act as a stimulant and return them to consciousness. However, the subject could not communicate this, because the drug will have incapacitated the rest of their body from movement. Promising whoever uses it a long and painful demise as they suffocate from an inactive diaphragm.
 For this reason, I am not in support of Euthenasia in the hospital or Capital punishement. I believe that we should do away with capital punishment, Move euthanasia from the hospital to another organization, and Create a more ethical molecule for euthanasia.


_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>48</id><identifier>1g36ic</identifier><title>I believe capital punishment (or the death penalty) is a good thing.</title><commentCount>15</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1g36ic/i_believe_capital_punishment_or_the_death_penalty/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I believe capital punishment is a good thing. For outstandingly horrible crimes such as multiple murder or child rape combined with murder the death penalty should be handed out.

The only alternative which I accept is life long imprisonment. NO early release.

A frequent counter argument is the possibility of sending an innocent person to death. Regarding this I think the re-offending rate of murder and rape are around 1%. So if for every 100 death penalty there is 1 innocent, I still think this is the preferable option as a society. The point here is that i think every victim of a re-offender counts the same value as an innocently convicted person.

In fact, the number of victims of re-offenders is my central argument here. I personally knew somebody who was murdered by a re-offender.

I think 1 innocently convicted person for every 2 re-offender victims is still good rate. CMV.    </selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>49</id><identifier>1bmji2</identifier><title>I think life imprisonment is just as bad as capital punishment. CMV</title><commentCount>11</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1bmji2/i_think_life_imprisonment_is_just_as_bad_as/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Disclosure; When I speak about life imprisonment I am not including the likes of stabbings, rapes etc that occur but the actual idea of being locked away for life (life not 20-30 years like some places) and why it's so detrimental.

Firstly, I'm not for capital punishment. I'm totally against it. I don't believe killing is ever acceptable. The idea that we kill someone for killing is ludicrous to me. What kind of message does that send to society? ''Yeah killing's okay when the government's doing it.'' 

I also hate the argument of ''Why should I pay for that person to be alive?'' If you're not willing to pay to keep someone alive, what are you willing to pay for? I could go on about why I disagree with it for ages so I won't. 

On to my actual point. When talking about states that don't have capital punishment it's usually because of the core argument that killing is wrong. I believe capital punishment is wrong because it's killing but I also don't believe killing is simply a physical thing. I believe someone can be killed by more than just a heart stopping beating. Which is why I'm pro-choice as well. Being killed attacks you as a person. I mean, it changes you (obviously you're dead, fairly changing). 

In my mind killing is wrong because it takes away the most basic human right any human being can possess. Now, when I say that I think why is life imprisonment that much better? It's changing you at your core, it's taking away your inner-most being. It's a psychological assault on who you are. It affectively kills who you. It takes away several of your human rights. 

I think it takes away the idea of living. The idea that you're you. The only thing we're told takes that away is death yet life imprisonment does it too for the reasons I've stated and just exactly how altering life imprisonment is. I mean it does change your entire being. 

So since it does change your being, it does kill you, then why is it better? Why do so many people believe that a life imprisonment charge is doing someone a favour? I know these people are probably the worst of the worst, but they're still people. A state is their to protect it's people and whether or not you like it that's what these criminals are. The state isn't there to murder them. I believe life imprisonment murders just like capital punishment murders, kills, executes etc. Whatever verb it is you want to use. 

I've spoken on my issues with life imprisonment and why exactly it isn't any better than capital punishment and the fact that killing isn't simply a physical thing. The idea that by putting someone away for life imprisonment is killing them and that is never okay.

I'm not really asking people to change my views outright just as much as I want a discussion/debate to unfold :P. </selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>50</id><identifier>1fxite</identifier><title>I am pro-Capital Punishment. CMV</title><commentCount>11</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1fxite/i_am_procapital_punishment_cmv/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>I believe capital punishment is a very fair system, while unpleasant it seems to be a very balanced philosophy in my eyes;

We are all, of course, human and we all equally deserve every right that is bestowed upon humans. We deserve shelter, food, family etc. and of course the right to live. Humans as a species have lasted this long by learning to live with each other and not totally blow each other pieces (for the most part). Within a small society such as a state or indeed a country, an act that opposes this will to live with each other (in my eyes I cannot see this stretching much further beyond murder, torture or perhaps rape) could be deemed 'un-human', and therefore sacrifices their status as a human, and therefore their human-rights to shelter, food, family and then the right to live. 

Now yes, death is as final as anything you'll find on this planet, and if it is to be used it is to only be used carefully. But think of it contractually - you are a human with human rights, but if you make the decision to commit such an act then you are at that moment you commit the act making the decision to admit and accept your punishment. The law would be there and you would know when just thinking about committing murder, the punishment WOULD be death. If, after knowing and acknowledging this, you then choose to commit the act anyway you are accepting the punishment you chose to ignore. 

Yes, I of course see the irony in capital punishment. 'Don't kill or you will be killed' is of course ironic. But the idea is more that if you commit the crime you are accepting a sentence set forth by a law, and the death is the carrying out of that sentence bestowed upon the criminal as an abstract concept and a state of being.

Maybe I make no sense. Probably. But I have long thought this and long had debates with people where I am yet to have my view changed. Part of me would quite like to change this view as it is quite controversial and upsetting to some people, but the logic just pieces together all too well for me to abandon it.

So, by all means, CMV.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>51</id><identifier>1h01gn</identifier><title>Capital punishment should be broadcasted over the internet and tv CMV</title><commentCount>10</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1h01gn/capital_punishment_should_be_broadcasted_over_the/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>Reasons:
- crime deterrence 
- sense of justice for the people
- total transparency from govt side
- serves as a check for prison wardens 

"Public executions of the convicted murderer would serve as a reminder that crime does not pay. Public executions of criminals seem an efficient way to communicate the message that if you shed innocent blood, you will pay a high price... I agree... on the matter of accountability but also believe such publicity would serve to deter homicide."  - Louis P. Pojman</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>52</id><identifier>1hoi97</identifier><title>I believe that so long as America has capital punishment, charges of rape and child molestation should qualify for capital punishment. CMV</title><commentCount>9</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1hoi97/i_believe_that_so_long_as_america_has_capital/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>At this point, we put murderers to death in certain cases, namely when it can be proven that the murder was Preeminated in cold blood. We put murderers to death because they are extremely dangerous to society and have broken the social contract. I believe the death penalty is not about vengeance, but about protecting the public from truly dangerous people whose harm can only be stopped by removing them from the earth. To be clear, arguably more minor forms of rape, such as statutory, do not fall under what i believe should be capital offense, similaraly to how a murder in the heat of passion may be treated with a prison sentence instead.

Although this definition is not strictly legal, I do side with femanists and law professors who argue that rape is the murder of the soul, and the issue society faces when dealing with rapists is best solved through capital punishment. Just as gangsters have had power to commit murder from inside their cells by sending hit orders through corrupt guards (see: al Capone and tookie Williams) rapists can and will still rape within the walls of a prison (see: US prisons). They premeditaded doing irreversable harm to an individual and carried it out because they thought they could get away. victims of rape often can never psychologically recover and are in a way "killed" on the inside. In many extreme cases, rapists are set in their sick ways and can no longer serve society in any way. Please, cmv.</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>53</id><identifier>2f2uki</identifier><title>CMV: A defeat of ISIS, with significant U.S. support, will only pacify Middle East problems. It will not do anything to "fix" the Middle East, possibly making matters worse in the future.</title><commentCount>7</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2f2uki/cmv_a_defeat_of_isis_with_significant_us_support/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>First, let me clearly explain that I think ISIS is full of maniacs that deserve death, and shouldn't be allowed to influence the world in any way, whatsoever.  Most of their victims are innocent people, and they should be helped.

I am not interested in debating previous US roles in Middle East governance - for example, our support of the shah in Iran, our continued support of the Saudi kingdom, or Musharraf in Egypt.  I agree, the US has played some dubious roles and at times, has not contributed to the greater good in the Middle East.  I'd like to limit the scope of conversation to only consider relevant, recent happenings in Syria, Iraq and with regard to ISIS.

That said, I recognize it's all a complex mess, so I'll likely even reference things out of my own scope during discussion...  But let's try to focus on the here and now.

My assertion is that the extremism projected by ISIS is the logical and predictable outcome of typical Middle East governance.

The Saudis, conservative sunnis, are [lopping heads off](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_punishment_in_Saudi_Arabia) left and right - recently even for the crime of [sorcery](http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/saudi-arabia-executes-19-during-half-of-august-in-disturbing-surge-of-beheadings-9686063.html).

In Iran, the government [censors](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Censorship_in_Iran) everything it is able and [hangs](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_punishment_in_Iran) people for all manners of "crimes" including [victims of rape](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atefah_Sahaaleh).

If you have access to the internet, and are interested in reading about, or discussing the Middle East, you certainly know it only gets worse...  Egypt has been known to routinely torture prisoners, many political.  In Dubai, a pair of British tourists can be convicted for kissing in public.  I believe it was the UAE where another British tourist was arrested and held for using foul language in public (I recall there was an argument with a taxi driver or something).  The list goes on, and on, and on...

I'm not making any disparaging remarks about the populations or character of people in these countries.  Instead, I am talking about their governance and legal systems.  These countries are backward, religiously oppressed, corrupt, breeding grounds for extremism.  They use violence and religion to control populations with threat of violence.  To keep these tools effective, they fund and encourage extremism in schools and pursue oppression in public.

As a result, a lot of people have been raised in an environment where it's OK to believe that someone is guilty of sorcery and they should be beheaded.  The same people believe it's OK to treat women and children like property.  The same people believe in supernatural, apocalyptic futures.  The same people are willing to turn a blind eye to the exact form of violence that ISIS is delivering to the regions under their control.

It seems to me that ISIS is a logical outcome from such conditions.  They've taken some of the fairy tales and and psychopathy to an extreme - a logical extreme, given that they've been taught to believe this crazy garbage in public and tolerated the entire time.  Keep in mind, that where ISIS goes, they find supporters.  It's not like they're a limited army of a few thousand guys - they pick up support in the communities under their control.

I say we let them fester and grow.  Obama has said they're a cancer - I agree.  But perhaps the governments in the Middle East could use a scare, in order to adopt a healthier lifestyle.  I say we pull out all together and let it all go to hell.  If the other governments think Islamism and brutality are good for populations, then hey - ISIS is just as valid a government as they are.  I think ISIS is their problem, and they should sort it out.

Instead, the US should take any money not spent bombing these cavemen and instead spend it on screening people traveling into and out of the region.  We need to keep the US safe, sure.  Let's do that by keeping the lunatics over there.  Hey - maybe we can create more jobs...  hey, maybe we can help poverty here at home...

And for the record, I'm perfectly willing to pay more for my gas and merchandise as a result of chaos in the Middle East.  Let the governing buttholes over their get their acts in order, once and for all.

_____

&gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText></submission> 
<submission><id>54</id><identifier>3vpybr</identifier><title>CMV: The execution of Mahmoud Asgari and Ayaz Marhoni was used by OutRage! to push a political agenda.</title><commentCount>1</commentCount><permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3vpybr/cmv_the_execution_of_mahmoud_asgari_and_ayaz/?ref=search_posts</permaLink><selfText>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Asgari_and_Ayaz_Marhoni
_____

The two youths were executed after they were found guilty of rape. 

We don't have any confirmation of their ages, so we can't assume they weren't eligible for Capital punishment.

The problem I find here is that the group OutRage! deliberately used this case as an example of a Gay hate crime, where there was no probable evidence to prove so. Further more, people still believe that the Iranian government killed these youths because of their claimed homosexuality.

If anything, the OutRage! group hindered any chance of the ruling being overturned.
</selfText></submission> 
