<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>84</commentCount>
    <id>3173dl</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/3173dl/cmv_people_sentenced_to_death_should_be_used_in/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Omega037</author>
        <ReplyBody>Wouldn't this incentive juries to give people the death penalty where they otherwise might not?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpyxtea</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>That is a really good point, I haven't thought of that at all.
I was thinking about the present situation, and I haven't thought that something like that would actually support death penalties.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpyypd8</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Omega037</author>
                <ReplyBody>There was some great short stories by Larry Niven (author of Ringworld) in the 1960s where improvements in transplants lead to a demand for organs that causes society to have the death penalty even for simple traffic offenses.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpyz5x3</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>∆

I would really like to read them, can you give me any kind of link?
Anyway, this actually changed my view!

P.s. did I do the delta thing right?

EDIT: trying to do the delta thing right</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpz1iil</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>pikk</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[Flatlander](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flatlander_(short_story_collection\)) is a good place to start </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpz1q5j</id>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>HavelockAT</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; P.s. did I do the delta thing right?

No, it mustn't be in a quote (the &amp;gt; before the Delta).</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpzh8rd</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Omega037</author>
                        <ReplyBody>You need to do the delta without the quote.

As for Larry Niven, "The Jigsaw Man" and "A Gift From Earth" deal with this topic specifically, but I love all of his work.

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpziu5o</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Bowbreaker</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Seeing how that Δ fell through I'm going to award you one of my own. And yes, it is actually deserved because you changed my view too. The only way to avoid this risk is in a competent dictatorship and in that case you don't need much in the way of justification for what you do with your prisoners anyway.

So Δ.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzoubt</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>DeltaBot</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Confirmed: 1 delta awarded to /u/Omega037.

[^Omega037's ^delta ^history](/r/ChangeMyView/wiki/user/omega037) ^| [^delta ^system ^explained](/r/ChangeMyView/wiki/DeltaBot)</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpzowgq</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>11</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>8</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>Δ

I'm giving you a delta, because using death inmates as test subjects has always been a view of mind.  You actually changed my view. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq01c2x</id>
            <replies>
                <author>DeltaBot</author>
                <ReplyBody>Confirmed: 1 delta awarded to /u/Omega037.

[^Omega037's ^delta ^history](/r/ChangeMyView/wiki/user/omega037) ^| [^delta ^system ^explained](/r/ChangeMyView/wiki/DeltaBot)</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq01go9</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>37</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ElysiX</author>
        <ReplyBody>I doubt you would ever get any ethics commission to approve such experiments, let alone the fact that that falls under cruel and unusual punishment.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpyxdvh</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Yes, that's exactly my point, *it is* cruel, but killing is far worse in my opinion, if they *decide* the death of someone, why not accept using his body to do some good?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpyy2u7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>ElysiX</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;but killing is far worse in my opinion

In your opinion.
The inmates might disagree.
So what is the protocol here?

They do 5 experiments then they get downgraded to life in prison?

They still get executed if they are too damaged for further experiments?

Who decides wether they take part in experiments?

Also you say only experiments which are pain free.
How would oyu know if they are? What about unknown sideeffects causing pain and suffering after the fact?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpyyemz</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Sorry I understand that I have not been clear, I edited the opening post.

I am talking about only one experiment per person, and the inmate dying anyway, whether the experiment has succes or it doesn't, within the experiment itself. Once put to sleep, he knows he is not going to wake up.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpyz954</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ElysiX</author>
                        <ReplyBody>So is this a voluntary thing?

Otherwise why not use the bodies of all deceased people for experiments as needed if you do not need consent?

Additional punishment? The families of the inmates too might want to receive the body intact for a proper funeral.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpz0ufa</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                            <ReplyBody>It's not voluntary, they don't have choice other than die anyway.

All deceased people (or at least most of them) have not been forced to die, and even though giving your body to science is a laudable thing to do, they have the right to decide what to do with their body.

I understand that the right to live, and the right to do whatever you want with your dead body are two different things, but isn't the second one negligible in comparison with the first one?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cpz1vp4</id>
                            <replies>
<author>ElysiX</author>
<ReplyBody>So you are saying once a significant right is compromised, all "lesser" rights are irrelevant?

Once someone is sentenced to death, guards can freely torture them ?

Once someone is sent to prison in general they do not have a right to be treated like people anymore?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cpz23gn</id>
<replies>
    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
    <ReplyBody>It's not compromised, someone took that right off of them on purpose, for the "well-being" of mankind.

By the same principle you can take away "lesser" right, for the well-being of mankind, no?

Torture is not useful at all, it's just *more* unnecessary cruelty.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cpz2rku</id>
    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>HavelockAT</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Otherwise why not use the bodies of all deceased people for experiments as needed

In principle this *would* be a good idea, but I think there's just no need. In Austria we have too many people who donate their dead bodies to science, so the university had to refuse a couple of donors. Later they imposed a fee, which is 450 Euros today, so it's still much cheaper than an funeral.

&amp;gt; Additional punishment? The families of the inmates too might want to receive the body intact for a proper funeral.

Well, in some countries (including Austria, where I live) everyone is a organ donator (as long as he didn't object in his lifetime). "intact for a proper funeral" is a loose concept.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cpzhq1d</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Bowbreaker</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Later they imposed a fee, which is 450 Euros today, so it's still much cheaper than an funeral.

Woah. I have to see how it is in my country. Because that honestly changes my (very) long term plans. Eh, maybe some artist will buy it.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cpzowpv</id>
<replies>
    <author>HavelockAT</author>
    <ReplyBody>Tell me when you're done. It's interesting how other countries handle it.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cpzugqc</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>9</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Rammite</author>
                <ReplyBody>So torture is worse than a painless lethal injection?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpz0dkd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>HavelockAT</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; painless lethal injection

I think some people might object if they were able to.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzhrs4</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>skilliard4</author>
                <ReplyBody>If I was sentenced to death for some reason, I'd probably rather die knowing when it will happen rather than be subjected to dozens of bizarre experiments I may or may not survive, not knowing what will happen. It's essentially mental torture-a prolonged period of endless fear.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpzirvk</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>16</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>In the United States, we have a ban on "cruel and unusual punishment" in our Constitution.  This seems like the definition of cruel and unusual punishment.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpyy73w</id>
        <replies>
            <author>HavelockAT</author>
            <ReplyBody>"cruel and unusual punishment" is a very loose concept. You may say that the death penalty *is* cruel. In the huge majority of Europe it's even a violation of human rights.

Where do you draw the line? There's no unitary definition of "cruel and unusual punishment".</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpzhx90</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Well, I know it when I see it, and trust me, this is cruel and unusual punishment.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpzlquf</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Bowbreaker</author>
                    <ReplyBody>If you're knocked out and never wake up it's no more cruel than a "normal" lethal injection. And it can't even be called unusual punishment because technically the experimentation isn't punishment. It is forced labor that happens to take place between your state mandated unconsciousness and your state mandated death.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzp16b</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>HavelockAT</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I think that *every* punishment is cruel if we have less severe methods to protect us. So the capital punishment is cruel, too.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzmhzl</id>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>6chan</author>
        <ReplyBody>After Tuskeegee and the Guatemala STI experiments and the [Belmont report](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belmont_Report) there  still have been numerous violations. 

In a perfect world I would agree with your premise, but the slippery slope it creates. Private prisons have already led to increase in incarcerations with even judges arrested for sending kids to prisons for kickbacks. How would you safeguard increased in the number of death sentences given that there is a positive externality to these.

This is especially worrisome when you consider the fact that fairly large sample sizes are required to draw generalizable conclusions from experiments. Couple that with the the prevalence of wrongful incarceration, makes the premise of using death row inmates as test subjects  highly dangerous in the worst case scenario, and even in the best case scenario extremely morbid, as in absence of the ability to draw population level inferences they stand to end up being a Mengelian experiment.

Finally you may want to read the Belmont report, which defines inmates as vulnerable populations and the reasoning behind it. 

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz2t1a</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>∆

Yes, you are absolutely right.

P.s. for everyone interested like me: [Belmont Report](http://videocast.nih.gov/pdf/ohrp_belmont_report.pdf)
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpz3huc</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>tweetypi</author>
        <ReplyBody>Forcefully? I would agree if inmates got the choice to do so in exchange for money or something, but forcing someone to be expereminted on would fall under cruel or unsusal punishment. It could also lead to more people put on death row, right now the death penalty is not a extremely popular choice, and any judge thinking of using it would be criticized, if death row becomes profitable or benifisial then people will be more accepting of it.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpyxjqm</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>About the cruelty: http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3173dl/cmv_people_sentenced_to_death_should_be_used_in/cpyy2u7

About the fact that this could actually promote death penalties: you're right: http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3173dl/cmv_people_sentenced_to_death_should_be_used_in/cpyypd8</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpyyrs0</id>
            <replies>
                <author>tweetypi</author>
                <ReplyBody>Some people believe that life in prison is cruler than the death penalty because at least the death penalty is an end to suffering, with your idea they still die, but slowly and painfully.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpyzfik</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No, in their point of view, they die in the exact same way as a lethal injection.

EDIT: (see the edit in the opening post)</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpyznb9</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>tweetypi</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Experiments are more than just seeing if the person died or not, you need to make sure there are no problems days or even years afterwards as well as get information like pain levels and how it interacts with medications etc ect. Just doing an experiment on someone and then killing them if it is a success loses most of the important information.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpz41ra</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I agree, but I think exclude something that surely does not work from something that it might it's still better than nothing.

And there are not only experiments testing procedures, we could just better understand how do we work.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cpz4bxl</id>
                            <replies>
<author>tweetypi</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;but I think exclude something that surely does not work from something that it might it's still better than nothing.


Can you maybe reword this? Are you saying that giving someone something and having them die from it is benifisial because now we know it kills us? I disagree, because many people would have to die before anything was conclusivly proven, and due to the dangerous and unhealthy nature of prison it would be hard to determine if the thing was truly dangerous, because it could have interacted with something the prisoner took or did.


The reason most experiments are done with laboratory raised animals is that science requires things to be conclusively proven, so when they do an experiment on a mouse they know what it has been eating, where it has been and everything it has been exposed to for its entire life, that way scientists can remove any variables. 


Prison is the polar opposite of that, the people have criminal histories, are in an unlean environment, and have access to drugs, scientists would have a hell of a time finding out why people died in the experiments. It would also cost money as the scientists would need information about the inmate, blood type, possible genetic disorders etc ect.


For better understanding how we work, we have CT scans MRI's and ultra sounds, and already dead people, there is little reason to do exploritory surgery.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cpz4zex</id>
<replies>
    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
    <ReplyBody>Like I "proposed" before: maybe some kind of experiment where you try to bypass the lungs of a patient and oxigenate directly the blood stream (and take away the CO2). That could lead to artificial lungs.

My point is, I don't think there are absolutely no good experiments that can be done.

Are they worth it? As I now understand, [no](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3173dl/cmv_people_sentenced_to_death_should_be_used_in/cpz2t1a)</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cpz5mx5</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>MrF33</author>
                <ReplyBody>I'm sorry but saying that

 "killing is inherently cruel, therefore increasing the cruelty suffered by those sentenced to death is not unethical."

If you're going to accept the death penalty, it doesn't just whitewash the treatment leading up to it.

Torture is *cruel*, and the death penalty is predicated on being as painless as possible.

</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpzh1h2</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>HavelockAT</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; and the death penalty is predicated on being as painless as possible.

Why do you have such troubles with painful executions, then? It seems that some states are not capable of using the least painful method.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzi5pj</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>MrF33</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; It seems that some states are not capable of using the least painful method.

And when its found out that they do it it is stopped, it's not that complicated.

If if didn't matter, then there would be no ongoing judicial review as to whether or not lethal injection is "uncruel" enough.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpzjuju</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>anonoman925</author>
        <ReplyBody>Now there will be an incentive to put more people on death row. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz6c22</id>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Spot_the_Ball</author>
        <ReplyBody>Prisoners in general have much worse health than the general population, the data is going to be skewed

Think back to that death row prisoner in Oklahoma who's execution was botched from his heavily damaged veins

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz038z</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Uhm, I see your point, but isn't tearing apart a not-so-good-anymore machine better than tearing apart a completely-dead one?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpz20jc</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Spot_the_Ball</author>
                <ReplyBody>Ignoring the ethics,  experimentation has very defined guidelines such as uniformity, controls and sample sizes

Lab animals come from specific stock, eat specific food all of their life

With humans we fill out surveys to fill out criteria, simply put there are not enough prisoners to get enough meaningful data and we've seen what happens when prisons have incentives for more prisoners </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpz7i3a</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;  and we've seen what happens when prisons have incentives for more prisoners

That's why I changed my view.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzd0yw</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpzqsxl</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; My main argument against that, and the death penalty in general, is that humans (and our creations such as the court system) are imperfect, this leads to innocent people being wrongfully convicted of all sorts of crimes.

This is not an agrument against the experimentation, it's an argument against death penalties in general, and I agree.

&amp;gt; experiments usually require very precise control groups to get useful data (they don't just use random rats).

This is, and I kind of disagree.
Of course we can't base our entire study on those patient, but on them we can test something in extreme situation, or just the "firsts".
There is always gonna be a first person who gets the [new artificial organ here], why not make this person be someone who doesn't matter if he dies or live?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpzyqm4</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>no-mad</author>
        <ReplyBody>Does "cruel and unusual punishment" sound familiar to you?

These exact words were first used in the English Bill of Rights 1689 and later were also adopted by the Eighth Amendment to the United States Constitution (ratified 1791) and British Leeward Islands' Slavery Amelioration Act (1798). Very similar words, "No one shall be subjected to torture or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment", appear in Article 5 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights adopted by the United Nations General Assembly on December 10, 1948. The right under a different formulation is also found in Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights (1950) and in Article 7 of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (1966). The Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms (1982) also contains this fundamental right in section 12 and it is to be found again in Article 4 (quoting the European Convention verbatim) of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union (2000). It is also found in Article 16 of the Convention against Torture and other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment (1984), and in Article 40 of the Constitution of Poland (1997).[1] The Constitution of the Marshall Islands, in the sixth section of its Bill of Rights (Article 2), prohibits "cruel and unusual punishment", which it defines as: the death penalty; torture; "inhuman and degrading treatment"; and "excessive fines or deprivations".[2]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpzv6nv</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>m0ddem</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Not experiments that involve high amount of pain of course, the kind of experiments that are pain-free (or almost pain-free) but with a high chance of death.

Two questions:

One, can you provide an example of what would constitute a high risk experiment that would not cause pain?

Two, would the subjects be aware of the experiments or their risks?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpyxens</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Uhm, let me see.

Maybe some kind of experiment where you try to bypass the lungs of a patient and oxigenate directly the blood stream (and take away the CO2), while the patient is put to sleep.

My basic knowledge of physiology tells me that we should see a heart failure anyway, but how can we be sure?

We know very little about the functioning of the human body when it comes to the details, I'm thinking of experiments with the purpose of understanding it better, like taking apart a working machine gives us a better idea of how it works, rather than taking apart an already broken one.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpyxxpr</id>
            <replies>
                <author>m0ddem</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Uhm, let me see. Maybe some kind of experiment where you try to bypass the lungs of a patient and oxigenate directly the blood stream (and take away the CO2), while the patient is put to sleep. My basic knowledge of physiology tells me that we should see a heart failure anyway, but how can we be sure?

What's the risk of the subject experiencing hypoxia or false hypoxia, which is what has lead manufacturers of most lethal injection cocktails to restrict sale to the US?  

You haven't answered whether or not the subject would be aware of the intent of the experiments.

EDIT: Formatting.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpyy1xh</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; You haven't answered whether or not the subject would be aware of the intent of the experiments.

You're right I'm sorry. It's just that the it doesn't seems important to me, he is going to die anyway. It could be aware, or it could be not, the awareness of the intent usually gives people choice to pull back.
He can't pull back, and I don't see why he should care of how he dies, as long as it's painless.

Anyway yes, I think it should be "fair" to let him know what's going to happen.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpyyhmp</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>m0ddem</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Knowledge of impending death is a clear psychological harm; while the  court system in the US has generally held that this is not enough to meet the burden of "cruel and unusual" punishment, it's also implicitly understood that the State should attempt to end the life of the prisoner in a humane and rapid fashion once an execution begins; if a subject is instead aware of a *possible* loss of life, they then face a situation where they're essentially given a false hope - maybe they'll live! Does your system give any sort of credit for successful experiments? If a patient survives some set number, is their debt to society considered paid? Or are they simply used up until they're eventually dead?  In that way it seems clear that this would meet the definition of cruel and unusual punishment, even without the pain component you seek to avoid.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpyypyo</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I see your point, probabily I haven't explained my view clearly in my post: it's only one experiment per person, and the inmate is going to die anyway, whether the experiment has succes or it doesn't, within the experiment itself. Once put to sleep, he knows he is not going to wake up.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cpyz384</id>
                            <replies>
<author>m0ddem</author>
<ReplyBody>So how do you kill them if the experiment doesn't?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cpyziva</id>
<replies>
    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
    <ReplyBody>Lethal injection? How is it important?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cpyzqac</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>strong_potato</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think it will be really difficult to get any scientists or whatever to want to do experiments on people that will probably kill the people. Like that seems unpleasant for everyone involved. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpyz8n3</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Of course I'm talking about experiments safe for the team, like invasive medical ones where the patient is put to sleep</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpz22f8</id>
            <replies>
                <author>tweetypi</author>
                <ReplyBody>I don't think they mean that the experiment would be unsafe for the scientist, but that most scientists would not want to do a procedure that will likely kill someone.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpz31qw</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Oh I didn't understand.

Anyway I don't be the lack of scientists should be a problem...</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpz3vmd</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>strong_potato</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It will be though. No organization is gonna fund research that'll kill somebody. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq00wyo</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>DoforReal</author>
        <ReplyBody>Cruel and Unusual Punishment comes to mind.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz1m1s</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ExploreMeDora</author>
        <ReplyBody>You are against the death penalty but you support human experimentation that will likely result in death? Isn't that essentially a death sentence? The difference is that your proposed experimentation is cruel and unusual. I can't think of many experiments that are likely to cause death, which are pain-free. This is basically torture.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz30i6</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Yes, I am against the death sentence, and I think it should be abolished. My idea was that since there is no intention of doing so, at least, we should use what we have to do some good for humanity, something like "if life gives you lemons, make lemonade".

I actually changed my mind understanding that [a procedure like this will likely increase the number of death penalties](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3173dl/cmv_people_sentenced_to_death_should_be_used_in/cpz2t1a)

EDIT: grammar</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpz3slu</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Seeking_Strategies</author>
        <ReplyBody>In addition to the problems already stated I think you still have the same problems that we have now with the death penalty, including uncertainty about guilt.

So do you begin the experiments before or after all appeals, including for clemency, have been exhausted? Do you do the experiments if the prisoner proclaims their innocence until their dying breath? What about prisoners that have been falsely convinced that they committed a crime?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz53dc</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Yes, and that's why I am against the death penalty in the first place, my idea was  to "do some lemonade".</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpz5b9a</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Seeking_Strategies</author>
                <ReplyBody>If a person is falsely convicted, I don't see how it could be better that we then increase their punishment, especially when there is a chance for their punishment to be reduced or their conviction overturned.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpz5ivv</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>My idea was not about "increasing" the punishment, from the inmate side, everything would be the same.

Things would have to go exactly how they go now, the only difference is that instead of a lethal injection, we put the inmate to sleep and do the experiment, killing him before he wakes up.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpz5tg1</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Seeking_Strategies</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I don't see how that would be practical. Typically a prisoner has the right to say their last words to their family, to the victims, etc, then they are put to sleep and executed. 

So the experiment would need to be short enough to not inconvenience or cause more mental anguish to everyone who is there to watch the execution and observation of the outcomes would need to be unaffected by the impending death.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cpz7owq</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I see how that could be a problem for the family, but compared to the fact that he will die, does it change that after the last word he wouldn't *really* be dead immediately?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cpzdden</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Seeking_Strategies</author>
<ReplyBody>I think it would for the observers. I don't think that the family of the prisoner or the family of the bereaved would have closure until the prisoner is dead. 

Certainly we could argue that it should not matter, but  I don't think that will change how most people feel about observing the final passing.

At any rate I found your original idea thought provoking. ::Doffs hat, smiles agreeably, exits conversation.::</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cpzm1jj</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>What kind of experiments did you have in mind? Because putting someone to sleep and then 'doing the experiment', killing them before they wake up sounds more like vivisection than human trials for medication, for example. What would we actually learn from vivisecting a live prisoner that we don't learn from an autopsy, or from examining bodies in medical school? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpz6foz</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
            <ReplyBody>Deep sleep experiments, artificial organ transplants, brain transplants (we could have evidence that the consciousness is located in the brain).

There's something for sure.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cpzdi4l</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Artificial organ transplants and brain transplants cannot be applied to wider research without knowing what happens after transplantation. If we know that an artificial organ can be placed into a human body, but the subject dies immediately or soon after the transplant, we don't really learn much about the viability of such transplants. If part of the point of the experiment is that the subject will die, what's the point in testing procedures that aim to increase life expectancy or require the subject to be alive to actually measure the results?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cpzdu0d</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Fiddler_Jones</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;  without knowing what happens after transplantation

Actually, we can, I didn't say that the patient should be killed *right after* the experiment, we could keep him in a sleep state for as long as we want, we can even mess with the normal functions of the body to see what happen.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cpzyl1b</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Nintenzo</author>
        <ReplyBody>This has got to be the most fucked up thing I've ever read on CMV. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cpze6ho</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>In principle, I am against the death penalty, but since it is a reality, and it seems that it's not going to change, I think we should take the opportunity of having people who are going to die anyway, and use them in high risk experiments. Not experiments that involve high amount of pain of course, the kind of experiments that are pain-free (or almost pain-free) but with a high chance of death.

EDIT: I have not been very clear, I am talking about only one experiment per person, and the inmate dying anyway, whether the experiment has succes or it doesn't, within the experiment itself. Once put to sleep, he knows he is not going to wake up.

EDIT2: [My view has been changed](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3173dl/cmv_people_sentenced_to_death_should_be_used_in/cpz2t1a), something like this will likely increase the number of death penalties.
_____

&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
