<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NamelessDave</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; infinite punishment (from a secular view point)

Clearly this is poor logic. It would be equal to "Life expectancy" minus "Age". Otherwise you are saying death is the same punishment to a healthy 18 year old as a cancer ridden 95 year old. 

In terms of surety this has always been an issue. Being ultimately unable to reverse a serious decision is tricky to argue. I would argue that some crimes are 100% definite. With the use of video evidence there is much precedence for crimes which are completely without doubt solved. It is important to note that this is the standard of proof REQUIRED in many countries (Beyond reasonable doubt). That being said it has been shown many times that there are innocent people in prison. Although it is unpalatable this has to be marked up as collateral as there is always a margin for error. 

This would be the main reason to argue against the death penalty I think. I think your assertion that this is the worst possible punishment is also wrong. Maybe read up on some North Korea style family based justice. 

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjs6jb</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjtv2v</id>
            <replies>
                <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                <ReplyBody>Is there some reason for you to think that an action made under the threat of harm to the defendant's family would not be considered during the trial or sentencing phase? Duress is a well recognized and litigated defense. It is not available as a defense to unlawful killing crimes but would be for any other crimes. It would also be available as a mitigating factor in an unlawful killing crime which would go a long way to avoiding a death sentence- which is never mandatory.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjurgp</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Jazz-Cigarettes</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The evidence of coercion might not come to light until after the conviction and execution, at which point exoneration or at least an appeal for a reduced sentence would no longer be possible.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgjyqmb</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>AlphaAgain</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It takes years and decades in the US for an execution to actually happen.  

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgk8278</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Jazz-Cigarettes</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Sure, and innocent people are *still* wrongfully executed.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgk87e5</id>
                            <replies>
<author>AlphaAgain</author>
<ReplyBody>This is an issue that can be totally resolved as DNA evidence is now commonplace.  </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgk8cge</id>
<replies>
    <author>Jazz-Cigarettes</author>
    <ReplyBody>DNA evidence has been commonplace for a few decades now and we're still executing innocent people.

If it were something that could be "totally resolved" don't you think we would have achieved that by now? This is the issue that always arises when confronting the death penalty. Someone says, "Oh well I wouldn't support it unless we were *absolutely* sure. Then it's ok, right?" 

But there is no such thing as "absolutely sure". There are lab errors. Evidence tampering. Prosecutorial misconduct. Coerced confessions. Racially/ethnically/gender biased juries. There is no way to remove human fallibility and malice from the equation and ensure that the death penalty is being applied without causing uncorrectable miscarriages of justice.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgk8mc6</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Well, for one, I hate the idea of the death penalty. My home state abolished it in 1846 (Michigan) and I'm damn proud of that. But the US Supreme Court has lain down some substantial procedural burdens on the remaining states that do still execute. That's why the necessary appeals take years to complete. That is a lot of time for evidence to come forward. If the guilty party was aware of the duress and simply refused to say anything about it, I suppose we'll never know. But you could play the what-if game ad nauseum. Which is one of the many reasons I do not support the death penalty full stop. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgjza1g</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgk4zre</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Well, in trials in the US, the defendant and his or her attorney are given the opportunity to bring a lot of information the court's attention. If there is insufficient evidence, there is likely an insufficient case for duress. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgk5jy0</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>8</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>NamelessDave</author>
                <ReplyBody>I know what your saying however that's a legal defence that would have to be DISPROVED in court. That is the important point that the offence proved and therefore the defence proved beyond reasonable doubt. But still I know what u r saying. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjtyjl</id>
                <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>zenthr</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Clearly this is poor logic. It would be equal to "Life expectancy" minus "Age". Otherwise you are saying death is the same punishment to a healthy 18 year old as a cancer ridden 95 year old. 

I don't like this interpretation of the "cost" of life. For one, how do you determine life expectancy? By national average? State average? Global average- but only those of similar 'socioeconomic class'? Do you account for my family history or my personal medical records (these *are* relevant, since because I live a healthier lifestyle than most, one must assume the penalty to be a higher cost to me)? Do you ask for some *prediction* for years remaining of those my age? Are you basing it on people who already died *who went through times where medical/biological knowledge was lower than it is now*? (ex: it's NOT appropriate to count my life expectancy based on people's death if they grew up in a time when smoking wasn't thought to be hazardous. This uniformly skews your view of a "fair punishment" against me.) In short, you don't *really* know when I would die if the state executes me, hence this doesn't escape Op's central point that is there is a lack of certainty.



That's just boring, logistics and maybe you don't find it really moving. Then I ask you to consider the implication of the court handing out different penalties to different people. It will be literally impossible to consistently charge people with crimes -unless- you define the punishment some other way. And since most violent crimes are committed by the age group 16-24, you will rarely see capital punishment used against them, but a disproportionately larger use against the more middle-aged and elderly (after all, you equate- at least implicitly- 15 years punishment the same in jail or in the ground). So now you've created a system where by capital punishment is more likely to people *simply* due to their age.

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjw1fx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>NamelessDave</author>
                <ReplyBody>Yeh totally agree. Sorry I don't think I was clear enough. I am not advocating this system I am saying that if you want to base it on how many lost years then the answer is clearly not infinite. 

Still quite right sir. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjw8oq</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>kerfer</author>
                    <ReplyBody>So are you saying that life in prison and the death penalty are the exact same punishment? Because life in prison would also be "years of life remaining minus age". The thing is that even with life in prison a person has the chance to make something of his life, even if it is just spiritually. With death that's it, it just ends. It is the same for a 20 year old and a 60 year old. In that sense it really is infinite. You're essentially dividing everything you want to accomplish with you life by 0.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgk0sos</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>NamelessDave</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I was trying to point out that it is not a mathematical problem. It seems you agree with me. But in a mathematical sense clearly that is correct that premature death robs the individual of the remaining years of life. The OP was comparing this to say 2 years in prison taking two years of life so in that context I think yes death and life term are the same. In reality this is obviously not the case. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgk4kpe</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>IllinoisLawyer04</author>
            <ReplyBody>The collateral damage far outweighs any good that is being done.  There are countless cases of people who should not have been executed but were. Georgia to this day executes the mentally retarded. The false conviction rate is unjustifiably high as well.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgk2oiq</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>If anything, wouldn't mental retardation mean there is less ability to change/rehabilitate? Honestly, i don't see why we should subject even the highest paid people to caring for a highly dangerous retard.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cglc9zj</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>IllinoisLawyer04</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Because most people consider it immoral to kill someone with the brain of a 6 year old.  The Supreme Court ruled that it is unconstitutional to execute the mentally retarded.  </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgmf1v4</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>death IS the same punishment to an 18 year old and cancer ridden 95 year old.

they are alive.  You make them not alive.  How many years they may live after that fact is irrelevant.  ending someone's life is ending someone's life.  </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgk1150</id>
            <replies>
                <author>NamelessDave</author>
                <ReplyBody>Agree to disagree I think. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk4lb2</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Korwinga</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I would argue that some crimes are 100% definite. 

The case I always think of is the Fort Hood shooting(not the one that just happened). Nidal Hassan was apprehended at the scene, with plenty of witnesses, plenty of evidence, and plenty of motive. It's a pretty cut and dried case. However, the majority of death sentence cases aren't anything close to that.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgk84z4</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjx2ze</id>
            <replies>
                <author>NamelessDave</author>
                <ReplyBody>I haven't read it yet but I will when I am on my desktop I assure you. Just to be clear I do not necessarily agree with capital punishment. I was trying t point out the poor reasoning of the OP. It seems I may have done this quite poorly lol. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk4hlu</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>19</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>duncanmarshall</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;infinite punishment

Would you rather die instantly, or be hooked up to a machine that keeps you alive and awake for 10,000 years while you're constantly physically and psychologically tortured in a way that you can never acclimatize to? You will do nothing else for the next 10 millennia than experience the maximum possible torture - there will be absolutely no quality of life.

Personally I'd rather just die right now, so does that mean the 10,000 year punishment is greater than infinite in severity?  Of course it isn't, since neither of them are *infinitely* severe, they're *maximally* severe (if they're even that).

If a man is 40, and will die at 70, letting him go makes him live 30 years of quality-socre 10 (let's assume), a life sentence makes him live 30 quality-score 1 years (also an assumption), and execution gives him 0 years of quality-value 10 or 1.  Exoneration denies him total-quality-value 0, a life sentence denies him total quality-value 270, and execution denies him total quality-value 300.

Obviously it's not infinite, it's just 300 - the *maximum*.

&amp;gt;infinitely sure

Crime severity and guilt certainty are not coefficients of punishment harshness (in the western system at least).  You don't need to be "certain beyond resonable doubt" to give someone a life sentence for murder, but "55%-45%" to sentence someone to an $80 fine for graffiti.

So this point is irrelevant.

Of course, I think the entire conception is flawed, since I'm not sure we should be hurting people because we don't like what they did.  You don't get to lock someone in a box because you think they acted immorally.  There shouldn't be some price-list of wrong-doing that you can choose crimes to commit from, and how many years you'll have to pay.

So really why would we imprison, fine, or execute anyone?  To protect our selves from them.  You lock a murderer up to stop him from murdering people.  You fine a parking violator to pay for his car being towed.  How do we make sure we're doing that to the right people?  We have a trial and make sure we're sure *enough* ("beyond a reasonable doubt" is a good definition of 'enough').

So what happens if we're sure beyond a reasonable doubt that a super hero killed someone *and will kill again*?  No prison can hold him, so let's take it as a given that the only way to stop him from killing someone else is to kill him.  We've got him on tape confessing, and committing the crime, but since it's impossible to be infinitely sure of anything, do we have to just let him murder everyone he likes, because we have no way of stopping him without an execution? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjstuq</id>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>IllinoisLawyer04</author>
        <ReplyBody>I used to be pro death penalty until I did some post-conviction work for death row inmates in law school.  There are so many wrongful convictions.  Something like 15% of people WHO CONFESS turn out to be innocent and cleared by DNA evidence.  

In Georgia, the State can execute people who are more likely than not mentally retarded.  They do this despite Atkins v Virginia.

I'm not against the death penalty in theory but, at least for now, it doesn't work in practice.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjyhv9</id>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>CausalDiamond</author>
        <ReplyBody>Consider someone who is on death row and someone who is sentenced to life in prison. Both persons are being punished for committing a crime that can never be infinitely proven. Consequently, there exists the possibility that they are both innocent. Person A is executed after 10 years on death row. Person B dies in prison after serving a 70 year sentence. Both scenarios can be argued to be unwarranted because there can never be infinite proof that each person committed their crime. The end result is the same: death. Or, as you put it, infinite punishment.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjqj3w</id>
        <replies>
            <author>JRutterbush</author>
            <ReplyBody>But if - after, say, 12 years or so - someone learns that the prisoner is innocent, the one who was given life can then be freed to at least live out whatever years they have left. You can't bring an executed prisoner back to life if it's later discovered that they were innocent.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjqwru</id>
            <replies>
                <author>CausalDiamond</author>
                <ReplyBody>That's why there is a lengthy appeals process for prisoners on death row. Sure, it's not perfect, but what is? There is the potential for innocent people to be executed just as there is potential for innocent people to rot in prison for life.
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjr4so</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>JRutterbush</author>
                    <ReplyBody>But, as I said, there is no potential for people who have been executed to be freed if they're innocent, while there is that potential for those who have only been imprisoned for life. It's the ability to rectify a mistake that's the issue here.

"It's not perfect." is not, in my opinion, a valid argument in favor of a permanent and irreversible punishment when we have no way to be absolutely sure of a person's guilt.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgjr6h0</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>CausalDiamond</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Yes, the potential is there. I am now genuinely curious how often that potential is realized versus when it is realized for prisoners on death row. Anyways, while I can readily accept that potential with ease, one still cannot ignore that there will always be those who suffer for their entire life in prison despite being innocent. To me, that misfortune isn't a whole lot different from the misfortune of those who are wrongfully executed. I wouldn't be surprised if there is a higher percentage of innocent people who serve prison sentences (enduring all the lasting harms/ills that come with that) than there is innocent people who were actually executed.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgjrc03</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>The point is that someone who's imprisoned for life can still come free if his innocence is proven later down the road while execution is irreversible. Even if you're wrongfully incarcerated for 30 years and then freed, I'd argue that's still a hell of a lot better than being executed. The justice system is not flawless and therefore I think it is the most logical step to abstain from methods of punishment that can not be reversed.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgjsyn1</id>
                            <replies>
<author>CausalDiamond</author>
<ReplyBody>Right, and I readily acknowledge that point. If executions were processed hastily, I think that point would be even more significant. With that said, I'd still like to see the rates of inmates who are proven innocent after serving large sentences versus the rates of inmates proven innocent after appeals on death row.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgk2e5a</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>nikatgs</author>
            <ReplyBody>Very few countries will actualy keep people in prison for 70 years. I would be interested if someone could name an example country and also the crime one would have to commit to recieve a 70+ year sentence (without parole)</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjrypl</id>
            <replies>
                <author>NamelessDave</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think you mean whole life sentences. [This](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_prisoners_with_whole-life_tariffs) is a list for the UK of people who will die in prison</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjs7f0</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>nikatgs</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Thanks thats very interesting. 42 people out of 97,000 (aprox) prisoners out of 63 million population. Just to give some perspective....</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgjsg7e</id>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Maybe the criminal didn't meet parole, it doesn't change the argument (although its flawed ^for ^^other ^^^reasons ). </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjs666</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>CausalDiamond</author>
                <ReplyBody>It's essentially a life sentence and I know at least in the U.S. it happens. Sometimes they even give greater than a life sentence (100+ years) in the case of mass killings, for instance.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk2fch</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's definitely not infinite punishment because you could compare it to the harshest form of life imprisonment (actually, you could argue that torturous life imprisonment would be worse). But I get that you're saying it's irrevokable and requires absolute certainty of proof. However, saying that it should be scraped along those lines ignores a couple of other potential reasons for capital punishment. Note that I don't necessarily agree with these but they are points to be addressed. 

* Deterrent. Studies on this are inconclusive, mainly because capital punishment is so (relatively) rare so collecting data on rates before/after is difficult. (IIRC some studies speculate that execution rates would need to be something like 100x what they are in the US to actually have any kind of deterrent effect. Some actually argue that capital punishment causes a "brutality" effect on society where people value human life less and causes a slight rise in violent crime. Interesting to read about, but again, inconclusive. )

* Consolation/closure for the victim/victim's family. Whether or not this is beneficial or actually ethical to grant is, again, a bit of a complicated area. 

* Safety of others and recidivism. Consider that even though we can get really goddamn sure 99.9999% proof, we can't get absolute 100% proof of a crime. Contrastingly, even though we can imprison them with 99.9999% certainty of them not escaping, we can't absolutely with 100% certainty guarantee they won't get loose and murder someone else (maybe a guard, fellow inmate, or god forbid escape prison entirely). In which case we should consider the overall benefit to society. We should also consider that the death of an innocent, say a child, may be morally weighted as being worse than the death of someone who is 99.9999% probably an evil son of a bitch murderer. Depending on your morality scale. 

You'd actually have to do quite a lot of studies to determine the actual chances of each, which is hard because both are so close to 100%, but it's something to consider. And even if it turns out prisons are more secure than our courts are accurate, all that means it that our courts are lacking, and that theoretically there does exist a point in which society receives more utility from capital punishment, if the courts can somehow magically increase their accuracy past the point where prisons are secure.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjrjtf</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>What about the 13 people murdered by Maj. Nidal Malik Hasan at Fort Hood in 2009? There is absolute, undeniable proof that he committed those murders and wounded 32 others. He currently awaits execution on military death row.

This is a man who took *thirteen* lives and would have taken many, many more if he hadn't been stopped. What justice is there in letting him live out his life in prison? Three meals a day, cable tv, a library, wood or leatherworking classes...he could even get a degree!

Here's the best way to look at it: Say it's 2009 and you are watching the news of Hasan's Ft. Hood massacre. You are horrified at the carnage and you feel so upset for the families as the death tally rises. Suddenly there's breaking news...a military police officer shot and killed the shooter. Are you upset that the officer shot him? Do you genuinely think he deserved better than a bullet to the chest or head? Do you think he deserved to die for what he did?

*What's the difference in shooting him on site versus him being convicted and put to death?*

Honestly, my only problem with capital punishment is how long it is dragged out. It's cheaper for life sentences than death sentences after you figure in all the appeals and court costs. I think Hasan should have been tried, convicted, and immediately put down for his crimes. 

It's different when you aren't sure, but there are a lot of instances where you can be absolutely 100% sure. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjs77e</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjswd4</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>I know the difference in shooting an armed versus unarmed person. I'm asking why it is so different in people's minds if he is (hypothetically) shot on scene or if he is convicted and put to death. Removing the gun from his hands doesn't remove the blood. 

Nobody ever says, "If someone raped and killed my daughter, I would prosecute them to the full extent of the law and watch them go to prison." They say, "If someone touched my baby, I would kill them." People think their own pain warrants it, but God forbid someone gets sentenced to death row for a crime that didn't affect them, no matter how heinous and deserving. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk27nz</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>instadit</author>
            <ReplyBody>Putting the absolute certainty issue aside. Putting the violation of human rights aside.

Even by retributive standards, a death penalty is not just.
The man you mentioned has killed 13 innocents. A proportionate and fair punishment (says the USA legal system) is death.
13 innocents who were not guilty of any crimes have lost their lives, some suffering to their dying breath.
1 guilty who has commited one of the most heinous crimes will lose his life, after a fair trial and will die a painless death.
Does this seem like a proportionate punishment to you?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjtlkc</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>What I think is a fair death for him is not what's in question. I, personally, think public lynching is a better deterrent for would-be criminals. I think we worry too much about the rights of murderers and rapists, people who themselves didn't respect the rights of others. They shouldn't have better access to healthcare, libraries, and schooling than parts of our own population. They shouldn't get less time in prison for murder than some people get for drug use. 

No, a painless death isn't proper vengeance, but it is retributive justice. The punishment fits the crime in the fact that he forfeits his life in exchange for the 13 lives he took. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk2sjn</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Get_a_GOB</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not sure military prison is the quasi-pleasant place you make civilian prison out to be...and he has a degree, likely two as a Major.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjtqpu</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>I agree that military prison is probably much worse and I'm sure he did have degrees considering his rank; however, most people are in state prisons and many don't have a way of achieving a degree outside of the prison system. I used Hasan as an example because it is a fairly well known case and is easily searchable because of the media coverage. 

My husband worked in a prison, as has my mother, my aunt, and several friends. Yeah, it can be horrible, but there are a lot of opportunities to be taken advantage of. There are a lot of people who have better lives in prison than they did outside. I get that a lot of it is for rehabilitative purposes, but it still doesn't make it fair that a murderer has a better chance of an education than an inner-city teen. It isn't fair that they can learn a great trade for free/cheap, but people who have done no wrong pay tens of thousands to learn the same thing in trade school. 

I know it is ultimately better for them to be educated or know a trade for if/when they are paroled, but it doesn't make it any less irritating that felons have better opportunities inside prison than so many hard-working, non criminals. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk33ku</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think others have adequately addressed the issue of "infinite punishment" being logically invalid; I'd like to address the concept of reasonably certainty - I think you're generally correct, that you can't have capital punishment without a level of certainty, but I think that that level *absolutely* can be obtained, *just not for every case*. It would then be required in sentencing to have a separate concept for seeking capital punishment, in which the person is found guilty beyond a reasonable doubt, but not with a surety that belies capital punishment. 

It's honestly a pretty fine line to have a case where you're sure enough a person committed a crime due to circumstantial evidence, but don't have the video/physical proof to execute, but I can see it existing, and as such, have to disagree with it being scrapped entirely. There are people so heinous, with such undeniable proof (including open confessions without duress), that capital punishment should remain on the table, even if the use of it in the first place (that is, whether or not capital punishment is moral/ethical, if you had your certainty) is still open for debate.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjw2tq</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjxv1x</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Grunt08</author>
            <ReplyBody>

Sorry angryherbivore, your post has been removed:  

&amp;gt; Comment Rule 1\. "Direct responses to a CMV post must challenge at least one aspect of OP’s current view (however minor), unless they are asking a clarifying question. Arguments in favor of the view OP is willing to change must be restricted to replies to comments." [See the wiki page for more information.](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules#wiki_rule_1)  

If you would like to appeal, please [message the moderators by clicking this link.](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Fchangemyview&amp;amp;subject=Removed+Comment+Rule+1+Post+Appeal&amp;amp;message=angryherbivore+would+like+to+appeal+the+removal+of+[his/her+post](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/2265kk/cmv_i_think_that_capital_punishment_requires_a/cgjxv1x\))




</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgk531n</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BoboTheTalkingClown</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's hard to "reverse" losing decades of your life, albeit not as extreme as losing the whole thing.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjz03g</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>w41twh4t</author>
        <ReplyBody>To clarify your position, you think in a hypothetical case where, let's say, a longtime member of a Neo-Nazi gang says he's going to kill a bunch of people and then he could go and shoot up a school and we could have dozens of security cameras and dozens more of footage from people's cellphones and you'd still believe that wasn't good enough evidence?

I can agree that probably 90+% of death row cases should be life sentences instead when they rely on circumstance, eyewitness accounts which can be unreliable and DNA which can be wrong or falsified. But to say you can never ever have ABSOLUTE certainty means you have to get into explanations like "maybe he was controlled by aliens" and "maybe the government made 100 different fake videos from fifty different sources."</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjz8hn</id>
        <replies>
            <author>hacksoncode</author>
            <ReplyBody>There's still the uncertainty that the person in the video is the one being held. 

If you're talking about the fantastically rare possibility that someone might be caught on a (somehow unimpeachable) video both killing people, and also being caught, and also having an unimpeachable chain of custody so that you know they are the ones that committed the crime, then all that's left is whether the person is legally sane. 

Of course, that's a pretty contentious issue. How would you ever be certain of that?

And in any case, that would merely change the view to "99.9% of all people charged with a capital offense can't be proven guilty sufficiently to justify the death penalty". </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgk32yj</id>
            <replies>
                <author>w41twh4t</author>
                <ReplyBody>Google says there are currently about 3000 in the US on death row. I've done no extensive analysis so I don't want to quibble on what I guess is more like 90% shouldn't be to your stated 99.9% and instead let's focus on that 0.1%. Your original statement was that we could never have a satisfactory level of certainty. I'd guess the better number from absolute reasonable certainty instead of the current standard of beyond reasonable doubt would put that number closer to 300. But even at 99.9% that leaves 3 people that we are certain of. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgk3jbx</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>hacksoncode</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Ummm... that would be 99%. 99.9% would be only .3 people. I'd say that's about right, when you include uncertainty about their level of (legal) sanity.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgk3m34</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>w41twh4t</author>
                        <ReplyBody>10 percent of 3000 is 300.

1 percent of 3000 is 30.

0.1% of 3000 is 3.
</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgk3w0y</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hacksoncode</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Thought you were saying something else. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgk40b3</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hacksoncode</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Personally, in those excruciatingly rare cases where we not only have that level of evidence that the crime happened, but also can be certain that they are legally sane, I would have no problem with the death penalty except that it's still an incredible waste of money and resources to reach that level of certainty. 

It's just not worth it to have a societal policy of a death penalty for 3 people over the course of several decades. Life in prison is a perfectly adequate and cost-effective solution to that problem that removes *all* possibility of society being responsible for executing an innocent person. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgk441v</id>
                            <replies>
<author>w41twh4t</author>
<ReplyBody>The expensive part of the death sentence is the decades of appeals to reach the point of execution. If the level were changed to absolute certainty and there were just 3 or even 300 death penalty cases those multiple appeals wouldn't happen because they would only attempt that punishment when there was absolutely clear evidence of guilt.

Here's an example I found by searching the phrase 'recorded himself murdering': http://www.volokh.com/2011/02/09/man-accidentally-records-himself-murdering-his-wife/

I'm not saying this case specifically deserves the death penalty or there'd be no appeals or mental evaluations, but this seems a pretty clear cut example where there'd be no fear of innocence and no reason we'd need decades of court appearances before an execution. (Personally I'd put the death penalty standard at absolute certainty of indiscriminate mass murder.)</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgk5tk7</id>
<replies>
    <author>hacksoncode</author>
    <ReplyBody>While I agree with your basic point, I would argue that there doesn't seem to be a large need to put in place an entire infrastructure for execution, including all of the protocols to ensure this level of "absolute certainty", to solve such an extremely minor problem that largely appears to be caused by mental illness in the first place. 

If 2997 of those death row inmates are only going to be put in jail for life, without parole, is it worth the extra effort to even *have* a death penalty? What do we really gain by dealing with those incredibly rare corner cases?

Also, one has to ask a question about fundamental fairness. I have no doubt that most of the people on death row are exactly as "deserving" of this death penalty as the ones where we could prove their crime with absolute certainty. 

If it were common that we could easily reach absolute certainty, my opinion might be different.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgk84mg</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think it's possible for the justice system to be certain enough of guilt to sentence someone to death.

Like the Colorado movie theater shooter, he got caught red-handed. No doubt it was him. I'm fine with him getting the chair, or whatever Colorado uses.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgk1vwz</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Sabesaroo</author>
        <ReplyBody>In most countries it is scrapped, and it definately should be everywhere.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgk283g</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>hacksoncode</author>
        <ReplyBody>While others have pointed out that your view of "infinite" punishment is incorrect, I'll take a different tack on that:

By your metric, life in prison is exactly the same punishment as death, i.e. "punishment for all of your remaining life". So should your view also say that life in prison is unjustifiable by any degree of certainty?

The real reason we need that certainty is that the death penalty is *irreversable* in case of error, not that it is of life-long magnitude.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgk39m4</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>krausyaoj</author>
        <ReplyBody>Death is not an infinite punishment but is actually zero punishment. The executed prisoner no longer experiences the suffering of incarceration. A life sentence is actually worse than the death penalty as they will experience the suffering of incarceration and then death.

Some prisoners want to be executed to lesson the suffering they experience in prison, http://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/oct/20/death-row-alabama-execution-prisoner

The suffering in prison is so high that efforts are made to avoid suicide, http://www.usmarshals.gov/prisoner/suicide_prevention.htm

Executing prisoners does not cause them harm, but potentially harms society if an innocent person is executed and we lose their contributions.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgl6xz5</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>EmptyMaG</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think the idea of punishment is achieved by the removal of something, for example, ten years of incarceration achieves punishment by removing the freedom of an individual both spatially and socially, similarly community service achieves punishment by taking labor and time. Capital punishment is then just the removal of the remaining natural life span of the convict and is therefore not infinite and mathematically achievable by committing heinous crimes.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjqat9</id>
        <replies>
            <author>JRutterbush</author>
            <ReplyBody>The issue here then arises in the certainty of guilt. Even a life sentence can be taken back after being given if it's later discovered that there was a mistaken conviction. There is no such possibility with the death penalty. A permanent punishment should require absolute, 100% certainty of guilt, which is not something that we can ever achieve with a human-based justice system.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjqw26</id>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>LiveBeef</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; death is an infinite punishment (from a secular view point)

No it isn't. This would imply that there would be absolutely no punishment worse than it. What about being killed *and* having to watch loved ones being beaten? What about having your child killed in your place? Plain death isn't the worst punishment inflictible; you can't therefore claim that its punishment value is infinite, nor that a fitting crime has to be infinitely abhorrent to the point of nonexistence. I would argue that it would be slightly worse than life in prison; this is why these are usually these options are so difficult for a jury to decide between, because they are as close punitively as they are. I would hazard that if you offered death over life in prison to fresh convicts, a decent amount would prefer not to rot out in prison. This isn't something you can compare pseudomathematically as you are trying to do; eveything is relative.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjqhxt</id>
        <replies>
            <author>nikatgs</author>
            <ReplyBody>How does that imply there is nothing worse. it quite simply states that death is permenant ans thus secularly can be considered infinite. Obviously there are worse punishments that death, although intersingly very few are used by modern correctional systems. i for one would like to know which countries still make you watch your loved ones being beaten?? OP is about modern capital punishment. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjs02j</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;How does that imply there is nothing worse.

if it's infinitely "bad" how can there be a worse punishment than it? Are you trying to argue cardinalities of different kinds of infinitely "bad" punishments? 


&amp;gt;it quite simply states that death is permenant ans thus secularly can be considered infinite.

Permanence only implies infinite punishment if you think that people can live infinitely long. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjs5nc</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>nikatgs</author>
                    <ReplyBody>OP doesnt say its bad, rather OP is about the length of service. 
&amp;gt; Permanence only implies infinite punishment if you think that people can live infinitely long

People cant live infinetly wrong and that is a valid point both I and OP neglected to consider
</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgjseu5</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>joemama19</author>
        <ReplyBody>I didn't really believe in capital punishment, but then I read this article: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence_Bittaker_and_Roy_Norris

These two men tortured, raped, and killed at least five teenage girls in the back of their van in 1979. Read the full descriptions of what they did to the five girls.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgjrpf5</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>So you are advocating capital punishment as a form of revenge? I'd just like to make that clear before I write a long winded post responding to that. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgjrryv</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgjsbov</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Let us assume for the sake of argument that revenge is indeed a legitimate goal of the justice system. Nevertheless, capital punishment is a flawed sentence. One point often raised against capital punishment is the fact that it is irreversible. If the goal is revenge, why can't we imprison someone for life in miserable conditions? Not only could we adjust how miserable or torturous those conditions are as appropriate to the crime, possibly even worse than death, but in the rare case that someone was wrongly convicted we can free them from at least part of their sentence. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgjseg4</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgjsfho</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Best to just kill them and move on. Think of their "souls" as a cancer that needs to be eradicated by high intensity radiation.

You aren't advocating just revenge then... Are you implying that society is somehow better off by them being dead vs lifetime in solitary confinement? They both essentially have no impact on the rest of society (if you have an argument otherwise, I'd like to hear it!) . Yeah there's cost involved but as it stands, court costs with appeals and such forth often equal if not outweigh life imprisonment. 

There is a lot of appeal in a simple, convenient solution like killing them and moving on, but I think we're obligated to at least *try* to find the most moral course of action. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgjshk2</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Taodeist</author>
<ReplyBody>.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgjsjxa</id>
<replies>
    <author>[deleted]</author>
    <ReplyBody>How does extremely painful/miserable imprisonment not also serve as a deterrent if we are to take this route? If, for example, it's well known you'll... I dunno, take regular acid baths (w/o dying) for the rest of your life or something equally extreme, wouldn't that also be a deterrent? 

I'm also curious if you actually have any statistical evidence of capital punishment having a deterrent effect. I actually had to research the topic for a class and could not find any definitive findings one way or the other, but that was a few years ago. 

(Also, now you're introducing another motive *besides* revenge, which I explicitly asked for in my first post of this comment thread, but that's beside the point because I think my argument still applies. )</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgjsmob</id>
    <upvotes>4</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>dcxcman</author>
                    <ReplyBody>What does revenge accomplish exactly?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgjshq9</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgjsjal</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>dcxcman</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Why are either of those two things good?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgjsl9b</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Taodeist</author>
<ReplyBody>.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgjsms1</id>
<replies>
    <author>dcxcman</author>
    <ReplyBody>So are you trying to shape behavior (either in the person convicted or in others who might be tempted to commit a crime), or is there some other reason you favor draconian punishment?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgjtj4c</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<replies>
    <author>TheAwesomeTwo</author>
    <ReplyBody>And why is it better?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgjtlxr</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
