<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>65</commentCount>
    <id>22ss7b</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/22ss7b/cmv_the_death_penalty_can_be_justified_but_the/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Amablue</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The only course of action for these criminals is capital punishment.

Why is it the only course of action? Whats the drawback to just sticking them in jail for the rest of their life?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq0i1x</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Dark512</author>
            <ReplyBody>I honestly believe a life in prison would be worse than the death sentence. With the death sentence, that's it, you're gone. Life in prison? It's.... Well, life in prison. Cut off from the outside world, from family and everyone else, surrounded by other murderers etc. It would be hell.

To add to this, there's the normal "but what if they're innocent?" The 'collateral damage' of the consequences would be far too great. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq4uux</id>
            <replies>
                <author>jerry121212</author>
                <ReplyBody>Ok, but everyone else might not share that opinion. I think the best solution is make our prisons healthy places to live with the intention of actually rehabilitating people.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq9cgp</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>awa64</author>
                <ReplyBody>Are you saying you'd rather die than go to prison and be released later?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq6djs</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Dark512</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I imagine life in prison would be pretty sucky. I don't know if I'd prefer to die or not honestly, but when I say life in prison I mean until your dying breath, no chance of being released later.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq6g06</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>awa64</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I'm not sure what you mean by "collateral damage," then. If someone were unjustly accused, isn't exoneration always a possibility?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgq6i6g</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Dark512</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I was referring to OP's comment about collateral damage. I mean, if an innocent were put to death, that's the collateral damage, whereas if you're found innocent while in prison then you're released.

I think we're both on different pages here. Did you think I meant an innocent possibly being killed would be better than prison?

I'm confusing myself now...</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgq6mbw</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Facetious_Otter</author>
                <ReplyBody>They can be released. How can you say that "But life in prison would suck more than death" 

Tell that to the people who DO get released. They are MUCH happier that they didn't die. Sorry, but unless it's YOU who is going to death row or life in prison, I don't think you should be able to choose death.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq7ov6</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Dark512</author>
                    <ReplyBody>It's just my personal thing. I don't know if I'd rather die or spend my life in prison honestly, I just mean that, for me at least, the isolation would really fuck me up.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq7sjt</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Facetious_Otter</author>
                        <ReplyBody>But you can say what others would prefer.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgq8gti</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>kaminamina</author>
            <ReplyBody>It is often important to the victims and/or the victim's family that the victim is killed. If they fit all my criteria, it's unlikely they're contributing much to society, and unlikely that they're capable of being rehabilitated as well.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq5czh</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Amablue</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; It is often important to the victims and/or the victim's family that the victim is killed. 

Important in what way? They feel they've been wronged so they want to get revenge?

&amp;gt; If they fit all my criteria, it's unlikely they're contributing much to society, and unlikely that they're capable of being rehabilitated as well.

This is also an argument for life in prison. I'm questioning why we should take the extra and irreversible extra step of killing them. Is it worth killing and number of innocents to exact some level of revenge? Can you really justify that by saying it makes the family of the victims feel better?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq5uu7</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>kaminamina</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Well... yeah, they want revenge. Why not give it to them? What is one murdered life compared to the satisfaction of a family? What's the point in keeping them alive?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq606l</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Amablue</author>
                        <ReplyBody>There are a lot of reasons to not give them that satisfaction. The biggest reason being that you're going to kill innocent people from time to time. That alone makes the whole idea a nonstarter in my mind. It's absolutely never okay to put people do death if they're innocent, especially if your only justification is to make other people feel better. You're prioritizing peoples feelings over a human's life.

If I really, really hate frank, should I be allowed to kill him? Of course not, my satisfaction with franks death doesn't justify killing him no matter how much I hate him. I don't see why it should make a difference if I hate him for killing my family or if I hate him for the color of his skin.

The question comes down to "what is the purpose of punishment?" I argue that we should only punish people when it serves to prevent future harm. Killing a criminal doesn't prevent future harm any more than throwing them in jail does. There are three main ways punishment serves to prevent harm: it deters bad behavior, it isolates dangerous people, and it *can* rehabilitate wrongdoers so they do not commit crimes again (though our current system doesn't do much to rehabilitate). Killing people doesn't serve any of these ends. It just creates more suffering with the reason that we think they deserve it and that somehow makes it okay.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgq6bgo</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>krausyaoj</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Killing does serve the purpose of preventing future offenses. It is currently more expensive due to the cost of legal appeals. If execution took place immediately after conviction then the death penalty would cost much less than prison.

We spend so much on execution to attempt to save innocent lives. But innocent lives are lost every day from many causes including vehicle collisions, fires, and other accidents. If we spent the money on avoiding the loss of innocent lives in the most cost effective maner, legal appeals for death penalty convicts would not be the most cost effective method.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgq6vf2</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Hemingwavy</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;If we spent the money on avoiding the loss of innocent lives in the most cost effective maner, legal appeals for death penalty convicts would not be the most cost effective method.

You know we could just imprison them right?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgql4tp</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>10</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BenIncognito</author>
        <ReplyBody>I don't see how your three requirements eliminate the possibility of killing an innocent person.

 &amp;gt; However, even the slim possibility of accidentally killing an innocent is something which I cannot abide.

The only way to ensure we *never* kill an innocent is to never kill anyone.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq0u1b</id>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>jrafferty</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'm not sure if this kind of responses is against the rules, because I want to change your view on something you did not list in your original post.

For the most part I agree with everything you said, I think you just missed addressing something in your list.

You say  
&amp;gt;I feel that these requirements would all but eliminate the possibility of accidentally killing an innocent

But none of your changes really does enough to eliminate this possibility.  I believe that in capital cases only, the standard of guilt needs to be raised.  Reasonable doubt is not good enough when deciding the fate of a person's life.  I believe the state should have to prove irrefutable guilt instead of guilt beyond a reasonable doubt.  

For example, when there is a mass shooting, there is enough evidence to prove absolutely who did it.  This type of case provides the kind of evidence that I'm talking about. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq0z3b</id>
        <replies>
            <author>kaminamina</author>
            <ReplyBody>I agree, but the standard of guilt for the death sentence is already extremely high, because if there is any (and I mean ANY) doubt after the initial trial, there will more than likely be several appeals, and cases involving capital punishment are very often heard by the SCOTUS.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq5gxs</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>FaerieStories</author>
        <ReplyBody>What's the point? Why not just put them in prison for life? Do you crave their blood? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq0kor</id>
        <replies>
            <author>AWildCesarAppeared</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Do you crave their blood? 

There are two arguments for capital punishment that don't rely on a retributive line of reasoning: 

1. The threat of death is a very useful deterrent of would-be criminals who would commit severe crimes (e.g., murder, rape, etc.)

2. Death is the ultimate incapacitation. A criminal is no longer a danger to society if they are dead.

This is not to say that there aren't criticisms of these arguments as well, but proponents of capital punishment don't all rely on the "murderers deserve to be put to death" cliche.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq1ytx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>FaerieStories</author>
                <ReplyBody>1) There is no statistical evidence that the death penalty is any more effective a deterrent than a life-sentence.

2) A criminal is no longer a danger to society if they are in prison for life either. Yes, there's the chance they might break out - but the odds of that are so slim that it's probably more like that they are a wrongly convicted innocent.

&amp;gt;This is not to say that there aren't criticisms of these arguments as well, but proponents of capital punishment don't all rely on the "murderers deserve to be put to death" cliche.

The OP of this thread does. Read his response to the post of mine that you replied to.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq22vc</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>AWildCesarAppeared</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The OP of this thread does. Read his response to the post of mine that you replied to.

I did, and specifically this part—

&amp;gt;There are some crimes so vile, so reprehensible, that those who choose to commit these are often, in my opinion, beyond rehabilitation.

—fits both a retributive and a utilitarian reasoning. The idea of killing a criminal because the crime is "vile and reprehensible" sounds like the former, and the idea of killing a criminal because they are beyond rehabilitation is more utilitarian.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq2hqo</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>FaerieStories</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; and the idea of killing a criminal because they are beyond rehabilitation is more utilitarian.

I don't necessarily see that as utilitarian. It doesn't explain why they need to be killed as opposed to locked up for life.

And anyway, even if they the OP did argue that somehow killing them is more practical or cheaper than locking them up for life - in what possible way is that remotely moral?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgq2n79</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>AWildCesarAppeared</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I don't necessarily see that as utilitarian. It doesn't explain why they need to be killed as opposed to locked up for life.

If a criminal is beyond rehabilitation, then this would mean they would continually be a threat until they die. Capital punishment ushers what life imprisonment eventually ends with. The idea is that since we know, say, Joe is completely homicidal and cannot be rehabilitated in any way, then it would be more reasonable to simply execute him. A life in prison—however small it might be—still gives him the possibility of escape. We could also include the dangers of confining the criminal as well; a dead Joe only needs a grave while an alive Joe needs security watching him—who can also be harmed themselves.

The crux of the issue though is whether if we (or more specifically the courts) can be reasonably certain that someone like Joe is both **a)** guilty and **b)** beyond rehabilitation. If we can, then we would have a pretty strong case for capital punishment. Presumably though, our current criminal justice system is fallible to the point where **(a)** and **(b)** aren't possible in any circumstance. In which case, it is not capital punishment itself that is necessarily wrong but the way it is implemented. Improving implementation would solve this issue—which is what the OP is seemingly arguing for.

&amp;gt;And anyway, even if they did argue that somehow killing them is more practical or cheaper than locking them up for life - in what possible way is that remotely moral?

Killing another being need not always be wrong. Self-defense, for example, is still homicide—but it is *justifiable*. Likewise, proponents of the death penalty can argue that it is justifiable, like self-defense.

EDIT: Words.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgq32ml</id>
                            <replies>
<author>FaerieStories</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Capital punishment ushers what life imprisonment eventually ends with.

So does murder. It doesn't make it any more moral.

&amp;gt;A life in prison—however small it might be—still gives him the possibility of escape

It also gives him the possibility of being proven innocent, which is actually a more likely option than him escaping from prison.

&amp;gt;We could also include the dangers of confining the criminal as well; a dead Joe only needs a grave while an alive Joe needs security watching him—who can also be harmed themselves.

Like I say: being convenient doesn't make it any more moral.

&amp;gt;The crux of the issue though is whether if we (or more specifically the courts) can be reasonably certain that someone like Joe is both a) guilty and b) beyond rehabilitation. If we can, then we would have a pretty strong case for capital punishment.

Yes, assuming that we've already decided that it's completely fine and moral to take a human life just because we think he deserves it. And I don't happen to agree with that.

&amp;gt;Killing another being need not always be wrong. Self-defense, for example, is still homicide—but it is justifiable. Likewise, proponents of the death penalty can argue that it is justifiable, like self-defense.

Except they can't, because the only reason they are doing it is to make themselves feel good - to give them the satisfaction of revenge (which they call 'justice') and sate their bloodlust for someone who has wronged them. Killing in self-defence is justifiable because it is quite literally your last resort. Killing someone because you don't like them is nothing more than killing someone because it makes you feel better. It's barbaric, and should have no place in civilised modern society. It deserves to be firmly part of our troubled and violent history as a species. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgq3j0p</id>
<replies>
    <author>AWildCesarAppeared</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;So does murder. It doesn't make it any more moral.

Right, because murder—by its very concept—is unjustified killing. Whether capital punishment is justified or unjustified is what's being argued.

&amp;gt;It also gives him the possibility of being proven innocent, which is actually a more likely option than him escaping from prison.

Assuming we can be reasonably certain that someone is guilty though, then this doesn't seem to be an issue.

&amp;gt;Like I say: being convenient doesn't make it any more moral.

The argument is not operating on convenience though. The reasons being brought up are legitimate and need to be addressed. Simply dismissing them as only being somebody's convenience does not suffice without proper argument.

&amp;gt;Yes, assuming that we've already decided that it's completely fine and moral to take a human life just because we think he deserves it. And I don't happen to agree with that.

Nothing is being said that the criminal "deserves it". There's no retributive reasoning here. It's an utilitarian argument. You're misrepresenting the argument if you believe it is arguing that it is ok to take a human life if the human deserves it.

&amp;gt;Except they can't, because the only reason they are doing it is to make themselves feel good - to give them the satisfaction of revenge (which they call 'justice') and sate their bloodlust for someone who has wronged them.

It's not clear whether proponents of the death penalty really—"deep down inside"—all want to "sate their blood lust" and only argue for retributive reasons. That seems to be a very presumptuous generalization.

And even if we granted that this is correct, so what? You still have to address their arguments; addressing their intentions does not address the actual issue and reasons given. A proponent of the death penalty can still be within reason to support it in a utilitarian manner and still harbor retributive feelings towards the criminals. This is no different than being within right to defend yourself against an attacker and still have animosity to those who attack you.

&amp;gt;Killing someone because you don't like them is nothing more than killing someone because it makes you feel better.

No where in this argument (and even in the retributive one) does it premise that it is ok to kill someone because "you don't like them and it makes you feel better".</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgq4fph</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>kaminamina</author>
                    <ReplyBody>What reply? I was at school and just started responding like ten minutes ago.

I would consider the death penalty a mercy compared to life in prison, and it's also satisfying to the victims.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq5emw</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>FaerieStories</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I would consider the death penalty a mercy compared to life in prison, and it's also satisfying to the victims.

A mercy? So you think that the majority of criminals would choose death over life in prison?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgq5mxq</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>kaminamina</author>
                            <ReplyBody>No, but I would. And giving the choice to the criminal is a bit counter to the whole point, no?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cgq5slw</id>
                            <replies>
<author>FaerieStories</author>
<ReplyBody>Well yes. But I wouldn't be against giving them the choice. What I'm against is killing them whether they want to be killed or not. I find that incredibly immoral, and I don't really see why that makes you any better than them.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cgq5tvx</id>
<replies>
    <author>kaminamina</author>
    <ReplyBody>I'm better than them because I didn't murder/rape someone. That should be fairly obvious. 

If someone rapes my daughter, and I can prove it beyond a shadow of a doubt, you're damn right I'll be out for blood. How does that make me a lesser person?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cgq643d</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>8</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>14159265</author>
                <ReplyBody>If you want to use the threat as a deterrent, you should use torture instead of death. The longer and more painful the torture, the more effective. Maybe a publicly viewed torture session over a long period of time would be most effective. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgrxrac</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>Because the people who the criminal murdered didn't get to live a life, and neither should the criminal. That is justice. 

If somebody were to murder your loved one for no reason, you would want justice. And that is one of the purposes of the government, to punish criminals fairly, in order to respect the victim(s) and their families.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq0s9b</id>
            <replies>
                <author>FaerieStories</author>
                <ReplyBody>So because people do bad stuff to us, that gives us the right to do bad stuff back to them? You consider that to be moral?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq0zp8</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>maybachsonbachs</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Following on this line of logic, /u/Steelerskickass should support stealing from thieves and raping sex offenders and dumping trash on the yards of those who litter.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq190a</id>
                    <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Yes, if they don't care about us why would we care about them?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cgq9t5c</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>FaerieStories</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Because we are (presumably) better people than they are.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cgqhs28</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Because the people who the criminal murdered didn't get to live a life, and neither should the criminal. That is justice.

Let's say a criminal kills an entire family. Would justice be to kill that criminal as well as his entire family? What if a criminal committed identity theft? Would justice be to make that identity of that criminal (birthday, address, phone number, social security number, etc) public? What if a criminal is arrested for involuntary manslaughter. Should this criminal then be killed accidentally? The idea that an eye for an eye equates to justice is false.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq1sj7</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>m0arcowbell</author>
                <ReplyBody>That is not justice. That is revenge.  The purpose of the justice system is to remove and rehabilitate people who are dangerous to society, not satisfy someone's bloodlust.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq1zqm</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Sharkbait_ooohaha</author>
        <ReplyBody>Our justice system (US) is set up so that you are either declared guilty beyond the shadow of a reasonable doubt or innocent. If you are found guilty of any crime you should be punished appropriately. It doesn't make sense to have lesser penalties because we aren't sure. Either we are sure enough or we shouldn't be punishing them at all. I understand that innocent people are sometime found guilty and when the death penalty is involved it seems more terrible but that is a fault of the jury trial that will always exist. Every punishment should merit the same level of proof of guilt otherwise the justice system is not fair and impartial. Mistakes do happen but there is no perfect system.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq0vyb</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Pinewood74</author>
            <ReplyBody>The burden of proof in criminal cases is beyond a reasonable doubt, not "the shadow of reasonable doubt", whatever that is.  And actually in america we do allow lesser punishments for not being that certain.  They just have to be done in a civil case.  Think OJ Simpson here; only need preponderance of evidence in those.

Also, I don't see OP advocating for different rules regarding different burdens of proof.  Just that the death penalty should only be used for repeat offenders.  Which isn't new, we already have different penalties for the number of times someone has committed that offense.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq57jb</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>hacksoncode</author>
            <ReplyBody>The reason it's important in this case, where it is not that important in other cases, is that there is no way to correct a mistake if it is later found.

That makes the death penalty *qualitatively* different from all other punishments that we mete out. 

Even that said, I think you'll find that we don't view things that way in society. The burden of proof that we accept for traffic citations is abysmally low.

Also, "beyond a reasonable doubt" is not the same thing as "beyond a shadow of a doubt", and your mixing them just obfuscates the question. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq52o7</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>hacksoncode</author>
        <ReplyBody>What does any of this have to do with whether the person is "innocent" of the crime?

It would seem to me that if you want to avoid killing innocents, you would be focused on what kind of *evidence* we would need in order to be sufficiently certain that we're not making a mistake. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq53th</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>krausyaoj</author>
        <ReplyBody>None of your requirement separate the innocent from the guilty. We can all agree that [Adam Lanza](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Hook_Elementary_School_shooting) is guilty of murder but would fail to meet your requirements.

Who deserves capital punishment and what is the purpose? If deterrence is the purpose then capital punishment should be much more widely applied. One option is for all crimes with a victim, each convict had a [10% chance of execution](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decimation_(Roman_army\)).</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq6eu3</id>
        <replies>
            <author>kaminamina</author>
            <ReplyBody>My requirements were meant to differentiate between "possible to rehabilitate" and "not possible to rehabilitate."</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq6tz7</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>awa64</author>
        <ReplyBody>The death penalty is already more expensive than sentencing someone to life in prison, simply due to the more stringent standards for prosecuting a death penalty case. Adding even more restrictions is likely to raise the cost even further. From an economic standpoint, the death penalty is entirely unjustifiable and your argument only makes the problems worse. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq6g8x</id>
        <replies>
            <author>kaminamina</author>
            <ReplyBody>My restrictions are objective and easily measurable, except for the sanity part, but that restriction already exists. My plan would reduce the number of death penalty cases.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cgq6sqj</id>
            <replies>
                <author>awa64</author>
                <ReplyBody>Reducing the number of cases doesn't help when the inefficiency is per-case.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cgq746m</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>Personally, I think that the standard for what deserves the death penalty should actually be *lower*. I think that anyone who shows a pattern of "devoting" their life to being a general sack of shit should just be culled.

However, I don't think that the death penalty should *ever* be used in practice because there will always be the possibility of executing the innocent, and I find that to be totally inexcusable, since life imprisonment accomplishes most of the same goals while being quite a bit more reversible.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgq7ho8</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why are you limiting it to the sane? Ted Bundy was super fucked up, and he died inn the chair. I don't think any therapy could fix him, so why waste money on a serial killer who derives pleasure from death, and let's say he was caught literally red handed. Why should we give him food to eat while actual humans starve but he gets free food in prison?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgqf85x</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Hemingwavy</author>
        <ReplyBody>It fails to deter crime and is more expensive than life imprisonment.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgql4an</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Pepperyfish</author>
        <ReplyBody>you only need to do a little research to realize that what makes the death penalty wrong isn't the idea of killing someone it is the idea that we are so bad at picking the right people. Eighteen people have been saved by project innocence alone, if they had been slower that is eighteen people who did no wrong who would be dead, and I would much rather let a guilty man go than fry a innocent.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cgqqf64</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>There are some crimes so vile, so reprehensible, that those who choose to commit these are often, in my opinion, beyond rehabilitation. The only course of action for these criminals is capital punishment.

However, even the slim possibility of accidentally killing an innocent is something which I cannot abide. What makes us better than the people we're condemning if we accept that collateral damage is a possibility?

I would suggest the following requirements:

- The accused must be over 25 years of age (the median age at which many neurologists say your brain stops developing).
- The accused must be a repeat offender of violent crimes.
- The accused must be declared sane by a neutral, respected psychologist.

I feel that these requirements would all but eliminate the possibility of accidentally killing an innocent, while keeping the death penalty as a possibility for those that truly deserve it.
_____

&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than just downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
