<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>137</commentCount>
    <id>4u5b66</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/4u5b66/cmv_if_we_must_use_the_death_penalty_the/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5n42gv</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>Surely it needs the same as my method?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nftpx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5nfy53</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>My post was inspired by this video:

https://youtu.be/XcvkjfG4A_M

You can see that there's someone there to save him, and it was rapidly depressurised, but you can just as easily place someone in the tank and leave them there alone without a mask. The room itself slowly depressurises, and they lose consciousness.

I've yet to hear any benefits to using N2O over the low pressure tank</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5ng58b</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>exosequitur</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Cheaper.  Like 50 dollars of equipment cheap.  Physician can verify death before turning off the gas.  Pleasant euphoria.  </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5ngut0</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I HIGHLY doubt it'd only cost $50.

Also in the grand scheme of things executions in the US cost multiple millions of dollars, what is a few extra thousand?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5nh8qe</id>
                            <replies>
<author>exosequitur</author>
<ReplyBody>I mean the apparatus.  A standard o2 mask,  Regulator,  and a rented no2 bottle.  The execution itself,  well,  that's probably a cashfest for God's only know who. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5nh9zx</id>
<replies>
    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
    <ReplyBody>Right but these sorts of tanks I'm talking about already exist. I don't really know how much they cost to use/rent/build/etc but I don't think cost should be a deciding factor in how we end people's lives</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d5nhayi</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>exosequitur</author>
<ReplyBody>A human sized vacuum tank is probably in the 100k range. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5nhaii</id>
<replies>
    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
    <ReplyBody>So you have one per state that is practicing executions. Or maybe one in every few states. Each execution costs around $3 million

Let's say we use this tank for 40 years, starting now. There's currently around 40 per year, over 30 ish states. So let's say there's one per year per state. If every state had one, then that cost could be cut down over 40 executions, right? So it'd be only 20k per execution. When they cost over $3million to go to court and prisons, what is the extra $20k?

Could cut that down even more if you just placed them in areas where more executions take place, i.e. Texas, Oklahoma, Virginia, Florida, etc</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d5nhdvj</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Fontaine911</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Are there any negative side effects for that guy?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5o746a</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>No ?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5okynx</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>18</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Oliver5366</author>
        <ReplyBody>Isn't suffocation, even slow suffocation, intensely painful before the euphoria?

There's also a cost factor; would this be fiscally feasible?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5myokh</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>This isn't suffocation. Watch videos of people in low pressure tanks, they're clearly under no pain

Also death penalties are already immensely expensive. I'd like to see data to show why this is fiscally not feasible </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n0dce</id>
            <replies>
                <author>browster</author>
                <ReplyBody>You can replace the air with pure nitrogen.  The person breathing doesn't notice the difference, but gradually loses their senses without really going through any distress.  I recently saw a video of an experiment that pilots did related to this.  It didn't look unpleasant at all, but if they left it to continue it would certainly have been deadly. After seeing that I was left thinking that if I wanted to end my life (and I don't) that'd be the way to do it.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n6jyp</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Sure but why is that different to just lowering the pressure? Seems like more could go wrong</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nfvdx</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>browster</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It seems to me that lowering the pressure could have unpleasant side effects related to the mechanical aspects. Getting the bends, for example.  People feel changes in pressure for differences encountered in an airplane, which of course is nowhere near what is needed to suffocate.  I don't see what could go wrong with just pumping pure N2 into a chamber.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5nk17l</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>If there was such a risk why do we train people and let people do this optionally?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5nkkpy</id>
                            <replies>
<author>browster</author>
<ReplyBody>Encountering a depressurized environment is a potential hazard for some occupations, and people doing that work need  to train for it so they know how to react in case it happens. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5nofyp</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>11</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Trenks</author>
                <ReplyBody>so deadpool was fulla shit then?!?.... sonsabitches...</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5nbhak</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>If your brain lacks oxygen you just get a little confused and a bit shaky, but you don't feel any pain and a lot of people say it actually feels great, like very surreal or euphoric. Sounds perfect for executions. They wouldn't resist at all, just slowly let it happen until they pass out</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nfybd</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>StaplerTwelve</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You get a need for air if the CO2 level in your blood it too high, *not* if the oxygen is too low. I can't remember what they did in the movie though..</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nf816</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Bears_Rock</author>
                    <ReplyBody>There's a distinction. When the body is prevented from breathing (ala dead pool), the feeling is akin to drowning or holding your breath for too long. This is very painful and stressful, and the basis for water boarding. In the movie Deadpool, they essentially left him in a constant state of suffocation for a long period of time. The oxygen wasn't replaced with nitrogen, the chamber turned into a vacuum. 

The scenario above replaces the oxygen with nitrogen. The body can still breath of its own volition, there is no pain or panic about "not breathing", but the body is still deprived of oxygen and death occurs. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nm06v</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>7</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>swarlay</author>
            <ReplyBody>It's not the lack of oxygen, it's the buildup of carbon dioxide that causes a bodily reaction. That doesn't happen if you inhale and exhale normally in an environment with little oxygen.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nvfcv</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Aubear11885</author>
        <ReplyBody>Correct hanging isn't choking, it's a neck snap. That's why there is a drop, otherwise they'd just tie a noose and hoist, which is how they used to torture folks in things like lynchings. I would actually suggest some sort of smaller form of the guillotine. Design it to sever the connection quickly without decapitation, the guillotine was designed to be a humane execution machine. I think this might not be cost effective initially, but one could set up a singular location that all executions take place at for all states. 

Edit: or we could easily and cheaply set up an automated firing squad. Unfortunately while cost effective, likelihood of initial survival is decently high and painful. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5mzbek</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Edit: or we could easily and cheaply set up an automated firing squad. Unfortunately while cost effective, likelihood of initial survival is decently high and painful.

Not only that but someone ultimately has to pull the trigger</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n1g8u</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Aubear11885</author>
                <ReplyBody>no, it would be automated. You'd hit a button or switch just like the lethal injection system</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n1uva</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;no, it would be automated

So how does it know when to fire?

&amp;gt;You'd hit a button or switch just like the lethal injection system

So somebody has to tell it to fire? What's the difference between this and a gun?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n2ubc</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ayyy__1mao</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Well every execution method requires someone to push a button. I think people just don't like how visceral it feels to actually be pointing and firing the gun.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5n4pat</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Exactly, hence why it should feel to them less like murder</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5nfu1g</id>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>cfmat</author>
                        <ReplyBody>In the old West there was a system designed where the condemned would walk onto a plank and set off a firing squad of rifles pointed at him after a slight delay. Only used once though. There was a similar design for hanging. 

Forces someone to essentially commit suicide, which may be an issue in and of itself I guess. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5nbpdh</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Exactly my point, requires their consent so tons could go wrong</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5ng0kr</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Krieg-The-Psycho1</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Someone has to administer the gas for them to die of hypoxia </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5n6tnz</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>You didn't read my post did you? You use a low pressure tank and just slowly thin the air. No need to administer any gas. They don't go through any pain so the executioner would be less mentally traumatised, in theory</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5nfw5l</id>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>john_gee</author>
        <ReplyBody>You can't suck the air out of a room without either replacing it with something or creating a vacuum. If it's the latter, I'm willing to bet the change in pressure before dying would be pretty unpleasant. If the former, what are you going to replace the air with that won't cause the body to go into distress from breathing it?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5mz2ei</id>
        <replies>
            <author>autonomicautoclave</author>
            <ReplyBody>Probably some mix of N2 gas and CO2. both are already abundant in the atmosphere and aren't toxic (except in the sense that they displace vital oxygen which in this case is the point)</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n0412</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Shufflebuzz</author>
                <ReplyBody>Replace the oxygen with nitrogen.  It already makes up 78% of air.  

The body notices high carbon dioxide levels. That's what makes you hyperventilate and gives the "burning lungs" feeling when you exercise. You can't get the CO2 out fast enough.  </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n0e5p</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>autonomicautoclave</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Your right. I was too busy thinking as a chemist about what is technically toxic that I forgot some basic biology.

sidenote: technically toxic would be a good name for a band</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n135t</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>4</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>john_gee</author>
                <ReplyBody>Nitrogen makes sense. It's inert, and already abundant in the atmosphere. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n0bvt</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>speedyjohn</author>
                <ReplyBody>What about NO2? Laughing gas people to death. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n2z8a</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>tstrimple</author>
            <ReplyBody>You don't take all the air out of the room. Simulating the air at 25,000' is enough.

https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kUfF2MTnqAw
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5ncn63</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>browster</author>
            <ReplyBody>Pure nitrogen.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n6lzh</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>smp501</author>
            <ReplyBody>Car exhaust? Doesn't that just make people go to sleep (and then die)?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5mzl8l</id>
            <replies>
                <author>john_gee</author>
                <ReplyBody>Carbon monoxide can be pretty unpleasant too. My understanding is that they might fall asleep, or might die hacking and choking, but I could be wrong.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5mzv5l</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>smp501</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Oh wow I had no idea!</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n0pny</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>Err, yes you can. It makes the pressure drop and therefore less oxygen. Astronauts and pilots do this stuff all the time</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n0fbm</id>
            <replies>
                <author>john_gee</author>
                <ReplyBody>The pressure drop is what I'm referring to by "vacuum." Not necessarily a complete vacuum like space. Astronauts and pilots do it all the time, but not to the point where they die. And depending on what's going on with your inner ears, pressure changes can be really unpleasant for some. Did some googling and it looks like lowering the O2 content by replacing it with nitrogen is the winner. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n0mab</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>A pressure drop isn't a vacuum, far from it

Astronauts obv don't do it to a point where they die, because they have people to save them if they go too far. Astronauts are tested in scenarios that could kill them if they aren't assisted or sort themselves out. Obviously in my OP this wouldn't be the case</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n0tnd</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>4</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>autonomicautoclave</author>
                <ReplyBody>yes but they are extensively trained and conditioned to deal with changes in pressure and the changes happen relatively gradually. If you plan to evacuate the chamber quickly, a better analogy would be to a diver getting the bends by ascending to quickly. If you want to draw it out slowly, aren't you concerned about the potential psychological impact of sitting in a room for hours knowing that your death is coming?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n0p23</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>It doesn't have to happen over hours, merely minutes. At 25,000 feet altitude you lose consciousness in a few minutes, and a big chunk of that time you're not fully conscious but in a sort of euphoric limbo. It isn't painful, as people have been in this situation multiple times and described it when conscious as just surreal and painless, you're at ease and don't really care

It doesn't have to be one extreme or the other</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n0wkq</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>phcullen</author>
                <ReplyBody>Part of the reason they do those test is to see if you are tolerant to those kinds of pressure changes anyone with sinus issues could feel like their head is exploding, air bubbles could expand in their blood causing the bends or if they hold their breath could stretch their lungs. 

All horrible experiences that could be caused by the pressure change its silly when you can accomplish the exact same thing by displacing oxygen with another gas </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5pb06k</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>SomeAsshatOnTheWebs</author>
        <ReplyBody>Wouldn't a better method be giving the convict a mask attached to a tank of nitrogen and have him inhale that? It requires less money (there is no need to put air removing ducts and other required equipment the room), and it's also painless.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5n910k</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>Seems like thay requires consent of the convict. Most people don't consent to dying</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nfwh1</id>
            <replies>
                <author>SomeAsshatOnTheWebs</author>
                <ReplyBody>By that logic what makes your method more consensual to the convict than mine?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5ngepa</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>It doesn't require consent. I'm not saying it has to require consent, I'm saying putting a mask on them that is giving them poison has too many issues like them ripping it off. You'd have to restrain them or it would never work. You could just shake your head or twist your jaw and try throw it off. You can't just shake off an entire room</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nh6qi</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SomeAsshatOnTheWebs</author>
                        <ReplyBody>You could always just restrain to a table like they do with lethal injections....</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5ntnpo</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Seems like unnecessary mental trauma</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5okwz4</id>
                            <replies>
<author>SomeAsshatOnTheWebs</author>
<ReplyBody>But they're gonna be dead in a few minutes anyways though....</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5pl6n4</id>
<replies>
    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
    <ReplyBody>They still have human rights</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d5psr7o</id>
    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>4</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>NGeX</author>
            <ReplyBody>You would have to strap down the convict. That would cause trama to not jsut the convict, but the attending officers as well. In a tank, after the door is shut, the convict could get up, walk around, get on knees, do push ups, whatever. They still have a moment of freedom before death. Even if they committed a horrible crime, I think they should be given that moment. Remember, the average citizen is meant to take the high road.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5t0fcd</id>
            <replies>
                <author>SomeAsshatOnTheWebs</author>
                <ReplyBody>Don't most people about to get executed get a lavish last meal as that "last moment of freedom"?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5t31x3</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>NGeX</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Well...most States in the US have actually cut that program because it costs too much. Many inmates were asking for expensive foods. So now most inmates just get the regular prison food before death. So no, that "last moment of freedom" was taken away.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5t3e5y</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>AZebracake</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Aw what a shame.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5t52kc</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SomeAsshatOnTheWebs</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Eh I guess that guy ordering a bunch of gourmet steaks and then saying he's not hungry pissed the police department off a lot....</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5topmn</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>NGeX</author>
                            <ReplyBody>It actually got removed because one guy requested his dinner be donated to a homeless man</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5ub11f</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>FuckTripleH</author>
        <ReplyBody>I dispute the importance execution being without trauma or messiness

Say what you will about the medieval days when petty theft resulted in limbs being chopped off and any number of crimes carrying the death penalty 

But at least they were honest about what it was. If you wanted someone executed then someone had to personally decapitate them. It was bloody and barbaric *but that's what capital punishment is*. 

If we as a society have decided that people should be executed then no one should be able to hide behind euphemisms like "humane". 

Quick and painless should be the primary goals and in that regard a reasonably large caliber bullet to the base of the skull accomplishes both just fine.

But it also would hopefully have the side effect of making people a little less willing to dole it out as a sentence</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5n4sqz</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>This doesn't really address what I said</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nfus7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>cephalord</author>
                <ReplyBody>Yes it does. It offers a counteropinion to your central point #4.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5nj5d8</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>FuckTripleH</author>
                    <ReplyBody>And #3</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nzube</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>RemoveKebabz</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why shouldn't the manner of execution be up to the condemned (within a range of reasonable options). Maybe a pamphlet or a counselor to give the damned the pros and cons of each method. 

Personally if I were to be executed I would want either the firing squad or the guillotine.  

Both are cheap, relatively painless, and almost certainly fatal. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5na1he</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>I've addressed why these are bad methods, they aren't always painless and you can survive them. Furthermore firing squads make the shooters get serious mental issues because they are shooting unarmed people, convicts or not</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nfxeh</id>
            <replies>
                <author>RemoveKebabz</author>
                <ReplyBody>Well even way back when they had contraptions that served the purpose of a firing squad. 

Maybe something like this hooked up to a computer. https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=oWEqyrKLz6M

But that wasn't my main argument, I just meant the condemned should be given the choice. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5nnh87</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>sheeple666</author>
        <ReplyBody>Aren't "suicide bags" with nitrogen the preferred method by euthanasia organizations? I can't remember the name but I think there's a documentary somewhere where a guy sets out to find the most humane way to kill another person and he decided on Nitrogen Aphasia. If you're interested I can try to find the link</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5oi3jf</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>I've seen similar documentaries where they find it to be altitude hypoxia, but I'd be willing to watch yours if you can find it :)</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5okz3b</id>
            <replies>
                <author>sheeple666</author>
                <ReplyBody>https://vimeo.com/83750163 

How to Kill a Human Being</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5p6bky</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Sheexthro</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Painlessness to the convict. It is, after all, justice, not revenge. We are not executing people to torture them, but because they did something we agreed they should pay for with their life. We don't want to turn our justice systems into revenge killings. We've moved past that.


No, we have not. This is the fundamental problem with your view: you misunderstand the social purpose of the death penalty.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5mzsxx</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>The point of it is, like all sentences, to reduce crime by creating incentives not to commit the crime.

Whether this works or not is another issue but that is the intention</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n0rap</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Trenks</author>
                <ReplyBody>That's not necessarily true. The death penalty is to eliminate that particular offender who can't be stopped otherwise from existence. And jail is to keep dangerous people from society, not to scare people into not committing crimes. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5nbmk8</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Ugh no, the death penalty is meant to deter people from committing certain crimes. If all you wanted to do was stop them committing any more crimes you'd just put them in jail for life without parole. Most people I would argue if they were dead set on murder they'd be more likely to think about it longer if they knew they could be killed. Although I don't agree with the death penalty as it hasn't been shown to actually reduce crime, the point of it is a deterrence

Mostly the point of prison is rehabilitation and deterrence, but execution has no chance for rehab.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5ng07s</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Trenks</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Ugh no, the death penalty is meant to deter people from committing certain crimes.

You realize just because you say something doesn't make it so. Some could argue it's not for society as a whole or deterrence it's literally for a punishment of a crime as it possibly was in history. A secondary benefit is deterrence, but it's not it's sole purpose. If we just want to deter crime we'd still put their heads on spikes or torture people who committed crime.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5ngmae</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Yes but why do we punish crime? To stop people comitting further crime. So why do we execute people? To give a warning to future would-be criminals

I'm not here to debate whether the idea of capital punishment is ethical</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5nh7ha</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Trenks</author>
<ReplyBody>Again, if you have a rapist and you kill him it's stop that particular person for raping another person, not really to stop someone else from raping. That may have the secondary psychological effect, but killing a rapist is to quite literally making sure that particular person never rapes again.

You're acting like punishment in the justice system has nothing to do with the actual person who committed the crime and it's all about sending messages.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5qqh3m</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Satafly</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;And jail is to keep dangerous people from society, not to scare people into not committing crimes.

When I was in front of a judge he literally said

"If I give this man a light sentence, what's to say I'm not sending an effective message of deterrence"

It might be a good idea to only speak about issues you have knowledge in.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nskfy</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Trenks</author>
                        <ReplyBody>That's like saying a cop shot an innocent black man therefore it's the job of all cops to kill black men. One judge doesn't make it so. And the thing about the law and justice system is it's in the eye of the interpreter. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5qq14m</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>NGeX</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Has it occured to anyone that the fact that the US jail systems are so horrible that these people who keep re-offending aren't getting any ACTUAL rehabilitation? There are ways to do this. Just look at the prison systems in Sweden. They educate their inmates, teach them social skills, give them access to decent living quarters. You know...they don't treat them like pitbulls in a pound.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5t0ldz</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Trenks</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It has occurred to the swedish.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5u220w</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Stevey854</author>
                <ReplyBody>If you believe that the purpose of the death penalty is as a deterrent, then it logically follows that the execution should be made as horrific as possible and televised live across the country so as to better deter others. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5pw6o3</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No because they have human rights. I'm not here to debate whether it works but it is obviously meant to be a deterrent. If it was just meant to stop people committing further crime we'd just lock them up for life. It'd be cheaper too</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5pwwnc</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Stevey854</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Locking people up for life would not be cheaper than summary execution in an inhumane and painful manner. 

Beating a guy to death on the steps to the courthouse with baseball bat is essentially free. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5pxmes</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>And that's true justice right there... /s

As it stands in the US life in prison is cheaper than execution</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5py20x</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Stevey854</author>
<ReplyBody>And that's a flaw with that specific system of execution, not an issue with execution as a whole </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5py4uv</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Sheexthro</author>
                <ReplyBody>I really don't think this is true either historically or contemporaneously. The history of executions - particularly public executions - has been *very little* concerned with the comfort of the victim.

edit: Downvotes don't change views, my friend.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n0zbv</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Complete rubbish. The reason why lethal injection is used over other quicker, easier and cheaper methods is because of the painlessness to the convict. Since it is the first choice for all practicing states shows the clear intent to cut down painlessness and make the execution more "ethical"

Purposefully choosing a more painful method is hugely controversial, and while often convicts have the choice themselves it is rare for it to be forced upon them. We HAVE moved past that, as can be seen by the fact states have over time moved towards lethal injection over electrocution, gas poisoning and other methods.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n1dcz</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Satafly</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The reason why lethal injection is used over other quicker, easier and cheaper methods is because of the painlessness to the convict

Nope, the lethal injection was introduced because it was less traumatic for the viewers. They are widely understood to be more painful than hanging, shooting or beheading.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5nslqw</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Sheexthro</author>
                        <ReplyBody>But as you state in your OP (and as I'm sure all of us know) lethal injection *isn't* painless. In fact, the three-drug cocktail that most American states use doesn't even have a painkiller! People who are executed by lethal injection often undergo intense, excruciating agony.

It has the *appearance* of painlessness, I guess, but that's because the victim is paralyzed and unable to thrash about in pain.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5n1g50</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Hence why we need to create a more painless method, such as my suggested method

It has widely been accepted to be less painful as electrocution, hanging and gas poisoning, hence why they fell out of fashion for it.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5n1ib2</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Sheexthro</author>
<ReplyBody>I think that the reason electrocution and gas poisoning fell out of favor is that they *appeared* to be more painful, and the screams and thrashing were distressing to the people watching it right there. But fundamentally, as a society, we're fine with executed prisoners spending their last moments in excruciating agony, as long as we don't have to *literally see it* with our own two eyes.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5n1l8z</id>
<replies>
    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
    <ReplyBody>That doesn't solve the problem of them actually being barbaric though</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d5n2skr</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<replies>
    <author>notcatbug</author>
    <ReplyBody>If that was true, why wouldn't we just put them in a gas chamber and *not* watch them die? We wouldn't have to see it. I think implementing an entire new method (lethal injections) shows that it wasn't just so we didn't have to watch them suffer, it was to make is so they didn't have to suffer. But they still do, with lethal injections.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d5n8z9h</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Trenks</author>
        <ReplyBody>First, I don't think there would be zero unforeseen problems at all. that's usually not how the world works. Second, there is still dread when they close the door. That's terrorizing in and of itself. There really isn't a good or civilized way to kill a man. It's an act of destruction of life, it shouldn't really be treated as anything but that. I think a guillotine would do the trick. But maybe in machine form so you can't see anything and it's all computer activated. It's 'barbaric' but yeah, that's what state sponsored murder is.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5nbla8</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Heis3nberg</author>
        <ReplyBody>Lethal injection by Nembutal would probably be equally as peaceful, and easier/cheaper to implement. It would also take a lot shorter than decompressing a room.

Helium/laughing gas, as other posters mentioned are better options by your standards too.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5ncnwg</id>
        <replies>
            <author>GnosticGnome</author>
            <ReplyBody>Except for the pain of IV insertion (which is usually a comedy of errors at present since doctors and most nurses won't participate in executions, and fear makes veins hard to find).  The other issue I have with lethal injection is that it pretends execution is a medical procedure which it emphatically is not.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nefw3</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Heis3nberg</author>
                <ReplyBody>True. Laughing gas it is then. Although I don't think anyone is pretending lethal injection is a medical procedure. It involves a syringe but that's it.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5neimh</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                    <ReplyBody>https://www.jstor.org/stable/4065314?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents

I think that medicalization of death is probably the number one reason we have such a silly method despite its inconvenience and extra pain compared to bullets or nitrogen gas.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nelm5</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>What benefits does laughing gas have over low pressure tanks?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5ng175</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Heis3nberg</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I suppose it would be cheaper to install? Nitrous oxide gas can be delivered via masks, while low pressure tanks would require you to empty an entire room.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5ng5e5</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Right but then they just have to fight and remove the mask so you're strapping them down and putting them through that fear. With the tank room you can just keep chatting to them as if nothing is happening and slowly they are getting less and less oxygen</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d5ng6h8</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Heis3nberg</author>
<ReplyBody>True.. But one difficulty I see with this method is that while they're losing oxygen, it wouldn't be quite painless. When people struggle with hypoxia, they're usually struggling with too much carbon dioxide instead of a lack of oxygen. In fact your body can't even notice a lack of oxygen. While the oxygen+co2 is being depleted and replaced with an inert gas or whatever, they would still struggle for awhile cause of the co2 buildup.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d5ngc95</id>
<replies>
    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
    <ReplyBody>Watch videos of people in this scenario, it is completely painless</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d5nh61r</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>maybe_I_am_a_bot</author>
        <ReplyBody>I have to disagree. If we are to have an execution, the method must be specific to the legal system. Thus, in the case of the USA, twelve stabs with a knife followed by decapitation.

One stab for, and by, each juror, followed by the completion of the sentence by the judge. If people wish to have a person killed, they may do the deed themselves. If they do not wish to do this themselves, then they can think about whether or not the person truly deserves death. Having executions be clean and without mental trauma for the executioner just makes people pretend its not the violent ending of someone's life without their consent.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5ngnl3</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not here to debate whether it is ethical</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5nh83y</id>
            <replies>
                <author>maybe_I_am_a_bot</author>
                <ReplyBody>You're trying to find an ethical method for suicide, and say that hypoxia is the best way to go about it. I'm just saying that you should look beyond just the person put to death to find the most ethical way to kill someone.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5nhf2a</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>That's what I'm doing. I don't think it is ethical to kill people but then I know some places do it so if they must I think this is the most ethical way</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5nhmbt</id>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>darthben1134</author>
        <ReplyBody>My ways are the old ways.  The person who passes the sentence should swing the sword.  I would go for beheading by a juror.  We need to do less sanitizing of state killings, not more.  It should be brutal and honest.  It SHOULD be traumatic to everybody involved.  And, if you are willing to pass a death sentence, you should do so with the knowledge that you may personally have to carry it out.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5nptkm</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>outrider567</author>
        <ReplyBody>"painlessness to the convict" and the families and friends of the murdered victims would like to know if the victims of these murderers experienced any "painlessness" WHEN THEY WERE MURDERED</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5nvs7k</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>This isn't justice, this is frontier justice. It's barbaric. Families of the lost shouldn't decide the punishment or how it is carried out</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5okxen</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>stickyliverhopkins</author>
        <ReplyBody>for the pain some people inflict on others to justify getting the death penalty why would we want to give them "one more high" on their way to hell .... burn them alive 

let something horrific happen to someone you love and see how gentle you want to lay them down </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5o6cr7</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>This isn't how justice should work. It's barbaric, primitive. We need to move past this whole ideology ASAP

Convicts still have human rights, we can't just torture them</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5okyjh</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>rtechie1</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Mental trauma to the executioner. ... Any way to cut down on this trauma is beneficial.

Why? Shouldn't killing people be traumatic? Sorry, I find this concern to be base and cowardly. If you won't get your hands dirty, don't get involved. 

&amp;gt; Cleanliness. Absolute obliteration causes essentially instant death with no pain or chance of survival. But it is gruesome, disgusting, and uncivil. We need to make the deaths as clean as possible, be it in blood, vomit, organs, whatever. I

It's this just denialism? It's like the packaged meat in the supermarket. Not seeing the slaughter let's you pretend it's not happening.

&amp;gt; Firing squads have never been massively popular, 

Given the choice, this is what most convicted murderers choose because there is a certain dignity to the firing squad. The also choose it because it's more traumatic, they want their killer to look them in the eye. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5qkb20</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Why? Shouldn't killing people be traumatic?

I don't think it's the executioner's place to decide what is right and wrong, it's just their job

&amp;gt;It's like the packaged meat in the supermarket. Not seeing the slaughter let's you pretend it's not happening.

I'm a vegetarian

&amp;gt;The also choose it because it's more traumatic, they want their killer to look them in the eye.

Another reason it shouldn't be allowed</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5qm1eq</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>NGeX</author>
            <ReplyBody>OP mentioned that he is anti-death penalty in general, but since the view is not going to change in the US Justice system any time soon, he is suggesting an alternative system that would have the smallest psychological footprint possible. There will ALWAYS be someone responsible for the execution, but OP is referring to a single action like the push of a syringe or trigger or button. Shutting a door is a mundane thing in comparison.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5t0pqj</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Hq3473</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think execution by artillery is pretty good. 

We take the condemned out to a desert artillery range, than a round is fired out of his sight, and he is pulverized.

Easy, effective, impersonal, reliable, no cleanup costs.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d5n34ot</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Krieg-The-Psycho1</author>
            <ReplyBody>Or execution by explosion. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d5n6w5s</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Hq3473</author>
                <ReplyBody>Artillery is better.

Tne condemned does not see explosives, the gunners can't see the condemned.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d5n8n2a</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Krieg-The-Psycho1</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You have to know exactly where the person is to use artillery, and may require multiple shots</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d5n8qdk</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Hq3473</author>
                        <ReplyBody>No,  you train the artillery on the precise spot, mark it with a gps, and then you bring the condemned over and tie his hands behind a pole.

The jeep drives aways, radios over to arti. Boom. It's all over.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d5n9596</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>I believe that we shouldn't use the death penalty but I understand some people want to and they are welcome to that opinion. I'm not here to debate whether we should, just if we do, how we should. I think there are 3 main objectives in the death penalty and we should aim to maximise all 4, in this order:

1. Chance of killing the convict. If there is a slight chance they may survive the execution, it shouldn't be carried out. It causes undue torture to not only the convict but to the person carrying out the execution.

2. Painlessness to the convict. It is, after all, justice, not revenge. We are not executing people to torture them, but because they did something we agreed they should pay for with their life. We don't want to turn our justice systems into revenge killings. We've moved past that.

3. Mental trauma to the executioner. Someone ultimately has to be responsible for the death of the victim. Whether they have done horrendously vile crimes or not, they are still a human and ending their life will have at least some impact on the executioner. Most people would SAY they would be OK with killing a mass murdering paedophile, but if it came to it I believe most would think first, and think afterwards. Any way to cut down on this trauma is beneficial.

4. Cleanliness. Absolute obliteration causes essentially instant death with no pain or chance of survival. But it is gruesome, disgusting, and uncivil. We need to make the deaths as clean as possible, be it in blood, vomit, organs, whatever. It also has some effect on the executioner.


I'm British and we don't use the death penalty, and I'm glad of that, so for this CMV I will use the US as an example of a country that executes criminals. Currently in the US there are 5 legal methods of criminal execution;

* Lethal injection (most common)

* Electrocution in Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Kentucky, South Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia

* Gas inhalation in Arizona and California

* Hanging in Delaware and Washington

* Firing Squad in Utah

Lethal injections have long been known to cause issues, for example issues finding a vein can cause undue mental trauma for the convict. Furthermore failures in the exact protocol for executing people in this way can cause severe pain for the convict. This means that both point 2 and 3 from the before. It fails in these issues, so I don't believe it is perfect. Furthermore people have been known to survive long times after injection, when under pain.

Electrocution has fallen out of fashion for the exact reason that often times the convict survives the initial electrocution and must be shocked a further 1 or 2, possibly more times. This fails point 1, but furthermore it means the convict is in severe pain when they die. Instant electrocution could be OK if it killed you instantly, but as has been shown in history that isn't the case.

Gas inhalation is similar to my proposed method, but it has a serious difference. It introduces a poison into the body, instead of restricting oxygen. The poison works actively negatively on the body, rather than just passively. This means the convict is in pain, and often very much conscious to the pain they are in. Multiple accounts of people moaning, screaming and thrashing in pain have been recorded in US prisons. A prison warden even said he'd quit his job if they made him do another, meaning this fails points 1, 2, 3 and 4 of my above post.

Hanging isn't painless, convicts thrash about as they gasp for air. They can physically feel their windpipe restricted and consciously know of the danger they are in. Mere videos of real life hangings show people clawing their throats out to try and remove the rope from their neck. We see videos of people being hanger in places like ISIS controlled territory and say it is barbaric. We talk about it in revolutionary France, and pirates in the Caribbean (ha) and act like it is something from the past. But it is very much still an option in parts of the US. It's quite effective in killing convicts, but it is painful for no reason. Therefore it fails point 2, possibly 3.

Firing squads have never been massively popular, but they rely on there to be someone to physically shoot the convict. We try and cut down on firing squad trauma by using blanks, multiple shooters, etc... but it still means people are actively walking up to their convict, pulling the trigger, and watching them die. This plays on people's minds, regardless of whether they had a blank or not. It also creates unnecessary mess, adding more trauma and failing points 3 and 4. 

Now, hypoxia. We can cause this by using a sealed "tank" much like a gas chamber or similar room. The air is SLOWLY pumped from the room while people slowly lose consciousness, become euphoric and just drift into black. They pass out, and eventually they die from lack of oxygen. In slow and gradual decompression it is almost always painless, and people despite being conscious are totally unaware of the pain they should be in. Watch videos of people optionally going through decompression. They talk about how they knew they were going to die, but simply didn't care. They were just in a state where everything seemed somewhat confusing, but also OK. No pain, no chance of survival, no poison. Just a lack of oxygen, unconscious, dead.

It's clean, it causes little trauma to convict or executioner, and should therefore be the only method of execution used in any country that wishes to call themselves civilised.

CMV!

_____

&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
