<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>67</commentCount>
    <id>1zhoyc</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/1zhoyc/if_death_penalty_opponents_were_ideologically/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>sguntun</author>
        <ReplyBody>This may seem like a glib answer, but what's wrong with the response that while a military and police force that are equipped to kill serve a necessary function (namely, protecting us), the death penalty serves no such function, because everything it accomplishes can also be accomplished by imprisonment?

Note also that we can hold this view while opposing the *actual operations* of the military and police, which we might think *don't* primarily serve the function of defense and security. We can think that but still accept that there is a *necessary* role for the police and military to play, even if they are not playing it right now, or if they are doing other unrelated things as well.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftrtic</id>
        <replies>
            <author>L34der</author>
            <ReplyBody>Can imprisonment save up over 1 million$ of taxpayer money? Don't bring up private prisons please unless you yourself actually advocate them.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfu49nu</id>
            <replies>
                <author>sguntun</author>
                <ReplyBody>Can the death penalty save money? It's my impression that it's actually more expensive than life imprisonment.

But let's grant that it can, and that imprisonment will always be more expensive. So what? That may be a reason to prefer the death penalty, but it has nothing to do with either OP's position (that it's not "ideologically consistent" to oppose the death penalty if you don't oppose the police and the military's license to kill) or my point that there's no necessary function the death penalty serves that couldn't be served by imprisonment. Saving a certain amount of money is not a necessary thing to do.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfu9uxv</id>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>The death penalty costs a lot more than imprisonment. Neither saves anybody any money. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfuaiyd</id>
                <upvotes>4</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>18</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I would say that many of them do so.   There are many anti-Police brutality and anti-War movements, are you unfamiliar with them?
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftqxz6</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
            <ReplyBody>I am familiar with them, but I am saying that they should not only oppose war and police brutality, but they should oppose the police and army killing anyone under ANY circumstances, just like they oppose the death penalty under ANY circumstances.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cftqzcw</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftrbko</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No immediate danger, true, but they could present a danger in the future. Also, what if there is a cartel or mob leader who is running his operation from behind bars, as many of them do, and his cartel or mobs is actively killing its opponents? And even though you've interrogated all the guards, you still can't figure out which one is in cahoots with the cartel leader. That seems like an immediate danger to me, and one which happens quite regularly. Would the death penalty be okay at that point?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cftrdqd</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cftrlzc</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                            <ReplyBody>So we have to leave him alive in prison to run his operation with impunity (and kill dozens more people) just because the police were unlucky enough to have captured him alive rather than put a bullet in his head right then and there? The only difference to me seems to be a difference of timing, and whether it's the judicial or the executive branch doing the killing.

People are still killing and being killed because of the cartel leader's continued life. Should we just release him from prison and then deliberately get in a gunfight with him, and kill him then? That would seem like a good strategy to get around your arbitrary prohibition of killing someone unless they possess an "immediate danger." Ironically, it would save more lives too, which death penalty abolitionists seem to be keen on.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cftru06</id>
                            <replies>
<author>DannyNullZwo</author>
<ReplyBody>Sry but your example is stupid. Why would you let him run his operation in prison?


In the case that you don't know if he is running a operation from prison, you would have no cause to punish him (killing or whatever).

In the other case you could easily prevent him from doing so, put him in solitary confinement and restrict his access to communicate to the outside world. And when you want to argue that something like this wouldn't be possible legally or practically, than this would be your problem to solve.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfudycu</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>10</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Would killing the leader even stop the cartel? Probably not. Not to mention that again the leader is not posing a direct threat</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cftrfii</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Let's say, for argument's sake, that it would stop the cartel, because the leader is that essential to their organization. If not stop the cartel outright, it would at least hamper their ability to kill more innocent people. I'd call that a direct threat, wouldn't you? His continuing to live means that others continue to die.

He may not be posing a direct threat, but if it's okay to kill a soldier who is "just following orders" and a general during wartime who is "only commanding troops," why should the cartel leader get a free pass? Just because society was unlucky enough to have captured him alive instead of being fortunate enough to shoot him in an armed standoff? Why should immediacy change the treatment we give someone?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cftrm6w</id>
                            <replies>
<author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Let's say, for argument's sake, that it would stop the cartel, because the leader is that essential to their organization.

This is becoming a very hypothetical situation. And an even simpler solution is just to transfer him to another wing, or even another prison depending on how much power he has.

&amp;gt; I'd call that a direct threat, wouldn't you? His continuing to live means that others continue to die.

Yes, but not in the same way. you can easily prevent him from continuing to guide the cartel, and as such, there exists a non lethal means to stop him. The same is not so if an officer encounters him in his hideout shooting at the officer.

&amp;gt; He may not be posing a direct threat, but if it's okay to kill a soldier who is "just following orders" and a general during wartime who is "only commanding troops," why should the cartel leader get a free pass? 

The solider isn't following orders, the soldier is trying not to die. He is stuck between a rock and a hard place. Kill the RPG dude, or die. He is acting out of self preservation and doesn't have a non lethal means of stoping the RPG dude, thereby limiting his options to dying or lethal force. And the general doesn't necessarily get a free pass. If he messes up, and kills multiple civilians, the blood is on his hands, and he will have to face the consequences.

&amp;gt; Why should immediacy change the treatment we give someone?

Once again, the issue is the level of the threat at that moment in time. If he's shooting at you, it's much higher than if he is stuck behind bars.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfts7fd</id>
<replies>
    <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
    <ReplyBody>How do time or level of threat justify or excuse killing?

If I commit a murder a year from now, how is it any better or worse than if I commit a murder today?

Situation A: I walk into the room after a rapist has raped and murdered my sister, and I kill him then and there.

Situation B: I walk into the room and he escapes, and I swear vengeance. Then, after a year of tracking him down, I finally find him and kill him for what he did a year ago. From my point of view it doesn't matter, I'm killing him for the same thing.

How is B worse than A? He still ends up dead, and for the same actions. From the rapist's point of view, situation B is preferable, because he gets to live another year.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cftsd4t</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>4</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>reonhato99</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; No immediate danger, true, but they could present a danger in the future.

So we should just kill people because they might be dangerous in the future. Who has the privilege of being the overseer who predicts the future. Do we kill prisoners who have not yet murdered but are violent. Do we kill people who are mentally unstable.

There is a huge difference between killing in active self defense and killing someone in a premeditated execution. 

Personally I think the US stance on guns being openly available for self defense is stupid, it does not mean I don't believe killing in self defense is never justified. I think the death penalty is wrong, it does not mean I think that killing is never justified, it means I think the premeditated execution of a captured, unarmed person is wrong </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfts8bp</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Why is it any worse than killing them while they are committing the act? 

Situation A: I walk into the room after a rapist has raped and murdered my sister. I see that he has a gun, and, fearing for my life, I reach for my own gun, I kill him then and there.

Situation B: I walk into the room and he escapes, and I swear vengeance. Then, after a year of tracking him down, I finally find him and kill him for what he did a year ago. 

How is B worse than A? He still ends up dead, and I killed him for the same actions. From the rapist's point of view, situation B is preferable, because he gets to live another year. From my point of view it doesn't matter; I just want him dead.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cftsgsx</id>
                            <replies>
<author>reonhato99</author>
<ReplyBody>Self defense is the difference. Self defense is not pre-meditated, it is something no one should have to do but unfortunately it does happen. Self defense is stopping something that is already happening. 

If you chase someone down, someone who is not threatening your life then you are simply a murderer. It does not matter if the person has raped or murdered someone, we do not punish people with an eye for an eye, it is also not up to you to decide his guilt and punishment. 

The word you used, "vengeance" is really a big part of the issue. The death penalty is all about vengeance. It is not about punishment or about rehabilitation. You should not have a right to get your vengeance, especially when your idea of vengeance is death. One persons illegal and wrong acts do not give you a right to do the same to them. To do so make you no better then them. 

For a society vengeance is not a good thing, it leads to a never ending loop. Criminals should be treated with punishment and rehabilitation, punishment for the act they committed and rehabilitation to lower recidivism. What the punishment should be is up to society to decide and most modern countries have decided that death is not a just punishment.   </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cftu4id</id>
<upvotes>7</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>17</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Some of them do.  Others may have different nuances to their views, such as seeing a distinction between a deliberate execution and the hypothetical homicide that is not adjudicated as criminal.  But I don't doubt that all of them would prefer that no such event occurred, whether at the hands of the police, the military, or even a civilian.



</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftr7w5</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Then why don't they advocate for completely disarming the police under all circumstances, including when the police are facing off against other armed people. After all, there's a small chance that an innocent person could die, just like with the death penalty.

They also should advocate for the complete abolition of the military, even in wartime. After all, if killing people is always wrong, no matter what they have done (or plan to do, or try to do) then the military is 1000x worse than the death penalty.

Death penalty opponents' focusing solely on the death penalty is like mowing your lawn when your house is on fire.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cftrb14</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Crayshack</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Then why don't they advocate for completely disarming the police under all circumstances, including when the police are facing off against other armed people. After all, there's a small chance that an innocent person could die, just like with the death penalty.

If the police are disarmed, how can we expect them to be able to stop an armed criminal from harming innocents?

&amp;gt;After all, if killing people is always wrong, no matter what they have done

I don't view killing as always wrong, I view executions as unnecessary.  In wartime, killing is sometimes necessary.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cftssmj</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; If the police are disarmed, how can we expect them to be able to stop an armed criminal from harming innocents?

Tasers, stun guns, etc. Seems to work okay in the UK. Though they do have some armed units and under the anti-death penalty logic, even those should be done away with. Maybe throw a net around the criminals, but my point is that if you can't kill them with a trial, you certainly can't kill them without one. It's unjust.

&amp;gt;I don't view killing as always wrong, I view executions as unnecessary. In wartime, killing is sometimes necessary.

Do you view ALL executions as unnecessary, or just some of them? If so, why are you willing to concede that killing in wartime or by the police is sometimes necessary, but executions are never necessary under any conceivable circumstances? 

What leads you to take an absolutist view on executions but a flexible view on war? War kills far more innocent people.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cftt84j</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Crayshack</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Tasers, stun guns, etc.

Every nonlethal weapon has it's drawbacks.  If we had stun guns as effective as what you see in Star trek, maybe this could be a valid course of action, but the reality is that nonlethal methods are significantly less effective than lethal methods.  For example:

&amp;gt;Maybe throw a net around the criminals

Every method we have available requires getting very close, which puts the net thrower in significant danger.  Even then, our most advanced net throwers have terrible accuracy and reload time, so getting in net throwing range isn't a guarantee that the criminal will be netted.  Finally, a determined person can still be dangerous inside a net.  If they have a knife they can cut their way out and if they have a gun they can still shoot someone from inside the net.

&amp;gt;Do you view ALL executions as unnecessary, or just some of them?

The vast majority.  I can see a hypothetical scenario where someone remains too dangerous even when in custody or is too skilled at escaping and is dangerous once loose.  But hose situations are rare enough that there is no need to have executions as a possible punishment for the average criminal.  I could see the necessity of executions maybe once every couple of years world wide.

&amp;gt;What leads you to take an absolutist view on executions but a flexible view on war? War kills far more innocent people.

Wars would kill more innocent people if we did not fight back.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cftwjfr</id>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>LontraFelina</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Tasers, stun guns, etc. Seems to work okay in the UK.

Because very few people have guns in the UK. It wouldn't work nearly as well in the US.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cfudndv</id>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I don't know who "they" are or that they aren't advocating such things.    But I certainly don't think they are solely focusing on the death penalty either, there are many who do speak of their opposition to these things you mention.

And as I said, a person can draw a distinction between a deliberate execution and the hypothetical homicide that is not adjudicated as criminal.  The latter is not an endorsement of force, but a decline to punish.  And perhaps instead of "killing people is always wrong" their sentiment may be more accurately expressed as something like the "state should never deliberate kill a human being as part of its policy goals" rather than your phrasing.  

And again, I don't doubt that all of them would prefer that no such events occurred, whether through the form of executions, wars, or the death penalty.  They may be able to accept them, or even find them needful, but that doesn't mean they don't oppose them.  They just aren't making the same choice of activities as you would prefer, but make other ones.  

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cftrnh8</id>
                        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Mad_Hatter_Bot</author>
                <ReplyBody>Would you include abortion?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftx9ic</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>9</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>081613</author>
        <ReplyBody>Military and police confrontations are not as predictable. If we could still meet the goals of military and police forces without lethal force than your argument would make more sense. A prisoner on Death Row is not a risk to society and it costs more for society to kill them than to have them confined to prison for the remainder of their lives.

It is a reasonable request that we don't kill people if we don't have to, but police and militaries sometimes have to in order to work effectively. The judicial system doesn't need to kill people.

That is the main difference that I see between the two, predictability/necessity.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftr02i</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; A prisoner on Death Row is not a risk to society and it costs more for society to kill them than to have them confined to prison for the remainder of their lives.

There are many cartel leaders who run their businesses from behind bars. Prisoners also could potentially escape, or harm other inmates. Look at Mexico and ask yourself if they would be in the same situation versus the cartels if they had the cajones to put a bullet in their heads?

As for cost, the military budget (of the US at least) dwarfs every other nation's, and is higher than the next top ten combined. 

The police and military could still function without killing someone. They could use tear gas, rubber bullets, or tasers. Even the military could function by stunning their enemies with knockout gas and rounding them up into POW camps.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cftr32l</id>
            <replies>
                <author>081613</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;There are many cartel leaders who run their businesses from behind bars. Prisoners also could potentially escape, or harm other inmates. Look at Mexico and ask yourself if they would be in the same situation versus the cartels if they had the cajones to put a bullet in their heads?

Mexico doesn't have a problem because they don't have the death penalty. There problem is that they have too many corrupt officials and prison guards who are in the pockets of cartels.

&amp;gt;The police and military could still function without killing someone. They could use tear gas, rubber bullets, or tasers. Even the military could function by stunning their enemies with knockout gas and rounding them up into POW camps.

There are many situations where non-lethal measures are not effective during police work. How about a hostage situation for example.

A non-lethal military is no military at all. The fact that you propose knockout gas and POW camps as an alternative is laughable. The plan of knockout gas wouldn't even work against guerrilla warfare much less a modern military with hermetically sealed tanks, destroyers, bombers, etc.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftrmdd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                    <ReplyBody>It's no more laughable than refusing to kill someone who is sitting in prison running an operation which is actively killing dozens of people, and whose death would severly hamper his cartel's effectiveness and save dozens or hundreds of lives. All because you were unlucky enough to have captured him rather than killed him in the field.

The reason that the autodefensas have been successful where the Mexican government has not is because they, unlike the government, is willing to use lethal force and shoot these murdering cartel leaders right where they stand. They don't waste years on a trial or put them in a cardboard prison. They do what needs to be done: they kill them.

Why you think this is wrong when having a lethal military is okay is beyond me. Both result in death.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cftryhr</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>081613</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Why you think this is wrong when having a lethal military is okay is beyond me. Both result in death.

There are plenty of countries that do not have the death penalty that also have a well functioning justice system. Every country in Europe, for example, is required to ban capital punishment. There are no examples of non-lethal military because it doesn't work.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cftx0a1</id>
                        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think you are grossly exaggerating the reach prisoners on death row have. They are the most strictly controlled group in any prison system. Their communications are tightly monitored, much more so than general population inmates. Death row inmates are typically confined to their cells for 23 hours a day. They are allowed an hour of exercise in individual yards.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfu8h8d</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>down42roads</author>
        <ReplyBody>I would argue that there is a great difference between use of lethal force as punishment and the use of lethal force as self defense in th face of imminent danger. There is a great difference between executing a helpless prisoner and actively defending the life and well being of yourself or another person.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftroy9</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
            <ReplyBody>What is the difference? One of timing?

Why should time have anything to do with it? Because someone is helpless at the moment, it's not okay to kill them in that moment? 

George just mugged and shot a man to death. A policeman arrives on the scene, sees George with a gun in his hand, gets into a confrontation and shoots George, who dies. This is okay with you.

Bob just mugged and shot a man to death. No policeman arrives until Bob has already left the scene. They collect DNA and other evidence, a court tries and convict Bob for the murder, and he ends up in the electric chair a year later.

They both still end up dead. The result is exactly the same. And they've been killed for exactly the same actions. Morally, I see no relevant distinction other than one of timing. How is *when* something happens, whether now or a year from now, different? If I commit a murder yesterday, how is it any worse or better than if I commit a murder a year from now?

Also, there are plenty of mob bosses and cartel kingpins who run their operation from behind bars and, if they were executed, their death would hamper their organization's effectiveness and save potentially hundreds of lives. Yet it's wrong to execute them?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfts490</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftspf7</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                    <ReplyBody>If you agree that a delay of death is a good thing, then how can you say that the death penalty for a crime after several years of trials is worse than shooting someone in self-defense in the moment?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cfttzc1</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Your example cheats by making an assumption that the police officer lives, when in fact George does pose a threat to the police officer's life.

The comparable examples would be:
A: Police officer shoots George.  George dies.
B: Police officer doesn't shoot George.  George lives 5 more years while police officer has a 10% chance of dying. 

From a utilitarian point of view, the life of a police officer is worth much more than 10x as much as the life of a murderer who'd spend his life in jail.  But I'd prefer a deontological point of view: you have every right to kill someone threatening you or a loved one no matter how much their/your life is worth.

Now, execution is very different from self-defense because the tradeoff is different.  In the case of self-defense the person is a threat, so you are trading off harm vs harm.  In the case of execution the person is not a threat, so you are not trading off the same harm vs harm.
</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfu10ez</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>the_machinist_</author>
                <ReplyBody>This isn't the same at all. If George is shot by police there is no investigation.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftsjye</id>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
        <ReplyBody>It's not the same thing though. Most police only fire if the suspect poses a significant threat (i.e. tries to shoot them), and a similar issue with the military (see WW2). Not to mention there are most certainly anti war groups anyways.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftr0bw</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
            <ReplyBody>People in prison can pose a significant threat, too. The Supermax exists for a reason. There's always the chance that they could escape, however small. If they are violent, they could potentially harm other inmates or guards. Also, if they are a head of a cartel or other criminal gang, they could still potentially run their operation from behind bars, as many of them do.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cftr5s7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
                <ReplyBody>But the key issue is the threat. A policeman who is getting shot at by an armed man doesn't have a choice not to shoot, as his life is directly under threat. People in supermax pose a threat, but that's why they are in a supermax, where they pose much less of a threat. Same issue with military. If someone fires an RPG at you, you can't just tell him to stop, you kinda have to shoot him.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cftrafh</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Sure he does. He could shoot back with a taser, or a rubber bullet. Or, he could don a bulletproof vest and wait for the shooter to run out of bullets. Even dangerous armed men can be taken into captivity (see the Aurora movie theater shooter) The man he is firing back at has never had a trial. How is that somehow allowed but the death penalty, with trials and multiple appeals, is considered unfair?

As for the guy firing an RPG at you, he could have been under duress or compulsion. His religion could tell him that it's okay. He could just be insane. Killing him is never the answer. We need to have the same compassion for him that Norway shows to Anders Brevik, and put him on a nice island for a few years and let him go. I'm sure he'll appreciate it so much that he'll never kill again. The fact that he is CURRENTLY firing an RPG at you (as opposed to having done it in the past) is of no consequence. Time should have nothing to do with it.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cftrirv</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; He could shoot back with a taser, or a rubber bullet.

Tasers have a limited range and are only so effective. Rubber bullets are even less effective as they can't stop the attacker, only momentarily stop him (if even that depending on whether or not he has any armor). And the military usually caries neither of them anyways.

&amp;gt; Or, he could don a bulletproof vest and wait for the shooter to run out of bullets.

They use them, but they don't work like that. They can prevent a fatal shot, but you can't just have someone unload entire clips into it and walk it off.


If there was a way to have the shooter subdued non-lethally that would be great, but that isn't always possible. The main concern is the life of the officer, which is more important in this case. And again, there are very few times where an officer even needs to use lethal force. Finally, the shooter poses a much more serious threat than someone who is already behind bars and therefore can only pose so much of a threat.


&amp;gt; As for the guy firing an RPG at you, he could have been under duress or compulsion. His religion could tell him that it's okay. He could just be insane. 

Those are not really acceptable excuses. If he is under duress, then he is still shooting at you (unless he is intentionally missing, in which case it would be a completely different story). And the religion thing is not acceptable, as no religion actively encourages violence, only groups that actively misinterpret religions.

&amp;gt; Killing him is never the answer.

The issue is that *if you don't kill him, you will probably die*. It's a life or death decision there, and if you don't shoot, his next shot might hit your vehicle instead of the truck next to you. Not to mention his motives are irrelevant. What matters is the fact that he is putting the soldiers life in immediate danger, and is forcing the solider to react in the only way possible in this situation.


In short, the issue is that in one situation (shooter), your life would be in immediate danger, and if you don't kill the attacker (assuming non-lethal methods are impossible), then you will die. This is not the case for someone who is already subdued and behind bars, as they no longer have this capacity, and as such do not need to be killed (Anders Brevik poses much less danger now then when he was actively shooting people). </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cfts0ds</id>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>gkwilliams31</author>
        <ReplyBody>You are presupposing why they believe that. Your logic is flawed.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfts8iv</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CartsBeforeHorses</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not presupposing anything. In my original post, I listed some common arguments against the death penalty, and showed how those same arguments could be used to argue against armed police and the military.

If there are other arguments for abolishing the death penalty, please bring them to my attention and I will update my post accordingly.

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cftsl7k</id>
            <replies>
                <author>gkwilliams31</author>
                <ReplyBody>One could easily say that unneeded death is wrong. The goal could be to minimize death. I've heard it said that peace is what every soldier wants. Ultimately the goal of police and the military is to protect and save lives. These organizations have a degree of needs death to save lives. One could argue because execution does not save lives it should be banned.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfty44e</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Crayshack</author>
        <ReplyBody>There is a difference between killing someone as a punishment, and killing someone because that is the only way to stop them from harming others.  Whether a guilty person sits in jail or a grave, they will not harm people again, but there is the chance at overturning a wrongful conviction when the person is in jail, not so when they are in a grave.  On the other hand, if someone is waving a gun around, sometimes the only way to stop them from shooting an innocent person is to shoot them first.  It could be that by killing one person, we can avoid the death of many.

**TL;DR:**  I view them as different circumstances and the killing as happening for different reasons.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftspr2</id>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Tytheg</author>
        <ReplyBody>The difference is that with the death penalty, there is a choice. When police have a suspect cornered who is armed and dangerous, sometimes the only way to ensure their safety, and to protect themselves and the rest of the people is to shoot. No cops take a suspect and lay him down and shoot him instead of arresting him, shooting is a last case scenario that is sometimes necessary to guarantee the safety of our police and army officers. Arguing that these situations are the same is not viable, because one involves a choice where the criminal is already arrested and not a threat, while the other there is a clear and present danger, that officers need protection from.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftsoiw</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Ralkir</author>
        <ReplyBody>The gigantic difference being once you have some one in prison (and we could modify the prison to fit the goal), they are completely and utterly no longer a threat. The use of force by military and police forces is to subdue a threat that is currently existent. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftu7lr</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>vanderguile</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think that the budget spend on defence and police help protect lives when used as a defensive force. I oppose wars that I think don't save lives. 

The death penalty costs more than life imprisonment, doesn't deter crime and kills innocent people. 

Aside from that I think taking the time to think about what you're going to do with someone who you believe broke society's laws and coming to the conclusion you should kill then is morally wrong. The immediacy of the situation is quite different. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftwfzm</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>There are a variety of reasons to be anti-death penalty, though.

It's generally more expensive to execute someone in the United States than to imprison them for life because of the appeals process and court costs. Without that process, we would execute the innocent, which we still do even today with that system in place, which is another reason to be against it. There is no way to make up for executing an innocent person, whereas a person sentenced to life in prison can at the very least be released and possibly compensated for their time. Thus execution makes the assumption that not only are we currently certain that the accused committed the crime, but also that regardless of whatever technology comes out in future, there will never be any possibility of finding evidence of the innocence of accused. The current method of execution is possibly very slow and painful, often taking hours for the inmate to die, and cruel and unusual punishments are illegal in this country. We use very little medical reasoning to determine what drugs we use to kill people, and as a result mistakes are made.

There is more to it than a general dislike of killing.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfty03d</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>jcooli09</author>
        <ReplyBody>My main objection to the death penalty is that our justice system convicts too many innocent people.  It goes beyond a simple uncertainty of guilt, it is certain that some percentage of convicts never committed the crime.  We have even seen cases where people have been executed even though their conviction was known to be wrong.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfu1eyg</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>jacenat</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Situation A: I walk into my house and discover that a crazed man has stabbed my family to death. Fearing for my own life, **and enraged at his actions**, I reach for my concealed handgun and shoot him, and he dies.

This is no legal justification to kill a person. Reasonably fearing for your life is (under certain circumstances). If you testify that you were drawing your weapon out of rage, you might be tried for manslaughter regardless. The right of self defense is just that ... a right of **self defense**. In my country (I think it's similar to the US), you are limited to reasonable force executing this right. This means if the murderer is unarmed and weaker than you, you can not kill him with a knife or a gun.

**THIS IS VERY IMPORTANT!** You do not have the right to revenge. The reason for the existence of the justice system is to de-couple feelings from judgment.

&amp;gt; Situation B: I walk into my house, see the murder scene, draw my gun, and the man runs away before I can shoot him. But I spend the next year tracking him down, and finally find him a year later, where I confront him and shoot him when he's unarmed.

Your life is not in danger. It is illegal for you to kill him.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfu1uvo</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Russian_Surrender</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; So, if you oppose the death penalty but support armed police and the armed forces, CMV that you're a hypocrite.

I oppose the death penalty because I just find it stupid and needless (especially with the expensive way it is currently carried out in the United States).  While there is a *tinge* of morality that influences my position, it is far from the dominant thought for my opposition.

Is there anything "wrong" with killing a guy who raped and killed 5 teen girls?  Meh.... maybe.  I dunno.  But since "I dunno", and because there are other alternatives available that I do know are not "wrong" (to me), we should just use those other alternatives.  Especially since those alternatives (as currently enacted) are significantly cheaper than the death penalty.

I also support some wars.  But I only support wars that save more lives than they take.  How many people would Saddam Hussein have killed over the rest of his life had he been left in power?  Is that more or less than the number that were killed as a result of the Coalition's war in Iraq?

I believe that, ultimately, the Iraq war probably saved more lives than it took (obviously, that is highly debateable).  I think the US could save lives by taking military action in The Congo and probably a few other places around the world that don't come to mind off the top of my head.

So I oppose the death penalty but support military actions, and **my view is NOT hypocritical because, in both cases, I support the action that results in the fewest deaths**.  In the death penalty situation, the condemned person lives and no one else dies (because I support detention in a manner that prevents the convict from killing again), so that is a net saving of human life.  In the military conflict situation, I only support those conflicts in which fewer people die in the war, than would have died without the war.

*Note*:  I didn't include armed police officers in my discussion because I don't think they're in the same realm.  Unlike the death penalty and soldiers in war, the primary objective of (good and competent) police isn't to kill, but is to apprehend.  As others have pointed out, (good and competent) police should only kill people in immediate self defense.  A totally different situation.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfu2gft</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>mattpayne</author>
        <ReplyBody>Prison is about quarantine, not revenge and not justice. Military actions are not about quarantine. They're ostensibly (in modern times) about protecting our nation from foreign invaders (although in reality they're about furthering the interests of the oligarchy, which makes many specific military actions morally WORSE than the death penalty, ie. the war in Iraq). Also, military action isn't usually against your own citizens. Also, when police shoot suspects there is (again, ostensibly) an element of danger to the cop.

Generally I don't like the idea of giving the state the legal power to kill its own citizens, unless it's reasonably necessary. Once a murderer is behind bars, the quarantine is effective. I personally feel more comfortable letting him or her live a long life, far away from the people I care about. People who support the death penalty are not thinking about the public good. It helps nobody. I would like to see longer sentences for violent crimes, but no death penalty.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chpsqqi</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BlackHumor</author>
        <ReplyBody>To your edit:

It doesn't matter which scenario the murderer prefers. The reason you get to kill him is to protect someone who is in immediate danger from him (namely yourself): you kill one person and you save one person, so your action is morally neutral. In scenario B you're not protecting anyone, so you don't get to kill him.

Or in other words: viewed in isolation it's equally wrong to kill anyone. It's just that the good you're doing by protecting someone in immediate danger balances out the harm of killing someone.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftxeb0</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ashishvp</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'm not opposed to the death penalty through some sense of morality for our country's worst criminals. I support life imprisonment because of one, simple fact. It's cheaper. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftzrbr</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>human_machine</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think the state should use the least amount of force necessary against its citizens. To that end I believe we should weigh the likelihood that a person convicted of an especially violent crime and imprisoned will harm another person without a conviction for an especially violent crime against the likelihood that we have convicted them in error or in a manner which is unfair (racist, sexist, etc.). 

In short and in plain English, I don't believe our justice system is very good at killing people in a just manner and the risk to the innocent doesn't outweigh the benefit.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfu58uw</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Azmodan_Kijur</author>
        <ReplyBody>I oppose the death penalty, but do not agree with the notion that the argument to eliminate such a penalty can be used to eliminate any "state sponsored" violence. My reasoning is simply reflected in a statement - what is the reason for catching a criminal and imprisoning them? More specifically, do we pursue and imprison criminals because we are seeking revenge or are we seeking punishment (and possible rehabilitation)?

Obviously, I would imply that it is the latter, not the former. We imprison to punish wrongdoing as defined by our social compass as reflected into the laws of the land. To seek revenge is an invalid motive as it gives rise to the "eye for an eye" mentality - seeking to enact pain upon others as they have inflicted. We must punish in a neutral manner, else it loses the legitimacy of social consent to be performed. Planning someones death, as in the case of the death penalty, is akin to premeditated murder. We have a person, John Doe, in this cell. We are feeding them and clothing them, but all in the service of eventually murdering them. In this manner, we are giving them an never-ending feeling of dread not unlike someone that has been murdered themselves.

This is not applicable to the police or the military. The police and the military of our countries (Canada in my case) are not enacting their jobs for the purpose of committing violence or per-meditating murder. They are doing their jobs. In such cases where forced is needed, they assess for the correct amount. In some cases, that means lethal force. It is situation based and somewhat subjective. If the cop encounters an armed man shooting innocents, he is mandated to protect the public with force up to lethality. This is just - the immediacy of the situation enforces the legitimacy of ending a stream of violence with another to protect others.

In this manner, the answers for your two situations become academic. In the first, the situation has immediacy and your use of violence is just. In the second, you premeditate the act, rendering it an act of revenge which invalidates the legitimacy and renders it criminal and immoral.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfu7tmj</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Nineties-Kid</author>
        <ReplyBody>In your thought experiment, consider the benefits of killing the man, beyond whatever satisfaction you get from the revenge. 

Situation A: The crazed man has demonstrated that he is a threat to your life and shooting him likely saves your life.

Situation B: The crazed man is not as likely an immediate threat to your life, so the benefit of killing him is removed. 

So yes, there is a moral asymmetry to these situations. It seems that you are using the uncertainty in these situations to argue that they're the same. Sure, a crazed man with a knife who just killed your family might not necessarily kill you, and unarmed prisoners could kill again. But it is not reasonable to assume both pose equal threats that deserve equal responses. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cfu85m8</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>natph14</author>
        <ReplyBody>In my opinion all good arguments capital punishment were demolished by the life-changing book "Hanged by the neck". The book has two authors: Arthur Koestler and the other C.H. Rolph.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cftxxpd</id>
        <replies>
            <author>pin_seeker</author>
            <ReplyBody>It's cool you have read that book but...more/synopsis/anything? I'm not reading that book so that I understand a point you are trying to make on reddit.

edit: I'm not against reading a good book and I may well read that one, but you added nothing to to the CMV besides plugging a book.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cfty6on</id>
            <replies>
                <author>natph14</author>
                <ReplyBody>Well the initial thread question asks for an argument against the death penalty and I think in suggesting a piece of literature that does just that I have somewhat given my answer: Read the book. It was recommended to me indirectly by Christopher Hitchens and I enjoyed it very much. The book looks at statistical evidence and the fact that putting in place a death penalty does nothing to the crime rate of a population, and takes specific examples of people being hanged to form a very persuasive argument against capital punishment. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cfu98bn</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>I have never heard a single argument in favor of totally abolishing the death penalty in all circumstances that couldn't also be used against having armed police or the armed forces in any circumstances, including emergencies or wartime.

"What if they kill an innocent person?"
"Killing another person is wrong, no matter what they've done."
"You can never know for 100% certain if the person you are killing isn't really innocent."
"It costs too much money to kill or put a person to death." (have you seen our defense budget?)
"Vengeance is wrong; we shouldn't seek to kill others, but rather, we should seek to reform them."
"Being killed is a violation of human dignity."

If you think about it, the death penalty is actually fairer than armed police. If the police shoot a suspect and kill him, he could have been innocent. Or, they could accidentally shoot a bystander. And if the suspect dies, remember that he didn't even get a trial! At least the death row inmate has had his day in court.

And the army? I mean, how many civilians are killed in wars every year? Way more than the actual combatants! Even when the army deliberately avoids trying to kill civilians, accidents still happen.

I think that most death penalty opponents aren't actually anti-death, they are just anti-judicial. The government dealing death is okay as long as the executive branch does it, but the second that the judicial branch does, it becomes wrong somehow? Doesn't make one iota of sense.

Yet that's how many South American nations conduct themselves. They haven't had the death penalty for centuries, yet they have shady death squads under control of dictators that force disappearances of political opponents or other undesirables. They're being hypocrites. 

So, if you oppose the death penalty but support armed police and the armed forces, CMV that you're a hypocrite. Tell me why you oppose the death penalty, and why that reason shouldn't also cause you to be a total pacifist?

**EDIT: One of the main responses I have been getting is that it's okay for the police or military to kill someone who poses an immediate threat, but an unarmed prisoner poses no immediate threat. So in their minds, it's worse to kill someone who isn't an immediate threat. But I'll respond with a thought experiment.**

Situation A: I walk into my house and discover that a crazed man has stabbed my family to death. Fearing for my own life, and enraged at his actions, I reach for my concealed handgun and shoot him, and he dies.

Situation B: I walk into my house, see the murder scene, draw my gun, and the man runs away before I can shoot him. But I spend the next year tracking him down, and finally find him a year later, where I confront him and shoot him when he's unarmed.

Which situation is morally worse? From the murderer's perspective, he'd prefer situation B, since he gets to live a year longer. From my perspective, it doesn't matter as long as the murderer dies. My motivations for killing him are nearly identical in both situations, too.

**This is also assuming that unarmed prisoners aren't a threat. They could always escape, or hurt other prisoners, or guards. If they are a mob boss, they could run their organization from prison, which might indirectly lead to more deaths.**</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
