<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
        <ReplyBody>As abhorrent as I find capital punishment, your solution is far from the most effective and painless. Nitrogen asphyxiation would be my nominee. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chta4vd</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Raiden_Gekkou</author>
            <ReplyBody>This. the inmate falls unconscious before dying, and it's a lot cheaper than the cocktail.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtafjv</id>
            <upvotes>19</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Dux_Spaghetti</author>
            <ReplyBody>Not OP, but what is the process of nitrogn asphyxiation? How much would it cost? How would one set up facilities for this?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtaouq</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>This has come in previous, similar discussions.  If a person is placed in a sealed room that contains an atmosphere of pure nitrogen, the person will then die of a lack of oxygen (or in medical terms, anoxia) which is a painless process.  Nitrogen itself is cheap and abundant, and sealed rooms are not difficult to build.  This is better than other gases that you can use (cyanogen, carbon monoxide etc.) because the nitrogen is completely non-toxic and is harmless if released to the environment.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtaw70</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; nitrogen is completely non-toxic and is harmless if released to the environment.

I think it's worth elaborating that air is 78% nitrogen. It's not just non-toxic and harmless if released - we're already breathing more of it than anything else.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtf7ts</id>
                    <upvotes>26</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I didn't see this before replying, but is there a reason the entire room must be sealed- wouldn't a mask do the trick?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtb11r</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Sure, a mask would do the trick providing the person being executed did not manage to get the mask off or even to spoil the seal of the mask to the face.  Masks are generally dependent upon the mask user, to use them correctly.  I think it is easier to use a sealed room.  But we could certainly research the possibility of a mask, as an alternative.  Perhaps something that is locked in place with a padlock, like the Man In The Iron Mask.  I could see that working.  Even a diving helmet or spacesuit helmet, suitably attached, could work.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtb58a</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Part of me wonders why I feel compelled to continue this conversation, but we could simply strap down their arms (the same way we do for LI since we don't want needles being pulled.) </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtbcxc</id>
                            <replies>
<author>GnosticGnome</author>
<ReplyBody>If you're going to make someone feel restrained and claustrophobic as you're killing them, that's probably at least as unpleasant as the bullet.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtcun2</id>
<replies>
    <author>critically_damped</author>
    <ReplyBody>Yes, locking them in a small room and literally suffocating them is much better in that respect.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtrxw6</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>14</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>Yes, but the face is also mobile.  Face masks fit well if you do not screw around with them.  Still, I think a diving helmet would work nicely.  With arms strapped down.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtbg7f</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>8</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>aardvarkious</author>
                        <ReplyBody>If we are going to kill people, I do think we should give them as much dignity and autonomy as possible throughout the process. To me, being put in a locked room with a comfortable chair and a comfortable cot allowing them to do as they wish is preferable to having their arms strapped or having something strapped to their head.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtbpp2</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>TheThirdBlackGuy</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Unless you want to clean up the occasional bloodied room, strapping wouldn't be a bad idea. People aren't going to always sit quietly waiting to die. Banging their head against every surface, bitting through their tongue, attempting to smash the glass, etc are likely scenarios. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtc562</id>
                            <replies>
<author>aardvarkious</author>
<ReplyBody>And if that is how they choose to go, I think it should be their choice. It isn't like the prison doesn't have the personnel/equpiment/experience to clean up. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtceht</id>
<replies>
    <author>TheThirdBlackGuy</author>
    <ReplyBody>I'm questioning the dignity afforded to an individual when that is what your construct drives them to. Essentially, we'll watch humans self-harm, defecate, weep, etc their last few minutes away because we've locked them in a cage to watch them die. I honestly think reconciling diginity and execution is a lofty ideal. Not much dignified in being killed, despite our best efforts. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtcu1t</id>
    <upvotes>9</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>8</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>That is never going to happen even if it is the least bad option. That is essentially a gas chamber and no matter how logical is, gas chambers are never going to acceptable in America.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtcjpm</id>
                            <replies>
<author>BlackHumor</author>
<ReplyBody>Gas chambers were used in American executions for long after WWII.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chti5by</id>
<replies>
    <author>[deleted]</author>
    <ReplyBody>I wasn't aware of that but still, the antithesis towards anything reminiscent of the Nazis I think is too powerful to overcome. Besides the people who support the death penalty either don't want to be reminded or don't want to remind others that we usually look down upon state sponsored executions.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtq6cj</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>5</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>LifeinParalysis</author>
<ReplyBody>There was a time that most people could fathom gay marriage ever happening in America as well. Gas chambers may have "bad feelings" associated with them, but how pitiful of a society are we that we ignore logic and comfort in favor of a more painful procedure just so we don't step on anyone's toes? If I was to be executed tomorrow, this is how I would want to go. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtqbl1</id>
<replies>
    <author>[deleted]</author>
    <ReplyBody>I don't really see the connection between gay marriage and this. People were opposed to gay marriage for religious and cultural reasons. The opposition to this is for historical reasons.

Just because the country has become more socially progressive doesn't mean that execution methods are going to change, those two things really have nothing in common and no connection.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtqijl</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>That's just stupid.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtf8le</id>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>insaneHoshi</author>
                    <ReplyBody>And apparently the lack of O2 leaves you in a state of Euphoria</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtjrwz</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Quite so.  The brain gradually shuts down, just like getting drunk on alcohol.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chu3vl3</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>I_am_the_Jukebox</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; This has come in previous, similar discussions. If a person is placed in a sealed room that contains an atmosphere of pure nitrogen, the person will then die of a lack of oxygen (or in medical terms, anoxia) which is a painless process

Pure Nitrogen from the get go would actually be pretty bad.  You'd physically breath but have no reaction from it.  You'd be cognizant of it the entire time.  Instead, you'd rather want a normal room, but instead slowly reduce the amount of oxygen in the room.  The person would then become hypoxic, eventually becoming delusional and eventually leading to a loss of consciousness.  Depleting the oxygen and replacing it with nitrogen even more would then eventually lead to death.

Either that, or put them in a centrifuge until they die.  It'd cause the same hypoxic death, but through a different method.  Though that'd be quite a bit more painful.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtmw1i</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>cfuse</author>
                        <ReplyBody>[When humans breathe in pure nitrogen, helium, argon, sulfur hexafluoride, methane, or any other chemically inert gas(es), they exhale carbon dioxide without resupplying oxygen. Inert gases are generally free of odour and taste. As such, the human subject detects no abnormal sensation. This leads to asphyxiation (death from lack of oxygen, not from poison) without the painful and traumatic feeling of suffocation, or from side effects of poisonous interactions.](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inert_gas_asphyxiation)</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtqlyv</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chts8hn</id>
                            <replies>
<author>BenIncognito</author>
<ReplyBody>Sorry, your post has been removed.

&amp;gt; Rule 5. No low effort comments.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtw8hy</id>
<replies>
    <author>OakenBones</author>
    <ReplyBody>that low in the thread? allllrighty then. no hard feelings, just doin your job, i guess</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chu5qkc</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>I_am_the_Jukebox</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I've sucked on pure nitrogen before.  If it happens before you become fully hypoxic then it's fairly clear that something is off.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtw2ji</id>
                            <replies>
<author>cfuse</author>
<ReplyBody>Dose people with inert gas and they've got about 10 seconds of consciousness before they're out. If you zapped them with a bit of N^(2)O during that time they are going to be so out of it that they will be unconscious before they even notice it.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtw4az</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>The medulla oblongata region of the brain, which regulates breathing, does not actually sense oxygen levels, only carbon dioxide levels of the blood.  Thus, if you breathe pure nitrogen, you continue to flush out the excess carbon dioxide and you perceive that your breathing is doing what it is supposed to do.  You do not have a sense of having (as you put it) no reaction.  It feels normal to breathe pure nitrogen, but you will succumb painlessly to anoxia.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chu3uwo</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>ZenDragon</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Why sealed room? You just need a bag over the head and a moderate flow of nitrogen for one minute. I mean you'd normally use a sealed room for toxic gases but the amount of nitrogen you'd need for the bag method would pose no danger to other people even in the same room as long as it's big or ventilated at all.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chts9ae</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>NuclearStudent</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Bagging them to death is likely very traumatic, and looks too much like murder for people to accept. In addition, it would be difficult to get a bag over someone's head without strapping them down, and that also is probably quite traumatic for everyone involved.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtsvwk</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Yes, you could do this very simply with a bag.  I think that since a prisoner being executed would resist having a bag attached, and therefore has to be restrained, the whole process is more dignified if you could just put the prisoner in a sealed room.  But a bag is OK.  It works either way.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chu3shs</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Vovix1</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Isn't suffocation generally quite painful? Or is it the build-up of carbon dioxide that is painful?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chttfco</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>koomapotilas</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It's the build-up of carbon dioxide. Nitrogen asphyxiation is completely painless.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtv08x</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>thefonztm</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Ugh, I'm here because I'm thinking of submitting a similar CMV. I just want to say that the pain related to suffocation can be from lack of oxygen or build up of carbon dioxide.

Most persons would experience pain from CO2 build up well before your body starts freaking out about the lack of oxygen. Some expections arise. Smokers and free-divers have been noted to override/ignore thier bodies warnings about CO2 and experience pain from low O2. I can't recall the mechanisms proper names at the moment.

For example, try this (preferably underwater I guess because it's awkward/hard to do in air). Take a deep breath and hold it. Time how long it takes before you can't take the pain and resume breathing. Now repeat this but exhale slowly. You should last much longer. I'm not sure if the eventual pain you feel is from low O2 or still CO2 build up but I think it illustrates my point well.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckmw8pr</id>
                            <replies>
<author>koomapotilas</author>
<ReplyBody>I guess it's time to pull out the sources. If I show mine, will you show yours?

[Wikipedia](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inert_gas_asphyxiation)

[A BBC documentary](http://youtu.be/dDlDN2nsopE) (the relevant part starts at about 36:30)
</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckn0qaz</id>
<replies>
    <author>thefonztm</author>
    <ReplyBody>http://scuba.about.com/od/Freedivers/a/Freediving-Physiology-Basics.htm

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shallow_water_blackout

Skip to the images and this part.

&amp;gt; Note that the body can actually detect low levels of oxygen but that this is not normal. Persistently elevated levels of carbon dioxide in the blood, hypercapnia (the opposite to hypocapnia), tend to desensitise the body to CO2, in which case the body may come to rely on the oxygen level in the blood to maintain respiratory drive. This is illustrated in the scenario of type II respiratory failure. However, in a normal healthy person there is no subjective awareness of low oxygen levels.

So for most persons Nitrogen Asphyxiation is probably painless, but it is possible for persons to feel their body hit the 'low-oxygen warning.' Heavy smokers and experienced free divers to fall into the category of people that can feel it.

My other issue is that Nitrogen gives my far too much time to contemplate what's happening to me, *as it happens to me.*

Other than that, I do agree with you that Nitrogen is probably the best option that's on the table.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckn17ku</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Anoxia is not painful.  Suffocation in the sense of being prevented from breathing is quite painful.  Drowning is painful.  Carbon dioxide buildup is unpleasant.  But breathing pure nitrogen and succumbing to anoxia is entirely painless, and actually is a bit euphoric.  It's like getting drunk, in the way that the brain gradually shuts down.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chu3r7p</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>16</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                <ReplyBody>Essentially just but a mask over the mouth and nose and introduce a sedative then slowly replace the flow of oxygen with a flow of nitrogen (or other inert gas, but we're used to breathing nitrogen) the body slowly falls asleep and dies. Not sure about cost but nitrogen seems like it would be fairly inexpensive. I'm sure most death chambers already built could be retrofitted. But I don't think we should kill anybody.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtazp3</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Dux_Spaghetti</author>
                    <ReplyBody>What about serial killers? What about fucked up psychos, rapists and terrorists? Should they not die for their crimes?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtb2z9</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                        <ReplyBody>No. Not at the hands of the state when we can just as easily put them into a box for the rest of their lives.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtb8og</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>ryan_m</author>
                            <ReplyBody>The more debates I see about the death penalty, the more I see that it's not really about deterrence, it's about revenge, and that scares the hell out of me.  I barely trust the government to keep my running water clean, much less decide my fate.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtbgta</id>
                            <upvotes>12</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Dux_Spaghetti</author>
                            <ReplyBody>First off, some people just don't deserve to live. If a man killed his entire family in the most brutal way imaginable, would it be better to let him live where he could kill again? Or would it be better to put a bullet/lethal cocktail/overdose of nitrogen in him so that he won't ever kill again?

Second off, IMO, it's more of a mercy to kill someone than force them into a box for 24/7 365 days a year. I couldn't possibly live in a 6x6 cell for the rest of my life without going outside.

Third, the cost is huge. California has the highest prisoner population in the States, and uses a legal loophole to get out of executing people who really deserve to die. Because of this, California has almost gone bankrupt building and expanding prisons to accomodate the population. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtbjvg</id>
                            <replies>
<author>eye_patch_willy</author>
<ReplyBody>For what has to be the hundredth time, the cost of execution far exceeds the cost of lifetime imprisonment. California's prisons are not overcrowded because of their death row inmates. They are overcrowded because of many factors, not the least of which is an archaic three strikes mandatory sentencing law. Killing everyone on their death row next week wont make a dent in the total prison population.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtc14o</id>
<upvotes>13</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>Denny_Craine</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;First off, some people just don't deserve to live.

who has the right or moral authority to decide who deserves to live and who dies?

&amp;gt;If a man killed his entire family in the most brutal way imaginable, would it be better to let him live where he could kill again?

then why not kill anybody who commits a crime, so that they don't have the chance to commit crime again?

&amp;gt;Second off, IMO, it's more of a mercy to kill someone than force them into a box for 24/7 365 days a year. 

that's not for you to decide for other people

&amp;gt;Third, the cost is huge. California has the highest prisoner population in the States, and uses a legal loophole to get out of executing people who really deserve to die. Because of this, California has almost gone bankrupt building and expanding prisons to accomodate the population.

sounds like California is quite simply imprisoning too many people, less crimes should result in imprisonment. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtl8zn</id>
<replies>
    <author>grammartist</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;who has the right or moral authority to decide who deserves to live and who dies?

A jury of our peers.

&amp;gt;then why not kill anybody who commits a crime, so that they don't have the chance to commit crime again?

Because gradience.

&amp;gt;that's not for you to decide for other people

It's for us, as a society, to decide. At times.

&amp;gt;sounds like California is quite simply imprisoning too many people, less crimes should result in imprisonment.

We should just turn off crime.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtqb1c</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>5</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>Execution is vastly more expensive than life imprisonment. Stop with that tired old argument.

You're right, some people do deserve death for their actions. But the state can't be trusted to impose that.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtfcg9</id>
<replies>
    <author>_Thai_Fighter_</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Execution is vastly more expensive than life imprisonment. Stop with that tired old argument.

the point is that execution doesn't have top cost the insane amount it does, it would be far the cheapest option if not for the moronic expensive process used.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chx3nje</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>5</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>Celoth</author>
<ReplyBody>I highly, highly doubt that California's overcrowded prisons are due to a large number of deathrow inmates.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chth5ep</id>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>10</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>QuackersAndMooMoo</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Personally, i don't think we should have the death penalty for 2 reasons:

1.  It's not possible to 100% guarantee you are not killing an innocent person.  'Beyond a reasonable doubt' is not, to me, a high enough standard for killing someone.

2.  We have no idea what the future holds in terms of treatments.  Serial killers are mentally ill.  If you could cure them and put them to use bettering society, wouldn't that be preferable to death?

More #1 than #2 as far as i'm concerned, i only throw out #2 because it's possible.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtbf1q</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Dux_Spaghetti</author>
                            <ReplyBody>If you had the evidence, physical and genetic,   and they all point to the same person, wouldn't you say he's guilty? 

Also, there are some things we really can't fix. Mental issues, especially with serial killers, are hard to fix without going to shit like lobotomies or other unethical treatments.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtbn0s</id>
                            <replies>
<author>QuackersAndMooMoo</author>
<ReplyBody>How do you think they convict people now?  And they still execute innocent people.

And i agree its almost impossible to treat that level of mental illness today, but in 20 years it may not be.  

I'd rather not execute someone who is either innocent or potentially treatable in their lifetime than have a government that thinks it's ok to kill people.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtbuad</id>
<replies>
    <author>Adricko92</author>
    <ReplyBody>What if the suspect confesses to his crime?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtv36d</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>4</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>eye_patch_willy</author>
<ReplyBody>Genetic evidence?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtc3uk</id>
<replies>
    <author>Dux_Spaghetti</author>
    <ReplyBody>I mean DNA evidence.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtcdlc</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>_Thai_Fighter_</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Personally, i don't think we should have the death penalty for 2 reasons:

&amp;gt;1.  It's not possible to 100% guarantee you are not killing an innocent person.  'Beyond a reasonable doubt' is not, to me, a high enough standard for killing someone.

Of course it is, for example the soldier beheading in a London street in broad daylight, or the many that are tapped and put online, I am for the death penalty, but only in no doubt cases.

</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chx3q5j</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>_Thai_Fighter_</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Personally, i don't think we should have the death penalty for 2 reasons:

&amp;gt;1.  It's not possible to 100% guarantee you are not killing an innocent person.  'Beyond a reasonable doubt' is not, to me, a high enough standard for killing someone.

Of course it is, for example the soldier beheading in a London street in broad daylight, or the many that are taped and put online, I am for the death penalty, but only in zero doubt cases.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chx3q5z</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>_Thai_Fighter_</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Personally, i don't think we should have the death penalty for 2 reasons:

&amp;gt;1.  It's not possible to 100% guarantee you are not killing an innocent person.  'Beyond a reasonable doubt' is not, to me, a high enough standard for killing someone.

Of course it is, for example the soldier beheading in a London street in broad daylight, or the many that are tapped and put online, I am for the death penalty, but only in no doubt cases.

</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chx3q70</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>8</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>A shotgun blast to the brainstem IS instant and painless.  Maybe not the cleanest death but who cares?  The dignity of a convicted murderer/rapist doesn't matter.  </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chthv48</id>
            <replies>
                <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                <ReplyBody>Sure it does. Plus, with all the efficiencies we see in modern governments combined with the wisdom of 24 people not smart enough to escape jury duty is amazing we are on with issuing this type of punishment. Also why do you reject the idea that life imprisonment is a lesser punishment than death? Is certainly easier on the tax payer. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtiek1</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Iseverynametakenhere</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think it's a lot les about their dignity than the rest of us. You don't judge a society by how they treat their elite, you judge them on how they treat their worst.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chu1f6u</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>baabaa_blacksheep</author>
            <ReplyBody>I posted [this video](http://youtu.be/R18yDjc2lKE) in /r/morbidreality quite a while ago.

It basically tries to find a humane way to execute someone. Nitrogen asphyxiation looks like the 'best method'.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chu4s3m</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>50</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>rocqua</author>
        <ReplyBody>I agree that the current method is wholly stupid. However, the idea behind it I can support (for as far as I support capital punishment).

It is supposed to be a dignified method. This because of x things:

**Viscerality**: The only visceral harm done by injection is the puncturing of the skin. The foresight of this happening to a person in and of itself is pretty bearable. As such, the wait should be less torturous.

**Dignity**: Death by injection does not mutilate the corpse. This is important for two reasons. The first is people left behind. A man sentenced to death can still have people who love him. It is important to them to be able to pay their respects, to honor the person he once was. With his head mutilated, this may get harder, there is no legal basis for punishing these people.

Secondly, their is the person himself. Should he care at all about how his body remains in this world it would, to me, constitute cruel and unusual punishment. He would know, going into his final moments, that his corpse will end up mutilated. To me, that is among the cruelest things you could do to a person sentenced to death. It is an expression of wishing to deny that person his dignity even in death.

That being said, we do need to get rid of this stupid injection stuff. The nitrogen chamber mention elsewhere seems like a very decent option.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtga72</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>Honest question here; Would you agree that a person on death row forfeits their right to be treated with dignity when they commit whatever act has put them on death row? </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chts8sh</id>
            <replies>
                <author>rocqua</author>
                <ReplyBody>No, no, no.

So, in summary, not really. Dignity is a basic human right. Someone might do something so horrible as to no longer deserve to live, but he should not lose all of his dignity for it. To take his dignity would be savagery pure and simple.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtun2w</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>sauron2709</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I'll ask an honest question too. Do you rank the right to dignity higher than the right to live? I mean, you're taking away their right to live and okay with it, but you still insist that  taking away their dignity is savagery?

Also, to continue down the slippery slope, would you say that someone who had to live without any dignity whatsoever (say a kidnapped woman kept in a dungeon who is tortured and raped at the whims of her kidnapper, to give an extreme example) would be better off dead?

I'm not trying to be offensive, sorry if I come across like that. I'm just trying to understand your views.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtzem7</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>rocqua</author>
                        <ReplyBody>An issue here is the fact that I'm essentially opposed to capital punishment.

I think someones right to life probably ranks just above someones right to dignity. Taking the kidnapped women, and whether she'd be better of dead, I do not know. She might be. Dignity is important.

I feel that capital punishment is not (should not be) an act of anger. It is not done to hurt or harm the sentenced. It is done because society cannot bear to have this person. So it is not him doing something so bad he forfeits his right to life. It is society being put in such a bad position that it has to ignore his right to life. That however, does not mean society gets to ignore his right to dignity.

Taking the man's dignity is to me the essence of cruel and unusual punishment. I guess that's why cruel and unusual punishment is not allowed by law.

Perhaps an interseting fact is that I myself would much rather die by gunshot (shotgun actually) to the head than lethal injection or electrocution. That is preconditioned on my family being okay with it though.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chu016n</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>dyslexda</author>
                <ReplyBody>Absolutely, unequivocally, no. A certain level of human dignity is required, no matter your background. Past actions do not affect your natural rights now.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtytow</id>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>9</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>18</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>captintucker</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think that the judge that passes the sentence should be the one to pull the trigger. No automation, no walls to hide behind. They look the man in the eyes, hear his last words, and put him out of this world. Execution should ALWAYS weigh heavy on people's minds. It's not something you sugarcoat or pretend that the needle did the killing. Its not something you pass off to someone who doesn't even know or care about the cries the man committed. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtbwcq</id>
        <upvotes>8</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>TotalShadow</author>
        <ReplyBody>I think "painless" really means "painless for people to watch." I would rather have it over without the ceremony of getting shaved and prepped for electrocution or having to sit and wait 10 minutes in a room as a lethal dosage of some drug is applied. That would be horrific. Personally, the quickest way possible is the best for me. I'd be okay with them dropping a 2 ton weight onto my head without warning me. That's over is a nano second (But it makes for a lot of clean up and that's more important than a painless death). I think the most humane way would be a single shell of .000 buckshot going through the back of the skull. It's fast and effective and leaves no room for screwups. Bullets can fail. There are a lot of people who have been shot by bullets and lived. Not a lot of people who took a shotgun at close range to the head who were around for more than an instant after the trigger was pulled.     
The horror of the wait, for me, is like a roller coaster. Waiting in line is worse than the actual roller coaster. You watch the ride and hear people screaming and all you're thinking about is how scary it will be. No line? Get right on and it's not that bad. 2 hour build up? It's terrifying. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtf54i</id>
        <replies>
            <author>NevadaCynic</author>
            <ReplyBody>This. Lethal injection is about the audience, not the condemned. If we were being merciful to the condemned man instead of the audience, lethal injection would be quite far down on the list of methods of execution.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chti7yk</id>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>9</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BlueApple4</author>
        <ReplyBody>First off you have similar issues with failure rate. 

Second many families of victims want to see the execution, which a gun execution would be much more traumatic. Also I think they would have to have someone observe it, even if you didn't pull the trigger to make sure their is no foul play. 

Third you would also have to spend a lot of money on clean up. And the cleanup could potentially be traumatizing. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtbfb4</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Bullroarer86</author>
            <ReplyBody>The firing squad is the only sanctioned execution I can find with no insanely painful mess ups.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtm6tv</id>
            <replies>
                <author>BlueApple4</author>
                <ReplyBody>If you have a firing squad then they aren't exactly shooting you in the brainstem, thereby nullifying that argument of yours. Being shot with several bullets at once may not instantly kill you, and is definatly painful.

And how would you not have clean up via firing squad. Lots of blood, brains and guts to clean up.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtnkru</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Bullroarer86</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You haven't researched death by firing squad have you? They use multiple shooters but only one (usually) actual round. The rest are blanks so that nobody knows who did the killing

As to your other points high caliber rounds hit with such velocity that the target is usually knocked out, and do so much damage that they die immediately.

Now for shooting in the back or the head, what could go wrong? Find me one horror story from a sanctioned gun death.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtpfqt</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>denvek</author>
                        <ReplyBody>
&amp;gt;You haven't researched death by firing squad have you? They use multiple shooters but only one (usually) actual round. The rest are blanks so that nobody knows who did the killing

I believe it's the other way round. Only one is a  blank, no one knows who. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtqnq5</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>And really, I doubt that this is actually done. You would expect the men firing the guns to have experience with the rifles they are using. Which means they would know what sort of recoil to expect from firing a round from that rifle. A blank would have significantly less recoil (enough that one would be able to tell the difference).</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtue8q</id>
                            <replies>
<author>denvek</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;In more recent times, such as in the execution of Ronnie Lee Gardner in the American state of Utah in the United States in 2010, a rifleman may be given a "dummy" cartridge containing wax instead of a bullet, which provides a more realistic recoil.

[source](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Execution_by_firing_squad)</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtwixx</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>BlueApple4</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I don't think the logistics of work with a firing squad for shooting someone is such a small area as the brain stem. It's too many people shooting a small target. You could hit them in the brain and not kill them right away(not the hindbrain which controls breathing in such), or you could nick an artery so they bleed out, or you could sever the spinal cord leading to paralyisis. None of these are a "kind" way to die. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>chtxi8p</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Bullroarer86</author>
                            <ReplyBody>You are way under estimating the damage of a round at close range. The current firing squad method to my knowledge doesn't have any botched attempts and its firing at a distance into the heart. How can making the shot easier make it harder?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>chtzd0w</id>
                            <replies>
<author>BlueApple4</author>
<ReplyBody>Sorry OP was making the argument that a shot to the brain stem is the most humane way of killing someone, to which a firing range would logistically not work. 

I still think a firing squad is awfully messy to clean up, and would be quite expensive. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>chtzke3</id>
<replies>
    <author>Bullroarer86</author>
    <ReplyBody>Expensive? How? Op says one guy and  bullet. The squad is twelve guys and a bullet. Its much, much cheaper than lethal injection. As far as mess damage to the heart prevents it from beating which means no sprays or spurts.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>chtzpl9</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>have you looked at the failure rate with that method in animal killing?

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cht9qss</id>
        <replies>
            <author>RibsNGibs</author>
            <ReplyBody>I bet you could get an automated gun system to work flawlessly if you were willing to spend ~$1.3k per execution (and maybe use a bigger bullet than 9mm).</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtahcd</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Clausewitz1996</author>
            <ReplyBody>No. Could you provide some information?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtao2z</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1852607/

It's not 100% on that.

</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtb3zp</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BenIncognito</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Given that using a bullet to the back of the skull would neutralize the brain stem, the inmate would feel no pain. 

Every time? Every inmate? Guaranteed?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cht9zcu</id>
        <replies>
            <author>rimsh</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't think it's the cleanest way, or even the best way, but just as a counter argument, I'm pretty sure if we used a shotgun slug (rather than a single bullet as OP suggests) I think it would work EVERY TIME. Point blank range, back of the head. That person is a goner.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtakez</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Wehavecrashed</author>
                <ReplyBody>With a huge fucking hole in the back of his skull. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtmknu</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Clausewitz1996</author>
            <ReplyBody>No, of course not. There are always outliers. However, I'm willing to bet the failure rate is nill.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtaolk</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I imagine one of the biggest arguments against your method is the cleanup. No bodily fluids are released during lethal injection. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtbj6g</id>
        <replies>
            <author>GnosticGnome</author>
            <ReplyBody>Other than blood, urine, feces, vomit, and spit?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtcwfg</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chttaeu</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>BenIncognito</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Sorry, your post has been removed.

&amp;gt; Rule 5. No low effort comments.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtw1mr</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>10</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ultimate_zigzag</author>
        <ReplyBody>In my opinion, the death penalty is serious enough that it is not necessarily a bad thing for it to remain costly and inconvenient for those who carry it out. It is the lesser evil that it not be so efficient instead of being easy. These are people's lives being ended, and it has been shown that a significant percentage of people executed and people scheduled to be executed are innocent. So an efficient execution system is not necessarily desirable here.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtvhm6</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>telentis</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why not tie them to a chair, and put a mask on them that is connected to a CO2 tank? Dirt cheap, no pain, no mess.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtbdi2</id>
        <replies>
            <author>MooseV2</author>
            <ReplyBody>Carbon dioxide is not painless. The pain from suffocation is caused when too much CO2 builds up in your body. Try holding your breath for as long as you can. That's how it would feel like to die by CO2.

However, there are gases that we can use such as Helium or Nitrogen that would not cause pain.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtdk0t</id>
            <replies>
                <author>rocqua</author>
                <ReplyBody>To illustrate what /u/MooseV2 said, take an almost empty soda bottle, shake it, and suck out the air.

The sensation you feel is that of CO2 in the lungs. (To my knowledge, this is not dangerous.)</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtgc5i</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>cfuse</author>
            <ReplyBody>Even at non-lethal levels, CO^(2) causes an uncontrollable panic reaction in humans.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtqofp</id>
            <replies>
                <author>telentis</author>
                <ReplyBody>Woah, really? How is that possible? I mean, you can't even smell the gas</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtsm41</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>cfuse</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Your brainstem registers CO^(2) levels in your blood. This is not in any way a conscious mechanism - you'll freak out and you'll probably have no idea why.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtt95d</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Steppdeckenwolf</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The breathing reflex is triggered by CO2 levels in the blood. Imagine that urge to breathe intensifying with every breath. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtv3jo</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>thiazzi1</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The feeling of panic and pain you get when you hold your breath for too long is caused by your brain detecting high CO2 levels...</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>chtwfx1</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>It could work with other gas like nitrogen and helium.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chuoxde</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I agree 100% OP.  Buckshot to the brain stem is instant and painless.  I feel like giving a convicted rapist/murderer euthanasia drugs is ridiculous.  Many people in America seek euthanasia drugs but can't find them because they're illegal because of the Christian-ethos mindset in this country.  It's insane that a terminally ill person can't get Nembutal(The premier euthanasia drug) but violent rapist/murderers get it.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chthl90</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>naliao</author>
        <ReplyBody>I feel like its the person who has to pull the trigger whos gonna feel bad. This is the actual reason hitler made gas chambers, the mass shooters were going crazy with guilt and etc. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtxnuf</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>agitatedelf</author>
        <ReplyBody>Honestly I think what makes it different is that that disfigures the inmate. There are people who may want to go to that burial for various reasons, but nobody wants to see anyone's brains spilled all over. Also press are at executions and the average person will view that execution as more horrific simply because it's messy. I don't think it's the painless part that people care about so much as the gruesome factor</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chu3mje</id>
        <replies>
            <author>RockFourFour</author>
            <ReplyBody>A captive bolt system like what is used on cattle would work.  A pop to the back of the head, and disfigurement wouldn't be an issue.  It also wouldn't use bullets.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chu5bee</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MooseV2</author>
        <ReplyBody>There are (at least) three viewpoints that you should consider:

* The inmate's
* The executioners
* The general public

For each of those, compare what they think of the various types of capital punishment: (in your comparison) execution by firearm, and execution by lethal injection.

* Bullets, by design, are made to penetrate and cause harm to their target. It doesn't matter if that's a living being or a inanimate object. The bullet's main purpose is to cause damage to the target.

* Bullets are notorious for being incredibly harmful and nonlethal. The number of people who end up in agonizing pain from being shot outweighs the number of people who are killed instantly.

* The firing of a bullet is loud and verbose, causing emotions and reactions (adrenaline, fight or flight, etc).

* Bullet wounds are messy, as they cause internal damage as well as blood/flesh loss.

* Guns have been used in acts of terrorism, violence, and other unpleasant situations

In the eyes of the inmate, being shot with a bullet would be an incredibly scary experience. Knowledge and experience will cause most people to fear a firearm, as the majority of firearm incidences are negative experiences (as mentioned above).

In the eyes of the executioner, using a firearm is a very horrific experience. Training and conditioning can very much limit those emotions, but guns will always be traumatic for all the additional side effects they have (see above).

In the eyes of the public, firearms are inhumane and terrifying (see above). We have been taught to fear guns, and taught that guns are used for bad situations. If we let guns propagate into our justice system, the result will be fear and lack of trust in the system.

On the other hand, lethal injections are:

* Created to be humane.
* Safe and without pain (if done correctly).
* Trusted and administered by medical professionals.
* Silent and can be administered calmly
* Can be witnessed without causing PTSD or other trauma
* Used in many moral situations where ethics are extremely important, such as euthanasia in patients (and pets) with terminal illnesses or agonizing pain.

By definition, they have a much warmer reputation with everyone. The majority of people would feel safer knowing that the method used to kill is the same one trusted by humanity groups for euthanasia.


In terms of money, I wouldn't worry about it too much. $1300 may sound like a lot to *you*, but that's pennies to the government. If anything, consider that a higher price means more consideration would prelude capital punishment. The last thing we want is for the justice system to take capital punishment for granted, escalating sentences to death when there is no need for it.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtdfod</id>
        <replies>
            <author>sven_kirk</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; In the eyes of the inmate, being shot with a bullet would be an incredibly scary experience.

Ask how the victim felt. Did they enjoy being locked in a car trunk? Look  forward to be strangled by a telephone cord. Enjoyed being stabbed repeatedly and left for dead? That is a scary experience.

Here is an old [CNN](http://www.cnn.com/2010/CRIME/06/09/utah.firing.squad/) article on an interview on one of a five person crew.

"I haven't lost three seconds of sleep over it," he says. "... it's true justice."</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>chtmdif</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Jetlagofficial</author>
                <ReplyBody>I agree that I will never lose sleep over a man like John Taylor, but do the lack of ethics in a chemically imbalanced man really call for an abandonment of morals?  No matter how we kill the convicted, the victim will remain dead.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chto1g4</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>bracs278</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Ask how the victim felt. Did they enjoy being locked in a car trunk? Look forward to be strangled by a telephone cord. 

Yes, let's appeal to emotion, that always ends well. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtrryw</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>rainwood</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Ask how the victim felt.

That's vengeance. Making someone suffer like the suffering they've caused is not justice.

Think of it this way. Just for a second:

Imagine, I don't care about who you are. At all. I don't care what you do for a job. I don't care if you drive a car, or where your live, or what you look like. Or what your hardships are.

I don't care if you were to lose everything you had tomorrow, have your life spiral out of control, find yourself drugged up, desperate, and dangerous somewhere. 

I wouldn't care if you were to break into my house, murder my family, and take all their stuff. If the next day I found out you had done those things and were captured by the police, I would be the first person before the judge to ask you NOT be sentenced to death.

It's barbaric. In a hypothetical situation where 4 people have died, remitting a 5th skeleton to the Earth does not improve the situation.

We should not put people in prison to "punish" them; that's a petty and archaic sense of what the concept means. We should also not put them there with any hope of rehabilitation.

People should be put in prison because they are a danger to society. Period.

We all have rights and responsibilities to each other. That's what our society is based on. Mutual, communal, dependence. People farm for me so I can learn to make the world a better place for us all. If I had to grow my own food, I wouldn't have time to do what I needed. If I had to care for the health of myself and know what a doctor needs to know, I wouldn't be capable.

No man is an island and we depend on each other. When we can't depend on someone; when someone has proven they are working for the detriment of the greater good, you simply remove them from it.

If someone wants to shit in the apple pie, they get to live in the house where nobody ever bakes anything. If you can't play nicely with the others, you go to time out. That should be prison.

If you take a life, that does not give anyone else the right to take yours.

The perspective of the prisoner is not only important to the discussion, it's the entire fucking part. I'm (clearly) anti-death penalty, so I won't stand here and defend something I think should be abolished.

I would ask you, however, to remember that 4% of the people we executed were innocent people.

Let that sink in for a moment.

We, collectively, together as a society, paid taxes to ensure that we could murder these innocent people. Make no mistake. It's not a clerical fucking error when you take someone's life even though they were innocent of the charges.

It's codified vigilantism, and it's gotten innocent people murdered. 

So when you denigrate the experience of the victim, realize that one day you might be an innocent person on death row, guilty of a crime you didn't commit, and a guy with a shotgun is walking towards you.

Do you think you'd care how the prisoner felt then?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtth0i</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>bgh251f2</author>
                <ReplyBody>You know that is not really relevant to the whole question. We are talking about a humane way to do an execution not a way to satisfy a lust for blood.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>chtyjto</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>rainwood</author>
        <ReplyBody>I posted this below in a reply to someone else's shitty comment, but I'm going to re-post it verbatim here in the hopes you see it and it does something to change your mind.

===

&amp;gt; Ask how the victim felt.

That's vengeance. Making someone suffer like the suffering they've caused is not justice.

Think of it this way. Just for a second:

Imagine, I don't care about who you are. At all. I don't care what you do for a job. I don't care if you drive a car, or where your live, or what you look like. Or what your hardships are.

I don't care if you were to lose everything you had tomorrow, have your life spiral out of control, find yourself drugged up, desperate, and dangerous somewhere. 

I wouldn't care if you were to break into my house, murder my family, and take all their stuff. If the next day I found out you had done those things and were captured by the police, I would be the first person before the judge to ask you NOT be sentenced to death.

It's barbaric. In a hypothetical situation where 4 people have died, remitting a 5th skeleton to the Earth does not improve the situation.

We should not put people in prison to "punish" them; that's a petty and archaic sense of what the concept means. We should also not put them there with any hope of rehabilitation.

People should be put in prison because they are a danger to society. Period.

We all have rights and responsibilities to each other. That's what our society is based on. Mutual, communal, dependence. People farm for me so I can learn to make the world a better place for us all. If I had to grow my own food, I wouldn't have time to do what I needed. If I had to care for the health of myself and know what a doctor needs to know, I wouldn't be capable.

No man is an island and we depend on each other. When we can't depend on someone; when someone has proven they are working for the detriment of the greater good, you simply remove them from it.

If someone wants to shit in the apple pie, they get to live in the house where nobody ever bakes anything. If you can't play nicely with the others, you go to time out. That should be prison.

If you take a life, that does not give anyone else the right to take yours.

The perspective of the prisoner is not only important to the discussion, it's the entire fucking part. I'm (clearly) anti-death penalty, so I won't stand here and defend something I think should be abolished.

I would ask you, however, to remember that 4% of the people we executed were innocent people.

Let that sink in for a moment.

We, collectively, together as a society, paid taxes to ensure that we could murder these innocent people. Make no mistake. It's not a clerical fucking error when you take someone's life even though they were innocent of the charges.

It's codified vigilantism, and it's gotten innocent people murdered. 

So when you denigrate the experience of the victim, realize that one day you might be an innocent person on death row, guilty of a crime you didn't commit, and a guy with a shotgun is walking towards you.

Do you think you'd care how the prisoner felt then?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>chtthbu</id>
        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
