<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>cacheflow</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;  heard before (no sources, sorry, but I'm sure someone can dig it up) that lethal injections cost more than keeping someone for life in prison (this may be completely incorrect, but does not invalidate the following argument

This is completely incorrect.  The 'cost' of the death penalty comes from things like mandatory appeals and all the extra legal steps needed before we an execution can take place.  It's not the actual cost of the drugs.

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1udmy3</id>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;this may be completely incorrect, but does not invalidate the following argument

Even if the drugs were not very pricey, they are still more expensive than ammunition</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1uduxr</id>
            <replies>
                <author>cacheflow</author>
                <ReplyBody>The drugs are more humane, so the slight increase in cost is worth it. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1udzio</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>b00st3d</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Drugs are as humane as a correct gunshot to the head is.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1ug44c</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Stokkolm</author>
                        <ReplyBody>It's impossible to have your view changed if you believe this. Someone who makes that claim has to be very insensitive to violence.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1uoony</id>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ThatBelligerentSloth</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Drugs are as humane as a correct gunshot to the head is.

Correct being the operative word. If you miss the person is caused immense suffering. People make mistakes and the process of lethal injection is in part designed to avoid that. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1uh9pm</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>b00st3d</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Well, I was assuming the executioner would either be touching the persons head with the barrel or maybe a foot or two away, but there's no missing that.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1uhbdp</id>
                            <replies>
<author>ThatBelligerentSloth</author>
<ReplyBody>You should probably google gunshot wounds to the face. People have missed at point blank range. On others and themselves. There are a whole host of physical and psychological factors which would increase the chance of missing, here. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uhfno</id>
<replies>
    <author>b00st3d</author>
    <ReplyBody>Point blank is different than touching, however. And if it is touching, if that is considered point blank by some definitions, there is no way you can miss, especially if it's your job.

Yes, many people may have some other factors that may effect you, but if you're an EXECUTIONER and you did this as a job, I'd say its virtually impossible to miss a shot like that.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1uhk2j</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Sadsharks</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Not necessarily.  For example, the body is far less damaged by drugs (a small puncture compared to a potentially destroyed, unrecognizable head), which could easily cause concerns for the family of the deceased when it comes to funerals and so forth.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1uh9qj</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>b00st3d</author>
                            <ReplyBody>It's the criminal's fault for committing the crime. If he didn't want his family to see his messed up head (or lack thereof) , then he wouldn't have done the crime. Even if it made it to the funeral stage, I'm sure the event would be closed-casket. The family retains the full independence to just, you know, not look.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1uhe0y</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Sadsharks</author>
<ReplyBody>People don't forfeit all their rights when they commit crimes, unless you live in an insane Orwellian dystopia.  The state cannot simply do whatever they please with a person simply because the person is guilty.  Furthermore you're also making the absurd assumption that everyone who is executed is truly guilty.

My point was about the family, not about the criminal, anyway.  His concerns are irrelevant.  The family is not guilty and does not deserve to bear the burden for someone else's crimes.

&amp;gt;Even if it made it to the funeral stage, I'm sure the event would be closed-casket.

My point is that it shouldn't be, if they don't want it to be.

&amp;gt;The family retains the full independence to just, you know, not look.

And the justice system retains independence to just, you know, not use an unnecessarily brutal and disfiguring method of execution, when they have a reasonably humane one already.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uhjfm</id>
<replies>
    <author>b00st3d</author>
    <ReplyBody>The basis of my argument was that the person was guilty beyond a reasonable doubt, which is why I listed it in the bullet points above. I am not arguing over the ethics of even issuing a capital punishment, as I listed in the bullet points above. I am simply arguing over the method used once capital punishment is issued.

&amp;gt;The state cannot simply do whatever they please with a person simply because the person is guilty.

If the state (or the court rather) has issued capital punishment, then the criminal will die. As long as it is humane, they are open options. I am arguing that the best option would be gunshot to the head, as it is the most efficient and cheap.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1uhmrb</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>B0pp0</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Do it to the heart then. At least their brains can be studied. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1x71vn</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>YabuSama2k</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The drugs are more humane

Not lately.  Have you seen the stories and videos of the botched executions?  Also, they can destroy organs such that they cannot be donated.  </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1vbcv9</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>____Matt____</author>
        <ReplyBody>The main cost of execution is housing inmates on death row (more expensive than general population), as well as the exhaustive appeals process for which inmates sentenced to be executed are entitled (and since it's so exhaustive, that's why they often spend a very long time on death row). The actual cost of execution is negligible, and as such, changing the method of execution to one that is cheaper is unlikely to make any significant impact on the total cost of the death penalty. Even if it cost $50,000 to execute someone, which could be saved via your method, do you really think that's going to matter when the approximate cost of a year on death row is ~$90,000 more than for someone sentenced to life (http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/costs-death-penalty -- "The additional cost of confining an inmate to death row, as compared to the maximum security prisons where those sentenced to life without possibility of parole ordinarily serve their sentences, is $90,000 per year per inmate.")? No; since given that number, spending a mere 15 years on death row would be a cost of 1.35 million above and beyond what would have been spent if the sentence were life without parole. And that's not including the time spent by courts and district attorney employees in dealing with appeals, which are more exhaustive than they are even for life without parole.

The reason that lethal injections are often preferred is because they are less distressing for those witnessing the execution, very reliable when done correctly, and also because they're much more humane than many other methods.

Witnessing someone shot in the head at close range is likely going to be distressing to witnesses. It is not necessarily immediately fatal. And while likely being more humane than something like the electric chair, is definitely much less humane than a lethal injection.

Given how incredibly inefficient in both cost and time the death penalty is, it seems quite odd that you'd want to make the most efficient part even more efficient, at the cost of greater distress to witnesses, greater distress to the executioner, and less compassion for the inmate to be executed.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1uccsp</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Grunt08</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The reason that lethal injections are often preferred is because they are less distressing for those witnessing the execution,

If killing someone in cold blood affects someone that way, maybe they shouldn't do it.  You killed him either way, and for the exact same reason.  You shouldn't feel better because you did it clinically.

&amp;gt;Witnessing someone shot in the head at close range is likely going to be distressing to witnesses.

Good.  Their purpose is to witness and attest to the death.  It shouldn't be sugarcoated for them.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1udfjq</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>Death row will cost the same regardless. Although the price difference in changing execution methods may not be large enough to match up to the cost of housing people in death row, there is STILL a savings. Which means that it is both more efficient and cheaper.

&amp;gt;The reason that lethal injections are often preferred is because they are less distressing for those witnessing the execution, very reliable when done correctly, and also because they're much more humane than many other methods.

Well, if you don't want to watch it, don't watch it. Simple as that.

I'm sure a gunshot to the head (provided the correct caliber and bullet were used) is very reliable, and if it's near instant then it is humane.

&amp;gt;Witnessing someone shot in the head at close range is likely going to be distressing to witnesses. It is not necessarily immediately fatal. And while likely being more humane than something like the electric chair, is definitely much less humane than a lethal injection.

As I've said, don't look and use the correct gun and bullet.

&amp;gt;Given how incredibly inefficient in both cost and time the death penalty is, it seems quite odd that you'd want to make the most efficient part even more efficient, at the cost of greater distress to witnesses, greater distress to the executioner, and less compassion for the inmate to be executed.

You can never be too efficient, don't witness if you don't want to see it, find the right executioner, and compassion has no place in law.

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ucnv4</id>
            <replies>
                <author>parentheticalobject</author>
                <ReplyBody>But why do you feel it is wrong to say "We prefer to do executions this way even if it is a tiny bit less efficient than doing them another way, even though it offers no real benefit" and feel perfectly alright with saying "We prefer to execute people, even though it is massively less efficient than not doing so, even though it offers no real benefit"?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1uf1xx</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>b00st3d</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The benefit is being cheaper.

And I am not arguing for the ethics or morals behind killing or not killing people in the name of the law, purely pointing out my view that **AFTER** capital punishment has already been decided, what method best to use.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1ugchn</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>parentheticalobject</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I'm trying to draw a parallel between the two. 

Lethal injection doesn't really make much of a difference to anything, but it's a little more comfortable for some people that we use it, so we justify the minor expense.

The death penalty doesn't really make any positive difference, but some people prefer that we do it so we justify the huge expense.

If we're OK with spending a lot extra because some people just want it that way, why aren't you OK with spending a little extra because some people just want it that way?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1ugzyb</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>b00st3d</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I apologize if I'm not getting something, but I don't follow.

* Person is convicted of bad crime, person is sentenced death penalty.

* Person is going to die anyways, so might as well save money.

That's how I see it, where is the flaw?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1uh3a9</id>
                            <replies>
<author>parentheticalobject</author>
<ReplyBody>* People feel a little bit better if we use lethal injection instead of gunshots.

Do you think that, on principle, it isn't worth spending a little bit of extra money to make people feel a little bit better about something that doesn't really matter?

Let me ask you to clarify something, which of these two statements would you agree with more:

A: if the assumption that the death penalty has no real benefit is true, it wouldn't matter to my argument.

B: whether the death penalty has any benefit matters somewhat for the purpose of this argument.

If B is true, then while you aren't here to debate the rightness or wrongness of the death penalty, it is still relevant to your argument, so we should be able to talk about that.

If A is true, then it seems we can justify the death penalty on grounds that it gives people a sense of justice by itself. What I'm primarily getting at is that *this* is the same kind of reasoning by which people decide to use lethal injection instead of bullets. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uhimw</id>
<replies>
    <author>b00st3d</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Do you think that, on principle, it isn't worth spending a little bit of extra money to make people feel a little bit better about something that doesn't really matter?

Yes, it is not worth spending greater money.

I would agree with B more, but do not understand your analysis at the bottom. Yes, death penalty gives people a sense of justice (or to me at least). I do not understand how that justifies lethal injection over bullets.

Or am I stupid and missing something again? :(</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1uhqap</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Barology</author>
        <ReplyBody>The possibility for failure would be unacceptably high. People can survive gunshots to the head. If someone didn't die with the first shot they would be in unimaginable agony. Obviously that would be illegally cruel.

It would be horribly traumatizing to the executioner. They would relive the grisly scene for the rest of their life. 

One of the reasons for firing squads is to make it unclear who actually killed the prisoner. You can hope that you might have fired a blank. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1ucb1h</id>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The possibility for failure would be unacceptably high. People can survive gunshots to the head.

Use a large caliber, 7.62 hollow-point if you have to be sure. And if you REALLY wanted to be sure, just move up to even larger calibers. The stories you hear about people surviving headshot wounds are of smaller caliber and non-hollow point bullets. No one survives a .50 caliber shot.

&amp;gt;It would be horribly traumatizing to the executioner. They would relive the grisly scene for the rest of their life.

Aren't there already executioners that do lethal injections? They killed someone anyways. If they really didn't want to see it, put a bag over the person's head so there isn't as much sploosh. If that's not enough, just hire someone that will do it. There are probably some people who would do that for a living.

&amp;gt;One of the reasons for firing squads is to make it unclear who actually killed the prisoner. You can hope that you might have fired a blank.

As stated earlier, just find someone willing. Plenty of people are looking for a job.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ucis6</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Barology</author>
                <ReplyBody>I feel like you're downplaying the trauma of shooting another person in the head. That is not something a person will just forget. A bag would do little to alleviate it because the shooter or a doctor would need to pull off the bag and verify the death. Obviously it would be different than pulling the plunger on a needle. Why burden an innocent with that lifelong trauma?

Is your suggestion that prisoners be used for target practice a serious one?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1ucqgn</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>b00st3d</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Is your suggestion that prisoners be used for target practice a serious one?

No

&amp;gt;I feel like you're downplaying the trauma of shooting another person in the head. That is not something a person will just forget. A bag would do little to alleviate it because the shooter or a doctor would need to pull off the bag and verify the death. Obviously it would be different than pulling the plunger on a needle. Why burden an innocent with that lifelong trauma?

There is no doubting that there are people who will shoot someone in the head and witness all of it and have no issues (that are mentally stable, not including sociopaths etc.) Yes, for a lot of people, and probably the vast majority, blowing off someones head would be traumatizing and terrible. I do not doubt that some will be terrified for the rest of their life. All you have to do is find the right person, who wouldn't bat an eye.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1ucunw</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ThatBelligerentSloth</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Is your suggestion that prisoners be used for target practice a serious one?

&amp;gt;No

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;I feel like you're downplaying the trauma of shooting another person in the head. That is not something a person will just forget. A bag would do little to alleviate it because the shooter or a doctor would need to pull off the bag and verify the death. Obviously it would be different than pulling the plunger on a needle. Why burden an innocent with that lifelong trauma?

&amp;gt;There is no doubting that there are people who will shoot someone in the head and witness all of it and have no issues (that are mentally stable, not including sociopaths etc.) Yes, for a lot of people, and probably the vast majority, blowing off someones head would be traumatizing and terrible. I do not doubt that some will be terrified for the rest of their life. All you have to do is find the right person, who wouldn't bat an eye.

Mary people initially don't believe that they will experience PTSD after having killed someone and they go through conditioning to view the other as an enemy. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1uhclv</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>b00st3d</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Well, create a better interview process. Maybe have past experience or something. And if they do sign up for the job, but realize they can't do it, it's no one's fault but their own. Someone else more qualified will take the job.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1uhfig</id>
                            <replies>
<author>ThatBelligerentSloth</author>
<ReplyBody>You cannot sign a contract which signs away your capacity let someone murder you. The reason for this is that you cannot sign away your rights legally because it opens the door for abuse. Similarly, creating a set of circumstances in which one is subjected to unnecessary psychological harm opens the door up to abuse.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uhp4w</id>
<replies>
    <author>b00st3d</author>
    <ReplyBody>I am starting to misunderstand your argument. Please clarify?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1uhrab</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Grunt08</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The possibility for failure would be unacceptably high. People can survive gunshots to the head. If someone didn't die with the first shot they would be in unimaginable agony. Obviously that would be illegally cruel.

At present, [7.1% of lethal injections in the US are botched](http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-28555978).  Some potential side effects of said botching include full-body agony and suffocation while paralyzed, but fully conscious.  A gunshot to the head can either be immediately effective or quickly followed by a second shot.

&amp;gt;It would be horribly traumatizing to the executioner. They would relive the grisly scene for the rest of their life.

Killing someone requires responsibility.  If you can't find someone willing to nut up and pull the trigger, you shouldn't be ordering it in the first place.  That we pretend killing someone with a pistol shot to the back of the head is less civilized than getting a doctor to do it with a tube and a needle is ridiculous.

If our society wants to demand violence be done in their name, they should damn well own it.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ud8mu</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>browster</author>
        <ReplyBody>Throwing the person off a tall building would be less expensive.  Stabbing them in the heart would be less expensive. No cost of bullets. If your goal is to absolutely minimize even the smallest, most negligible cost without regard to any of other concerns, there are cheaper ways than shooting in the head.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1uei6f</id>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Throwing the person off a tall building would be less expensive.

I'm assuming you don't mean in public, because that would not be a good idea (public people who don't want to see it will see it, potential massive mess, have to calculate where the body is going to land, too many factors). If you propose that we construct a new building in a private area just to throw people off of, that would be a good idea if not very expensive.

&amp;gt;Stabbing them in the heart would be less expensive. 

This is hard to execute correctly every time, the person will always feel a few seconds or even minutes of excruciating pain.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ugao6</id>
            <replies>
                <author>browster</author>
                <ReplyBody>These issues aren't part of your argument, which seems to be based entirely on cost. I'm just saying that there are cheaper methods than shooting, which seems to be the overriding consideration for you. 

They're in a prison complex, so it could be a building there.  Doesn't matter who there sees it.

Pain doesn't matter, because they'll be dead soon anyway, if I'm understanding the gist of your other responses.  Someone can be trained to do it expertly, if that matters. Stabbing must be less expensive than shooting.

The point I'm making is that based on the parameters of your argument, gunshot is not the best choice.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1uhvjg</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>b00st3d</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;They're in a prison complex, so it could be a building there. Doesn't matter who there sees it.

Unless there is some super fortress prison I don't know of, prisons are not tall enough to die from falling with an acceptable rate of death. Hell, people fall from airplanes and survive.

&amp;gt;Pain doesn't matter, because they'll be dead soon anyway, if I'm understanding the gist of your other responses. Someone can be trained to do it expertly, if that matters. Stabbing must be less expensive than shooting.

No, pain does matter, it should be humane. Yes they will be dead anyways so you have many options, but the options are limited to those which offer a near instant death.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1uhzqc</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>browster</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Unless there is some super fortress prison I don't know of, prisons are not tall enough to die from falling with an acceptable rate of death. Hell, people fall from airplanes and survive.

Build a tall tower and throw them onto a pit of vertical knives.  Use a chute if you're worried about missing the target.  It can be done in a way that ensures fatality without any recurring cost.

&amp;gt; No, pain does matter, it should be humane. Yes they will be dead anyways so you have many options, but the options are limited to those which offer a near instant death.

You could run over their head with a dump truck.  Instantaneous, foolproof (certainly more so than a head shot), and zero cost.  Shooting in the head isn't the best option, given the parameters of your argument.

If all you care about is cost and being pain-free, shooting in the head isn't the best choice.


</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1uiepl</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>b00st3d</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Build a tall tower and throw them onto a pit of vertical knives. 

Expensive, time consuming, and possibly inhumane.

&amp;gt;You could run over their head with a dump truck. Instantaneous, foolproof (certainly more so than a head shot), and zero cost. Shooting in the head isn't the best option, given the parameters of your argument.
If all you care about is cost and being pain-free, shooting in the head isn't the best choice.

Unless you were going above the right speed, I imagine it would be very painful and not instantaneous (nothing is instantaneous, just almost instant). It is not foolproof, you can easily miss the head just like you can miss a gunshot. You have to pay for a dump truck and the gas (diesel?), unless you buy a new one and designate it the capital punishment dispenser, which would be more expensive. So not zero cost.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1uiiwf</id>
                            <replies>
<author>browster</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Expensive, time consuming, and possibly inhumane.

Time consuming?  You just march them up the stairs and throw them off.  Or if that takes too much time, just put their cell at the top.  If you're unsure if they'll die, you could tie a rope around their neck before you throw them off.  That wouldn't cost anything.

&amp;gt;Unless you were going above the right speed, I imagine it would be very painful and not instantaneous (nothing is instantaneous, just almost instant). It is not foolproof, you can easily miss the head just like you can miss a gunshot. You have to pay for a dump truck and the gas (diesel?), unless you buy a new one and designate it the capital punishment dispenser, which would be more expensive. So not zero cost.

OK, a train then.  Any regular route near the prison will do.  Head on the rail. Instantaneous. No cost at all.

I can't believe we're arguing over this.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uit9x</id>
<replies>
    <author>b00st3d</author>
    <ReplyBody>Tiring a rope around their neck and throwing them off would be a few split seconds of pain.

You are also traumatizing the train conductor, who (probably) did not want to witness that. The conductor may go the rest of their lives thinking it was their fault.

If you do not want to change my view, you are free to stop commenting.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1uivz0</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>b00st3d</author>
<ReplyBody>Also, the dump truck example would be more time consuming.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uilvo</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MrCapitalismWildRide</author>
        <ReplyBody>Lethal injection itself is not more expensive than life in prison. It's just some chemicals and a syringe.

The expense comes from the process of repeated appeals to ensure that a person is guilty beyond a reasonable doubt before an execution occurs.

What benefit is there to cutting the costs from what I assume is several thousand dollars and a few hours, down to a few dollars and a few minutes, relatively speaking? That's a drop in the bucket compared to everything else the government does, and it's done in the interest of ensuring the punishment is not cruel and unusual.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1ubsei</id>
        <replies>
            <author>RocketCity1234</author>
            <ReplyBody>this is talking about method of capital punishment, not capital punishment in and of its self</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ubuqk</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>ItIsOnlyRain</author>
            <ReplyBody>It would probably cost more money to try and change execution method as it would have to be debated on for a while.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ubw84</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>Downplaying the cost doesn't change the fact that that it is more efficient.

Save money = good

Save time = good

Anyways if you really wanted to get some benefit out of it you can tie the person's hands behind there back and blindfold em, tell them to run around and try to avoid the bullets. Give your local officers some target practice. Not that I'm suggesting this, but this could be done for more "benefits"

EDIT: Also, as stated in the 4th bullet,

&amp;gt;This is all assuming that the criminal is guilty without a reasonable doubt.

I am purely arguing for the fact that AFTER the criminal is already guaranteed death, the method that should be used is this.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ubwkt</id>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>SC803</author>
        <ReplyBody>People occasionally survive gunshots to the head, also finding someone to fire the shot would be difficult </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1uc22s</id>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>Use a large caliber (5.56 or even 7.62, still very cheap per round)

I don't think it would be too difficult, I know I would and can probably think of a few friends who would as well. Yes, it may conflict with many peoples' morals, but in the world we live in, plenty of people would do it for a job.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1uc66p</id>
            <replies>
                <author>SC803</author>
                <ReplyBody>Have you ever killed someone?

Also it doesn't pay very well, my friends dad was the guy who flipped the switch for the chair in an NC prison, he was paid $300 for the night

Plus large caliber bullets ensures closed casket, the families don't deserve to lose that</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>d1ud27m</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>b00st3d</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No, but I am confident I can.

$300 for flipping a switch? Sign me up, I'll flick it until it breaks (figuratively speaking)

Tough luck , your kid / sibling / (insert relation here) was a criminal and got punished. Deal with it.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>d1ud7q7</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SC803</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Also a simple Google could have shown you that lethal injection drugs aren't expensive </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1udshm</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>b00st3d</author>
                            <ReplyBody>still more expensive than ammunition</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1udu8l</id>
                            <replies>
<author>SC803</author>
<ReplyBody>How much do you think the drugs are?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1uek10</id>
<replies>
    <author>b00st3d</author>
    <ReplyBody>More expensive than bullets.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1ugaw9</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SC803</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Then why did modern firing squads begin to use wax rounds for 4 of 5 shooters?

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1ude62</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Grunt08</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Because the executioners were cowards. They didn't want to take responsibility for what they'd done and needed plausible deniability to sleep at night.

They had to pretend that they might not have done what they clearly consented to do.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>d1udmvd</id>
                            <replies>
<author>SC803</author>
<ReplyBody>So if they couldn't find 5 people willing to take the shot then why do you think they could now?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>d1udogb</id>
<replies>
    <author>Grunt08</author>
    <ReplyBody>I don't know whether they could or not (though I'm sure the right Craigslist ad could find someone).  If they couldn't, then nobody should be ordering executions.

My point is that protecting executioners from what they do or observers (and society) from the death they cause is morally indefensible.  Flipping a switch or pushing a plunger kills a person just as much as shooting or beheading, and we shouldn't try to pretend it isn't.

To put it another way: no matter what you think of the death penalty or of the relative humanity of different methods, whether or not it makes observers or executioners feel better shouldn't be part of the issue.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>d1udymu</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>askingdumbquestion</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; was a criminal and got punished.

Or not. Such a cavalier attitude regarding innocent people being executed all the time.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>d1vhhrm</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>RustyRook</author>
        <ReplyBody>I've read many comments and I feel the only thing that may be more efficient, deadly, and cheap --since it's reusable-- would be a guillotine.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1uowf6</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Grava-T</author>
        <ReplyBody>The cost of a lethal injection is something like $90. All other expenses are the result of legal processes and appeals that would take place even with a gun. We pay a little extra so that there isn't a big mess to clean up afterwards, and to lighten the psychological damage to the executioners. There was a reason that firing squads had most of them using blanks...it's because killing people takes a toll on people. You want to have one guy kill them execution style? You'll be paying a lot more than $90 for therapy sessions. I hope I don't need to point out the...issues... Involved in trying to hire remorseless psychos to kill people.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1v6xpv</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>championofobscurity</author>
        <ReplyBody>I disagree with the idea that the best capital punishment is death. Rather public humiliation/stockades where people can peg you with fruit anonymously would likely reduce crime. If you had to stand hunched over 8 hours a day and get pegged by fruit you'd likely never want to commit a crime again after even a short sentence.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1uedob</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Sadsharks</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I disagree with the idea that the best capital punishment is death.

That's oxymoronic; capital punishment *is* death.  Anything else is not capital punishment.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1uhdfo</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>As stated in the OP, I am not arguing over the act of choosing capital punishment. Rather, I am arguing for the method used once capital punishment is assigned.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ug4zo</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>We_Are_Not_Equal</author>
        <ReplyBody>Execution by gunshot is a bit too "militaristic," don't you think? IMO it has too much resemblance to totalitarian extra-judicial killings e.g. in fascist or communist regimes in the 20th century. 

Don't you think a proper hanging is more traditional and "republican?"  You can do it out in public, outside the courthouse if you want! With gunshots, there are safety hazards and the noise is too loud. Think of the money that would be spent on earplugs and cleanup too. A rope and gallows are reuseable, cleaner, no loud noises, no safety hazards, and it's more traditional and "official" looking. It's the perfect choice.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>d1uedph</id>
        <replies>
            <author>b00st3d</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Execution by gunshot is a bit too "militaristic," don't you think?

No

&amp;gt;Don't you think a proper hanging is more traditional and "republican?" You can do it out in public, outside the courthouse if you want! With gunshots, there are safety hazards and the noise is too loud. Think of the money that would be spent on earplugs and cleanup too. A rope and gallows are reuseable, cleaner, no loud noises, no safety hazards, and it's more traditional and "official" looking. It's the perfect choice.

Public hangings open up the execution to people who don't want to see it. In a gunshot-capital punishment situation, the only safety hazards would be when people did not follow procedure. This can be indoors with ear pro or outdoors, and it will only be the executioner and the victim and maybe an overseer present. Cleanup is almost a nonfactor, just put them in a bag or something prior to the shot. **The rope and gallows also make the criminal suffer before their death, which is a huge turn off.**
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>d1ug8m4</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
