<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>101</commentCount>
    <id>2dygof</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/2dygof/cmvdeath_row_inmates_should_either_not_be_allowed/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>mrmanuke</author>
        <ReplyBody>The glaring problem I see is that this would necessarily increase the number of wrongfully executed innocent people. [Here is a list](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_exonerated_death_row_inmates) of exonerated death row inmates from wikipedia.  

&amp;gt;In our hypothetical situation the person being disallowed of making an appeal or multiple appeals is 100% guilty.  

The thing is, that is already supposed to be the standard for putting someone on death row.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjubj4j</id>
        <upvotes>14</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Deadly_Duplicator</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Let us also assume that our hypothetical death row inmate is proven guilty beyond a shadow of a doubt

This is an unrealistic assumption. Are you suggesting there be two categories of death row inmates, those who did it and those who really really for sure 100% did it? How would the difference be determined? 

If your answer is using the judical system, that wouldn't work because the judical system is only supposed to give someone a death sentence if they really really for sure 100% did it, but the fact that death row inmates have been found innocent at all shows that the system has faults, hence the necessity of an appeals process.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjubmh1</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Saaciay</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; This is an unrealistic assumption. Are you suggesting there be two categories of death row inmates, those who did it and those who really really for sure 100% did it? How would the difference be determined?

Maybe it doesn't have to be labeled like that. Maybe there can be separate classifications for if it was "decided" by the court through secondhand evidence, and then the "doubtless" would be that cops witnessed it with video evidence (a point in why I support all cops wearing cameras)</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjuoyot</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Deadly_Duplicator</author>
                <ReplyBody>My point is the distinction would have to be made, and it would have to be made by the judiciary. Like /u/mrmanuke said in their [comment](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/2dygof/cmvdeath_row_inmates_should_either_not_be_allowed/cjubj4j), the highest standard is the only thing that should get someone on death row, thus defeating the utility of having 2 types of death row inmates.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjuu7x4</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>8</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>man2010</author>
        <ReplyBody>What happens when our justice system gets it wrong and we start killing people who are found guilty without giving them a chance to appeal their case? Allowing the government to kill even one innocent person by denying them the ability to appeal their case is one too many.

&amp;gt; In our hypothetical situation the person being disallowed of making an appeal or multiple appeals is 100% guilty. An example would be they were found holding the murder weapon standing over the victim covered in their blood laughing maniacly. So no evidence in the world can save them from execution.

What if this person was standing over the victim covered in their blood because they tried to save the victim? What if they were holding the murder weapon to try to preserve it for the police? Laughing maniacally would be circumstantial evidence, but what if the person wasn't laughing maniacally but rather was laughing nervously as a result of someone dying in their arms? These are all questions that could cast doubt in the guilt of this hypothetical person and would thus be grounds for an appeal.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjubmhj</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>TBH I just used that as an example. Ignore the whole covered in blood laughing thing OK? Let's just leave it at a person murdering someone and having a fair and just trial and being proven beyond a reasonable doubt that he is guilty of said murder and no evidence is going to pop up somehow miraculously declaring him innocent. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjuc3wa</id>
            <replies>
                <author>man2010</author>
                <ReplyBody>The person could still be found innocent if they appealed, like what happens consistently. Your view is based on the idea that the judicial system gets it right 100% of the time, but the fact that we allow for people to appeal the verdicts of the judicial system and that these appeals reverse their original decisions on a regular basis shows that the system itself is imperfect in determining guilt. This means that denying those on death row the ability to appeal their convictions will ultimately result in the government executing more innocent people than it already has. Is that what you want? Would your view be different if you were the person being executed even though you're innocent and don't have the ability to appeal your conviction?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjuc841</id>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>hyperbolical</author>
                <ReplyBody>Meanwhile in the real world, we have no way of knowing if new evidence will pop up. Thus why we need the appeals process (and why the death penalty is a piss-poor idea, but that's irrelevant here). </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjuia75</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>maxpenny42</author>
                <ReplyBody>The only way we can be certain that a trial was fair and executed appropriately is with the proper series of appeals. That what the appeals are for. To determine that everything is kosher. Without appeals we can never fully know that what happened at trail resulted in a fair and just outcome. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjupvy5</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Raintee97</author>
        <ReplyBody>Let me start by saying I am NOT here to debate on whether or not the death penalty is justified. I'm here to debate my view concerning appeals and what happens after someone lands on death row. Let us also assume that our hypothetical death row inmate is proven guilty beyond a shadow of a doubt and is most definitely guilty of the crimes that have landed him on death row in the first place.

You can't make this declaimer as this is not the real world today. That's like saying in world where there are no drunk driving accidents it should be legal to drink and drive:CMV.  

  There is most likely people on death row now who did not do the crime.   There have been people in the past who have been taken off of death row because they didn't do the crime. The appeal process is designed to assist people who have been a victim of a miscarriage of justice. That is its very important role. You can't just disclaimer that fact away. 

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjucc1f</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>I know it isn't but I felt that making this a hypothetical prisoner in a hypothetical fantasy world that has a perfect justice system would make this argument go a lot faster and smoother. Wouldn't you agree? Can you at least grant me that simple assumption? Its not like other people who post in this thread don't include certain stipulations in their arguments so people don't get stuck arguing on the minutiae of the argument. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjucer5</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Raintee97</author>
                <ReplyBody>Sure it makes it simpler to argue, but we aren't talking about the situation as the real world presents that situation. We are talking about a false version of the situation that favors your position. 

In would be like saying, in a world were baseball umps are perfect all the time we shouldn't replace them with computers: CMV.  That's great and all, but I just created a fake world. Baseball umps make mistakes just like the legal system does.  

You can't just disclaim that issue away. You can, but now we are just in a fantasy world of your creation and not the real world where judicial and legal mistakes happen and juries are prejudicial and where police get fake confessions and where those fake confessions convince juries to convict people. It would be nice to have those simply go away so the system can work. Maybe you can think like that, but I can't. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjucn5l</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>whozurdaddy</author>
        <ReplyBody>Id say that if we are going to allow for the death penalty, then we should also allow for as many appeals as is necessary to ensure that the process was fair, that all procedures were followed correctly, and also to allow for time should new evidence come forward.  

Even your hypothetical killer deserves fair treatment under the law. If an attorney did something incorrectly which biased the court, or evidence was not admitted which may have altered the decision or sentence... all of these things have weight in the decisions.  Sometimes even things that the audience in the courtroom does has an impact on the fairness of the trial and is appeal-worthy.  Appeals are meant to ensure fairness, not just handle new evidence.  And when you are talking about ending someone's life, it's only right to do everything possible to be fair.

The problem is really that the court system is too *slow*.  Something of which we are guaranteed by the Constitution, but are incapable of fixing in practicality.   Ironically, I would bet that some people have appealed their cases on the fact that they were not given a speedy trial.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjubix0</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>And another thing your argument seems to be implying (Correct me if I'm wrong) is that unless a convict's trial was without flaw or error on everyone involved's part, from the lawyer to the evidence itself to the judge and jury, he should be allowed to make as many appeals "as is necessary"? You do realize that even if you don't take my hypothetical situation in mind, a perfect trial doesn't really exist in the real world. The lawyers would use every means at their disposal to make as many appeals as possible based off of the slightest error or mistake and by doing this exploiting the various loopholes inherent in appeals. All the while knowing his client is guilty and at this point the appeals only serve to extend his life and save him from execution for a few more months or a year or more. The horrible part about this is that it is a tremendous waste of time effort and money and is a mockery of justice.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjubvqj</id>
            <replies>
                <author>whozurdaddy</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The lawyers would use every means at their disposal to make as many appeals as possible based off of the slightest error or mistake and by doing this exploiting the various loopholes inherent in appeals

I would suggest that attorneys know that some things just wont stand up, and excessive filing of appeals is an expensive process which gains them little if it's just not going to work.  For death row inmates, they probably do file for every little thing.. if they are doing it for the sake of saving the guy's life.  But it shouldnt take 5 months to review the issue.  It should take an hour at best by a different court.

You're right that some attorneys fight this simply because of the death penalty factor. Some consider it their moral obligation to do so.  And thats fine with me, so long as it doesnt take 16 months to review if the stain on the carpet tripped the defense attorney and caused him pain which resulted in him having a bad day and unable to question a key witness :/  
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjuc1ga</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I absolutely agree with you on everything you said. A lawyer can use anything to file an appeal on his client's behalf no matter how insignificant or ridiculous. That is why the appeals system for death row inmates is vastly flawed and an overall waste. Why waste millions of dollars and years of time and effort when a simple $1 bullet and a few minutes will suffice.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cjucalf</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>adagencies</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Why waste millions of dollars and years of time and effort when a simple $1 bullet and a few minutes will suffice.

Because human beings have rights. Arguments about efficiency aren't meaningful in the face of rights.

We could also execute everyone accused of murder, immediately, with no trial. That would save billions in costs. Why not? For the same reason - people have rights, and these rights are sacrosanct.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cjudb9r</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>maxpenny42</author>
                <ReplyBody>I don't believe there is such a thing as "as many appeals as necessary". There are limited appeals courts. At some point you have exhausted your options and are asking the Supreme Court to hear the case which they rarely do. At that point the appeals process ends. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjupyni</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Considering the average stay of a death row inmate now is about 15 years in prison I'm sure that you could file a lot of appeals if you were determined to and they have many times before</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cjuqarv</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>Are you saying our killer who is absolutely guilty, all the evidence proves it, he was tried fairly and provided with a proper defense in court without a single mistake (However unlikely it's a hypothetical situation) should be allowed to waste millions of the taxpayers' money and years delaying his inevitable death? The whole point of my view is to provide an infinitely more efficient way of execution while costing little to nothing. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjubp3p</id>
            <replies>
                <author>DHCKris</author>
                <ReplyBody>That makes no sense. Are you saying our killer who is absolutely innocent, the evidence was unclear and some of it was falsified, he was tried unfairly and his lawyers screwed him over and made many mistakes *shouldn't* be allowed to use the taxpayer's money to *save his own life?* And if that person has that right, then so too does the definitely guilty person, otherwise there is no point to appealing. You can't make a rule like, "oh you can appeal only if you're really not guilty." How would that even work? 

Honestly yours is a good argument for just not having the death penalty period.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjubszg</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No a good argument to make it a 1000 times more efficient. Also I can understand the need for 1 appeal, but anymore than that seems really ridiculous and wasteful. It should at least be limited to one appeal.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cjubybi</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>DHCKris</author>
                        <ReplyBody>What if someone is innocent, and immediately appeals and fails, then a year later, new evidence comes about that completely exonerates him. But, oh well, he already had his one appeal; guess he's gonna die an innocent man!</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cjubzsx</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>That is why I'm providing a hypothetical prisoner who isn't innocent, has been proven guilty, and no evidence will come to light a year later proving their innocence because their isn't any to prove. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cjuc1gd</id>
                            <replies>
<author>DHCKris</author>
<ReplyBody>But that doesn't matter. If my hypothetical prisoner can (and I think he should) get more than one appeal, then everyone can. That's justice.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cjuc23m</id>
<replies>
    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
    <ReplyBody>How many appeals should he be allowed to have? Because the number of appeals allowed at this point seems really arbitrary and a vast waste of money and resources. Every time the prisoner doesn't get his way because his appeal failed he is just going to file as many as you let him until you decide to kill him once and for all. By that time millions of dollars are gone all for nothing. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cjuccn4</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>4</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>maxpenny42</author>
<ReplyBody>In a hypothetical world in which we can know he is guilty for certain and that no new evidence will be uncovered, sure skip the appeals. That never happens in the real world and it is an impossibility. We cannot predict the future. So your scenario is brick man (inverse of a straw man) in that you've created a scenario impervious to being knocked down but that isn't the problem we are debating. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cjuq2q4</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>mrmanuke</author>
                        <ReplyBody>If you look at the list I posted in my top level comment, the most recent person appealed multiple times before being exonerated.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cjuc8x0</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>He was exonerated because he was innocent while the prisoner I'm referring to is guilty and has been proven guilty and no amount of appeals in the world will change his fate. Does that clear things up a bit?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cjuchph</id>
                            <replies>
<author>mrmanuke</author>
<ReplyBody>Your hypothetical situation of being 100% certain doesn't exist in the real world. In reality, a person must be proven guilty before being put on death row. Your proposed change would have no affect on who gets put on death row. It may save money, but it would also prevent innocent people from being removed from death row.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cjucsin</id>
<replies>
    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
    <ReplyBody>OK lets say someone is proven guilty beyond the shadow of a reasonable doubt in a court, and they make their first appeal and it fails and their execution is scheduled soon, what then? Do we allow someone to make pointless wasteful appeal after appeal until they react an arbitrary number and we execute them? That's what I'm trying to prevent, anyone can see that our current appeals system for death row inmates is a joke and far from optimal. And that leads us back to the whole "1 appeal and if you fail you get a bullet in the head" argument?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cjucxc7</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>4</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>man2010</author>
                <ReplyBody>Except the "killer" in the example you provided isn't absolutely guilty. This "killer" could have had blood all over him from trying to save the victim. He could have been holding the murder weapon to preserve it for the police to properly examine. Him laughing maniacally is circumstantial evidence, but he could have been laughing nervously instead because the victim just died in his arms.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjubweh</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>whozurdaddy</author>
                <ReplyBody>To be consider a fair trial, you have to have someone *else* confirm it.  That's the idea behind appeals.  Did the judge have the right to withhold evidence?  Did the jury selection bias the court against the black guy?  Did the (oh I dunno) accidental comment by the sequestered juror sway the opinion of the other jurors?

Once everything has been hashed out and it has all been deemed fair, then sure - light him up.  But dont you think he deserves *at least* that much?  Again, the problem isnt the appeals - it's the speed at which everything goes.  10 years on death row is absurd.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjubtfd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Yes 10 years on death row is ridiculous. 5 years is ridiculous. Any amount of time longer than it would take to simply have someone put a bullet in the inmate's head or hang him or lethally inject is ridiculous, ESPECIALLY if they had their chance in court and were proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cjubzzf</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>whozurdaddy</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;e longer than it would take to simply have someone put a bullet in the inmate's head or hang him or lethally inject is ridiculous

See this [link](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/innocence-list-those-freed-death-row).  

You cant just go from "guilty" to the chair.  Too many cases have been overturned years later.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cjuc4q9</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>That is why I made up an imaginary prisoner that doesn't exist in the reality that we know and reside in. So your lists of innocent death row inmates don't apply to my hypothetical prisoner. Understand?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cjucgpv</id>
                            <replies>
<author>adagencies</author>
<ReplyBody>I don't understand.

The purpose of the justice system is to determine whether or not individuals are guilty without actually knowing guilt.

The fact that you're claiming your hypothetical prisoner is absolutely guilty makes no difference, since the justice system cannot know that. The justice system has no choice but to operate on evidence. Evidence, regardless of how convincing at a particular point in time, has a nasty habit of appearing to be less useful later on. Worse, new evidence that is contradictory to previous evidence can be found after a period of time. Sometimes this period of time is several years.

Your hypothetical prisoner, guilty as sin, or not, would still have to benefit from all the legal protections afforded to all prisoners.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cjuda7x</id>
<replies>
    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
    <ReplyBody>I understand what you are saying but are you implying that we should allow the majority of death row inmates (Who are most likely guilty) to abuse the appeals system as many times as they want? 

I think we can reach a compromise. Here me out: a prisoner is convicted of murder in court, he makes an appeal and it finds nothing to cast a doubt on his guilt. He makes another appeal and it is the same result. He makes a third appeal and he's still found guilty. Where is the cut off point is what I'm getting at? Should he be allowed to make as many appeals as he wants even if no evidence comes forth exonerating him? Should there be a set amount of appeals he can make before he is killed? Some arbitrary number chosen? Should a prisoner be only allowed to be on death row for 5 years? 10 years? 15 years before they are executed? I think there should be certain limits. How about you?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cjudfp9</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>dale_glass</author>
<ReplyBody>Then your hypothethical scenario doesn't apply to the reality in which we make laws about how death penalty should work.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cjucvh6</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Jazz-Cigarettes</author>
        <ReplyBody>What would you say to the actual people in real life who have secured their release from death row after winning their appeal, or losing an initial appeal and winning a later one?

Would you say, "Too bad, sucks to be you guys but I would have been comfortable with you dying. I know your convictions were unfounded and executing you would have been a terrible miscarriage of justice, but you gotta understand, I just *really, really* wanna kill other convicts who I'm super sure are guilty of their crimes."

More to the point, your hypothetical is fanciful enough that it doesn't seem to have any applicability to the real world. Saying, "but what if the criminal definitely did it for sure," doesn't describe a scenario that has ever happened in the real world, nor one that will ever happen. We can't ever know that, we'll never have 100% certainty of the facts of any crime.

It's like you're asking for an omniscient "justice supercomputer" that's infallible and just decides the verdict of crimes without us needing to hold trials. But since we don't have that, we have to account for human fallibility and leave in mechanisms like appeals for us to correct the inevitable mistakes in the justice system--if we even have to have capital punishment to begin with.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjudljn</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>Let me clarify something since I didn't include it in the OP. If whoever decides whether or not an appeal is granted (I'm not familiar with this aspect) decides that prisoner A has a solid case for his innocence, then yes he should be granted appeals. But it has to be a solid concrete case for his innocence understand? Is that fair and reasonable? Now someone who goes on a killing rampage and is caught gunning people down in a public place and is subdued by the police...(Louhhner, James Holmes, etc) People like that shouldn't be given a chance for appeal if they are so obviously guilty it is ridiculous. They should be executed immediately after their sentence is given. IF THEY ARE OBVIOUSLY CERTAINLY GUILTY (Like James Holmes, Ted Bundy etc) to such a degree that the chance of them being innocent is less than 0.0000000001%. Not if there is a 50 50 chance of them being guilty or a 40 60 chance of them being innocent. Understand now?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjudqii</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>halfascoolashansolo</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;My argument now is that not every single person on death row should be allowed appeals or multiple appeals if the case for their guilt is too grear for their claimed innocence to be **Reasonably** faced.

So how would this system work exactly? How do we decide which people are allowed appeals and which aren't?


And if their guilt is so great in the first place why waste taxpayer money on a capital trial? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjv7rln</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>BreaksFull</author>
        <ReplyBody>The point of all the appeals is to delay the execution date so that evidence proving them innocent may be found. Considering that -despite all the appeals- we still sometimes execute innocent people, it seems mad to restrict appeals.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjubjhq</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Webby2120</author>
        <ReplyBody>there are very few cases where it is a 100% guilty verdict and even if it is 100% certain that the person was guilty what are the motives behind it?

Have you seen the movie "too young to die" it does a good job of highlighting how someone can end up on death row be 100 percent guilty of a crime but still deserve a chance to appeal.

I think you find that the majority of cases are not open and shut, who gets to decided if someone is 100% guilty or not? 

I agree if somebody takes a gun into a public place and start shooting, they should just be shot on the spot and save everyone time and money but i think if you look into most death row inmates their cases are not as open and shut.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjubnzu</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>In my opinion someone who kills a large amount of people in public and is found standing there  amidst the bodies holding a gun wearing tactical gear should just be shot right there. I agree with you on that.

I'm going to stress the point I made in my original post and have made a few times since this thread started: 

I understand in the real world that rarely is a death row case so open and shut but in this situation can we assume that we live in a perfect world where a person is proven absolutely 100% guilty of a murder or murders and justly tried without any error or mishandling of evidence or anything of that nature. We are discussing a hypothetical imaginary convict. He doesn't exist in this reality. I hope that clears things up because I'm tired of people bringing up how no one is ever truly 100% guilty. I know that that is why I made it hypothetical in the first place.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjuc8du</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Webby2120</author>
                <ReplyBody>if we lived in a perfect world with a perfect justice system there would be no need for any appeals process. the appeal process exists because once someone has been executed there is no bringing them back, It is worth the cost to make sure that we do not execute someone who is innocent.

imagine if you walk into a room and find yourself surrounded by dead bodies and there is a gun on the table. you run to a body to check if they are alive get some blood on you. then you hear something you turn around and see a masked figure enter the room, he reaches for a knife and runs at you, you grab the gun and fire, you miss, the masked man run off, next thing you know the cops come in you are standing in a room full of dead bodies holding a gun. you drop the gun immediately and you are arrested. your prints are on the gun, there is GSR on your hands and clothes you are pretty boned.   

from the outside it looks pretty bad pretty open and shut, you are found guilty, do you still think you have the right to appeall? 


</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjucqbv</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                    <ReplyBody>When does something like that ever happen? I mean I understand people are falsely convicted but making it seem like that no matter how large a case against someone is, no matter how vast the evidence against him, there is still a small .001% chance it could be a huge mistake and he's innocent is false and ridiculous. 

When has anything even remotely like what you described as an example ever occurred? Please provide some actual examples instead of making up what ifs that are completely outlandish</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cjud1pc</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Webby2120</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Yes i Agree my example is outlandish and wild, If something like that had ever happened the truth probably would not of come out. 

here are some examples of people found innocent after execution 

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse_Tafero

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlos_DeLuna

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy_Evans

http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campden_Wonder</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cjuexdm</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Remind me what your argument is again. I kinda got lost arguing with another guy until we both reached a compromise</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cjuezy7</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Webby2120</author>
<ReplyBody>there is no such thing as open and open shut case, it is worth the time and money even if it just stops 1 innocent person out of 1000 from being executed. there are examples of things that looked open and shut but later turned out to be wrong.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cjugp32</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>One_Wheel_Drive</author>
                            <ReplyBody>The Campden Wonder would make an amazing movie. 

Edit: Also, [your list is nowhere near long enough.](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_exonerated_death_row_inmates)</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cjugh54</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ThrustVectoring</author>
        <ReplyBody>Really, this is a question about who should be allowed to decide whether or not someone can launch an appeal. The answer is the court that holds the power to hear appeals - they're close to the problem, and are generally less biased than the people responsible for the conviction in the first place.

If you give this power to the prosecutor or judge, there's no recourse for getting railroaded by a local court.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjucthq</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>I agree that the ability to make appeals should be RESPONSIBLY limited to certain prisoners that have a strong case for their innocence. People like Ted Bundy and other monsters shouldn't be allowed to make appeals if the evidence against them is too concrete to reconsider their guilt or innocence. There is no need to waste hundreds of millions of dollars for nothing when it could be put to better use. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjudkc7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>ThrustVectoring</author>
                <ReplyBody>The real question is who gets to decide whether or not you're allowed to appeal. Whoever can decide that has oversight over the court that made the decision you are appealing. We've already decided who has that power - the appeal court for that jurisdiction. There's no need to change anything, since the appeal court can already decide to not hear an appeal.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjutnx1</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The only reason why the death penalty costs so much is because of all the stupid and useless appeals filed by pro-bono law groups in the names of death row inmates for no other reason than to make the process more expensive so that later on they can complain about how expensive the process is.  
  
This is not the only reason. You're assuming a lot about the motivations of these groups. Also, the only person that can appeal is the prisoner. If he or she is unwilling to go forward with elective appeals, then no group can have standing to speak on his or her behalf. I posted a TED talk in another comment where a death row attorney outlines the appeals that are available. You would do well to watch it.  
  
&amp;gt;We have decided as a nation and a society that some crimes are so heinous that they deserve the worst punishment, meaning taking someone's life away or their taking their right to live away.   
  
Not my state. Michigan abolished the death penalty in 1846, that's pre-Civil War. Only 34 states still execute, plus the military and the Federal Government. Sure, that's a plurality, but it's not all states.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjuhxwb</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>Very few death row inmates refuse appeals. Most of them jump at the chance to temporarily extend their life expectedly with the unfortunate effect of resources wasted and large sums of money wasted. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjuoibd</id>
            <replies>
                <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                <ReplyBody>I understand that, but the fact remains that outside groups cannot act without the OK from the inmate. Just like I cannot sue your neighbor for you if your neighbor damages your property, I wouldn't have legal standing. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjup2bd</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>mcg2</author>
        <ReplyBody>You'd have to add an amendment to the US Constitution that says something along the lines of, "by the way, none of these rights applies to citizens who have been sentenced by the federal or state governments to death" or "none of these rights apply to citizens who have been sentenced to death and have appealed once." Good luck doing that with the current Congress, which has set the record for passing the least amount of legislation of any Congress in US history.

For people who have irrational and over-the-top reactions to crimes, like this, I usually ask them to just look around at the world. Would any of the Scandanavian nations dream of passing legislation like this? What about Switzerland? Or the Netherlands? What about states like Vermont? There are some parts of the world that have extremely low unemployment, excellent healthcare systems, their citizens score highest in contentment, quality of life, and happiness, their economies are consistently rated the most robust, aggressive, and productive in the world, low income disparity, high quality of living, etc.

Then take a look at Eastern Europe, or Nigeria, or Mississippi and Alabama. These places have the kinds of societies and governments that have your mentality. Completely unnecessary overreactions to crime. An absolute obsession with "law and order", the death penalty, life sentences, chain gangs, striping people of their rights, human rights violations galore, and look at what they have to show for it. All of these places fall dead last in the developed world when it comes to quality of life, income disparity, poverty, lack of education, poor healthcare, longevity, happiness, and other barometers of a vibrant, successful, and prosperous place.

So the question is, would you rather have an enlightened society like Sweden or Switzerland, or a society based on revenge and retribution and testosterone outbursts like Uganda and Belarus? Would you rather live in a state that enjoys clean air and water, a high standard of living, great schools, and overall great well-being like some of the New England states, or live in the South where you can enjoy anti-union anti-minimum wage, anti-environmental regulations, anti-justice, anti-democracy, anti-Constitutional rights (except the 2nd amendment of course), and live amidst a racist, socially stratified, environmentally degraded state like West Virginia or the impoverished dumps in the South?

This whole thing is a mindset. It all goes hand in hand. That's why "law and order" places also fail in other respects, like environmental and educational quality. It is the symptom of a "tough love" type of society, one where stomping a mud hole in other people's lives because they did something wrong is acceptable. And that mentality is generalized to minorities and the environment as well. And I'm not dissing WV or any of the Southern states, I myself am from the South, and I think its sad that they have elected governments that have the kind of mentality that would be right at home with the kind of legislation you propose for death penalty inmates.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjuiff3</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>You're only giving me 2 choices as if there is no middle ground. Either have the US be like Sweden with clean air, water, and other stuff that has no relevancy to this argument at all or have it be like a poor African shithole like Uganda. Where did I propose any of this in my argument?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjuocf6</id>
            <replies>
                <author>mcg2</author>
                <ReplyBody>It all goes together. Its a package deal. And out of more than 200 nations, and countless more local, state, and provincial governments, you can't point to a single one that has draconian prison sentences, prolific death penalty implementation, and doesn't have all manner of violations of civil liberties and ram ant environmental degradation. That's not a coincidence. It is a mindset. If you want to live in some savage, knuckle-dragging society with state executions and chain gangs, you will also live in a society that couldn't care a less about surveillance, environmental destruction, homophobia, racism, and misogyny. Because there are two societies to live in: a society that reflects the interests of its citizens, and a society that reflects the concentration of power that defines state interests. And those two diverging interests manifest themselves in ways that are consistent no matter where you look.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjv35yj</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>hacksoncode</author>
        <ReplyBody>The problem with your view isn't your unrealistic assumption that it's even theoretically possible for someone to be 100% known to be guilty. It's with understanding what an appeal *means*.

If an appeal is granted (i.e. allowed to move forward to that point where you claim that it's "wasting money"), that means that some judge somewhere has examined the argument being made in the appeal and says "yes, there's something here that we need to have argued".

If there's something to be argued, then by definition the conviction wasn't 100% known to be correct. If there's nothing to be argued, then the appeal will not go forward, and the cost will be relatively minor.

The reason your view doesn't work in the real world is that there always *are* things to argue about in a death penalty case. 

For example, we have, as a society, decided that people who are so mentally ill as to not have a conception of right and wrong are not to be executed. You may agree or disagree with this, but it's a real point that actually has to be determined in order for the execution to proceed. And it's a very hazy concept that takes a lot of evidence to demonstrate, and often can never be demonstrated to everyone's satisfaction.

We have similarly decided, as a society, that evidence that is gathered in contravention of our Constitution (i.e. the fundamental rules that we agree to live by in society) is not to be considered in criminal trials. But this is also not a cut-and-dried issue, because the interpretation of what acts constitute contravention of the Constitution change regularly.

We have also decided as a society that people should receive adequate legal counsel in trials, especially when their lives are on the line. This is not an "obvious" thing, but has to be argued and decided.

These are just the most obvious 3 areas of haziness, but there are innumerable others. 

Basically, the entire legal appeals process is *exactly* how we try to get to that mythical 100% certainty that you're hypothesizing in this CMV. 100% certainty is not cheap. It's very very expensive to rule out all of the possible ways in which we might be uncertain about something.

Hell, philosophers don't even think 100% correct "knowledge" is even a possible concept. It should not be surprising that its extraordinarily difficult and expensive to even approach that standard. 

Your contention that we should reduce appeals is basically an argument that we shouldn't try so hard to be 100% accurate in our convictions, because appeals are exactly how we try to do that. Your attempt at begging the question falls rather flat.

For the record, I think that if you could prove someone was sane with near 100% certainty, and you had a high resolution videotape, collected in in a manner where there was no argument that it was in complete accord with our Constitutional protections, and proven to be accurate and not modified by the government, of the criminal not only killing people, but also being arrested (so that there was no possibility of mistaken identity), then, perhaps, we would be so close to certain that there would be little to appeal about.

And, indeed, in that case, the appeals very likely wouldn't take much time (or expense) to process.

It's just that that situation has never actually occurred, ever, in the history of the justice system, so we have little precedent to cover it.

TL;DR: Appeals are how we *get* to that near 100% certainty that you are trying to assume happens right away... it doesn't.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cjun4ac</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Cmyers1980</author>
            <ReplyBody>You are right you can't ask for 100 percent certainty in the real world. What I'm saying is that our current appeals system could be greatly improved so justice is carries out swiftly, fairlt , and with no large sums of money wasted so some convicts can live a bit longer. Which is what it is used for mostly. Not proving innocence but to tie the courts up so he doesn't have to face death. This defeats the entire purpose of the death penalty if the majority of death row inmates never get executed even if that would be the more cost efficient way. After all a bullet costs less than 2 dollars. I'm simply asking for a change in the system that doesn't hurt the chances of an innocent person being exonerated. It is the vast abuse exploitation and abuse that sickens me. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cjuoziw</id>
            <replies>
                <author>hacksoncode</author>
                <ReplyBody>What you consider to be abuse and exploitation of the system is, in fact, exactly how the system is supposed to work. When there is a question about whether evidence was handled properly, that's not a "loophole", that's something that really needs to be determined.

The fact that you can't actually ask for 100% certainty in the real world is the best possible argument to not have the death penalty at all. 

It's not an argument, by any ethical standard that I can imagine, for the position that we should be happy with 95% accuracy, or even 99%, when we're talking about dealing out unredeemable and permanent punishments. 

Personally, I think that the death penalty should only be considered in cases where the judge, jury, and prosecution are *so* certain that they are not committing premeditated murder themselves, via the judicial process, that they are willing to be executed themselves if it is later proven that the accused was innocent. 

And that their execution should be just as swift and appeals-free as you want their innocent victim's to be.

The fact that no one would ever be certain enough to sign up for this just drives home to me that the whole process is a hypocritical absurdity. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cjursfn</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>Let me start by saying I am NOT here to debate on whether or not the death penalty is justified. I'm here to debate my view concerning appeals and what happens after someone lands on death row. Let us also assume that our hypothetical death row inmate is proven guilty beyond a shadow of a doubt and is most definitely guilty of the crimes that have landed him on death row in the first place.

A common argument against the death penalty is that it costs many times more than just letting a convict rot in prison for the rest of his life. This is true only because of appeals made by the death row inmate which can run into millions of dollars of taxpayers' money wasted and years wasted just so he can get executed anyway.

The only reason why the death penalty costs so much is because of all the stupid and useless appeals filed by pro-bono law groups in the names of death row inmates for no other reason than to make the process more expensive so that later on they can complain about how expensive the process is. They create the problem within a system they disagree with so they can complain about the problem with the system. You shouldn't create a large flaw and then use it as evidence that you are correct.

A counter argument to my view could be that the death row inmate still deserves a right to appeal regardless of his actions or the fact that he is on death row. My argument against that is as follows:

 We have decided as a nation and a society that some crimes are so heinous that they deserve the worst punishment, meaning taking someone's life away or their taking their right to live away. Many would agree that a person's life is the most valuable thing you can ever possess and is the only thing that truly belongs to you. Now if we have a justice system that deems it justifiable and acceptable to take someone's life away if they have been proven of committing certain horrible crimes like murder in a court of law, then I really don't think taking away a death row inmate's right to appeal is that big of a deal and something to get angry over.

If new evidence is found that casts doubt on a person's guilt, then I can see why an appeal would be necessary. The key word is IF. In our hypothetical situation the person being disallowed of making an appeal or multiple appeals is 100% guilty. An example would be they were found holding the murder weapon standing over the victim covered in their blood laughing maniacly. So no evidence in the world can save them from execution.

That leaves one alternative to our usual costly method of multiple million dollar appeals that take years and years to process. A bullet costs less than $2. A rope costs less than $15 dollars and is reusable. Hell you could recruit people off the street that own their own gun and bullets who would be WILLING to execute a death row murderer or mass murderer. 

The inmate is dead and justice is served at little to zero to the taxpayers in a timely and efficient manner. I can't really think of any good counter arguments to my view but that is where you guys come in. Change my view!

Edit: Since people are saying my hypothetical situation defeats the purpose of appeals I'm going to narrow it down to the real world. My argument now is that not every single person on death row should be allowed appeals or multiple appeals if the case for their guilt is too grear for their claimed innocence to be **Reasonably** faced. Someone like a serial killer or a mass shooter who guns a bunch of people down in public in clear view of everyone and the police. Letting someone like that appeal over and over again to the point their scheduled execution is a decade or more away, all the while mocking the justice system and wasting millions of dollars and vast amounts of resources, is wrong and completely ridiculous. Our current system is greatly flawed due to the fact that any prisoner regardless of the case against them can and will abuse and exploit the appeals system to delay their impending death with the help of lawyers and pro bono law groups who then use the large cost as proof that we shouldn't have the death penalty, even though they are making the problem even worse than it should be while claiming the moral high ground. 

Here is a link describing how horrible and inefficient it is currently: http://m.sfgate.com/opinion/saunders/article/The-triumph-of-dubious-death-penalty-appeals-5631469.php

California has sentenced 900 people to the death penalty since 1972 and executed 13. The average stay for a death row inmate in California is over 15 years long due to them filing appeal after appeal. Most of them die of old age rather than getting executed. This is greatly inefficient and ridiculous and anyone should be able to see that 13 out of 900 sentenced is sad. That is little over 1 percent of the total prisoners sentenced to the death penalty since 1972. Anyone who looks at this as anything near acceptable and proper justice is being ridiculous and most of all mistaken. 

 The cost of the death penalty in California has totaled over $4 billion since 1978. I wonder how much of it was spent unnecessarily on appeals that only resulted in extending the criminal's life and nothing more

Link describing the appeals process: 
http://criminal.lawyers.com/criminal-law-basics/death-sentence-appeals-take-time-for-a-reason.html

In 2010, a death row inmate waited an average of 178 months (or close to 15 years) between sentencing and execution. Nearly a quarter of deaths on death row in the U.S. are due to natural causes. More evidence our current appeals system is a joke and should be improved upon.


&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
