<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I'm sorry, but if countries and states don't give a damn that they are killing human beings - even if the human being commits a "horrible" crime, what is wrong with (biologically) healthy individuals killing themselves if they so choose?  

There will be devil's advocates when this is how you present your argument. Countries that have the death penalty have them either because they believe it is the ultimate form of punishment reserved for "ultimate" crimes (mass/repeat murder, treason, etc), acts as a deterrent, removes an unwanted person from society or just saves money compared to life in prison. There are reasons why a nation would have the death penalty on the table that are completely independent from whether or not helping someone else kill themselves should be legal. You are trying to turn two debates into one, but they have very little in common. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvji6u</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>The issues of death penalty and euthanasia aren't all that different--they're both about who (if anyone) has the authority to end someone's life--and the OP is essentially correct in pointing out the absurdity of a government whose justice system is the *only* authority permitted to kill its citizens.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvqyg4</id>
            <replies>
                <author>celticguy08</author>
                <ReplyBody>But really how absurd is it? The justice system (in most developed nations) isn't just a group of people who decide who lives and dies. Through the various checks and balances present between the government branches, the process of a jury being chosen, etc. the decisions made in court a very much extensions of the opinions of the society the accused resides in.

Ideally, the government is simply a system to organize and put into effect the decisions of the governed. Obviously it's not the case everywhere yet if you have a plan to establish just governments across the world go ahead.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvv1pj</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>reprapraper</author>
                    <ReplyBody>but why should that system trump one's own self?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckw67ak</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>celticguy08</author>
                        <ReplyBody>When someone wants to die without a physical health reason (aka, is already dying), then it is a mental health issue that should be treated, not given in to. If you don't believe me, ask the hundreds of thousands who have attempted suicide and are now glad that they failed.

Yet, when someone is sentenced to the death penalty and has gone all the way through the appeals process to no avail, it essentially means society wants them to die. And that is alright because it means everyone else, all of the good-natured contributions to the progress of the human race benefits from it.

Obviously there are arguments against both arguments I presented, but like I said, they are separate with separate consequences and in no way should be considered an all or nothing deal.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckw7p9h</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>reprapraper</author>
                            <ReplyBody>why should psychological anguish be different from physical? why should we be telling people, "no, you're pain is the wrong kind, you're going to have to wait until it kills you inderectly"</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckwydxs</id>
                            <replies>
<author>celticguy08</author>
<ReplyBody>Because psychological illnesses cannot be terminal. It can always be treated and diminished. IIRC we don't let people kill themselves unless their illness is terminal.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckx0sw5</id>
<replies>
    <author>reprapraper</author>
    <ReplyBody>so, somebody who is suffering from psychological illness kills themselves because of that illness, they have not died because of that illness?</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckx1e26</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;If you don't believe me, ask the hundreds of thousands who have attempted suicide and are now glad that they failed.

How about people like me that tried and failed multiple times and are pissed off that they failed and wish they could just easily end it all because their life is a cesspool of shit that has not been getting better and due to their circumstances will not? I imagine you'll say,"well just don't pay rent and go buy a gun instead." It's not that simple. There's always a nagging part of you that tries to keep you alive. Keep you going through your paces. Literally keeping you doing the shit you want to escape. I just want it to be legal. Sanctioned. No fear of repercussions like involuntary lock up if I fail. Let me fucking die with someone dignity. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckwbxuo</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>There are a ton of methods out there that can kill you with certainty. Ultimately if you want to die then you will do it. Jump off a large bridge/building/parking garage, take a tylenol and soak in warm water for a few minutes then slit your wrists, electrocute your chest with enough voltage, carbon monoxide poisoning. The list really does go on and on and on.

If you really wanted to die you would do it. End of story.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckwdlp9</id>
<replies>
    <author>[deleted]</author>
    <ReplyBody>*claps* bravo. Spoken exactly like someone who doesn't understand at all the thought process that drives someone to end their life. You've got a lot to learn. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckwdpwg</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>celticguy08</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; due to their circumstances will not?

You don't know the future bro, that is the depression speaking. I know because I have it too, I have attempted suicide too, you aren't alone in everything you are feeling. Please seek help at /r/depression or other related subreddits or one of the hotlines that is posted there.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckwjbv3</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The issues of death penalty and euthanasia aren't all that different--they're both about who (if anyone) has the authority to end someone's life

I disagree, they have a certain thing in common (death by the hands of the government), but the arguments for why one is valid and the other isn't (regardless of which is which) are more much complex and specific to each than the one thing they have in common. Adding any of these factors makes it clear that the decision for one should have zero outcome of the decision of the other.  

&amp;gt; absurdity of a government whose justice system is the only authority permitted to kill its citizens  

That doesn't come off as absurd though, does it? If you were to guess which part of the government that could kill its citizens, it would be the military and the justice system, wouldn't it?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvvxxp</id>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>thaelmpeixoto</author>
                <ReplyBody>For what I see, in a State with death penalty and without euthanasia, the State still have power over the life of its citizens. Monarchist much?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckw52sx</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>23</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Dakrys</author>
            <ReplyBody>A lifetime prison sentence is less expensive than the death penalty. 

The legal process for death row is *very* extensive and it takes years to prepare. Beyond that, the prisioner will be held, fed, clothed, etc. for the duration of the setup. Then they have to pay specialists to actually perform the procedure. They have to have a legal team ready to go as well, because depending on the circumstances (something goes wrong, etc.) the family of the inmate might sue for cruel and unusual punishment. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvos3z</id>
            <replies>
                <author>The_Hoopla</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think he's making an example for why *someone would argue that*, not that the argument is, indeed, correct. Also that's really just in the case for the United States. The Saudis, for example, save an exorbitant amount of money simply executing their prisoners.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvqvh5</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Dakrys</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I see. I was interpreting "death penalty" from OP's standpoint where he seemed to be talking about more civilized countries. I don't think OP is quite fighting for the right to a merciful death in countries where talking shit about the color of some dude's shoes might get your head chopped off and shat in. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvqy7h</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I see. I was interpreting "death penalty" from OP's standpoint where he seemed to be talking about more civilized countries

Which civilized countries, with the exception of the US, have the death penalty? If it's only the US, then that's not a great sample size for how it could work - the US is pretty unique in a lot of ways, especially when it comes to crime and punishment, and getting bang for your buck.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvvtm8</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckw9owq</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>Cheers, it'd be interesting to see what these three countries have in common and what they don't. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckwd4ky</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>26</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>alaricus</author>
                <ReplyBody>You're speaking about a very specific instance of the death penalty and of life in prison. It doesnt have to be more expensive to kill someone than it does to keep them in prison for life. It can, in fact, be very cheap. The argument that it is more economical, is, if anything, simply an argument that too much money is spent on the legal process of killing someone. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvr3d1</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>vbevan</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Except for those pesky people who keep getting found to be innocent. That'd be a fairly strong argument that the amount being spent on legal costs for death row inmates isn't too much.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckwbmkq</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>15</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>ironmenon</author>
                <ReplyBody>You are speaking specifically about the USA which is one of the few (maybe the only?)  countries that hands out death sentences like they are candy while at the same time granting the convict a lot of rights such as multiple appeals, good living and dying conditions AND has complicated execution methods like lethal injections. I doubt most of these must be issues in other countries that kill a lot of people like China or Saudi Arabia.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvueu4</id>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Batty-Koda</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;A lifetime prison sentence is less expensive than the death penalty. 

I hate that being used in just about any death penalty debate, because it acts as though that's a necessary inherent part of the death penalty. It isn't. I really doubt it's true over in China, too.

Everything you just said is an argument against the current US implementation of the death penalty. It doesn't carry over to a general argument against the death penalty as a whole.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvw7as</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>amaru1572</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Maybe so, but the arguments you see about the death penalty are usually about the US, so it's a good argument in practice for the most part.

With that said, maybe it is an inherent part of the death penalty. Yeah, you can say that you can theoretically kill people for the cost of a bullet (or a garrote or whatever) and that costs less than putting someone up in a prison for life, and that's obviously true, but then who says putting someone up in prison for life needs to be a net loss? Certainly, more money is spent on prisoners than really needs to be too, and living prisoners can provide what amounts to slave labor which could provide vastly more value than the cost of housing them over the rest of their lives.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckw2edi</id>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Utaneus</author>
                <ReplyBody>You know that this is unique to the US, right? Most other countries that have the death penalty do not allow for a lengthy appeals process. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvvmad</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>raff_riff</author>
                <ReplyBody>Source?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckw4cz5</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>De_Facto</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;A lifetime prison sentence is less expensive than the death penalty. 

&amp;gt;The legal process for death row is *very* extensive and it takes years to prepare. Beyond that, the prisioner will be held, fed, clothed, etc. for the duration of the setup. Then they have to pay specialists to actually perform the procedure. They have to have a legal team ready to go as well, because depending on the circumstances (something goes wrong, etc.) the family of the inmate might sue for cruel and unusual punishment. 

You're writing this in regard to the US. In poorer countries with limited rights, once you're covicted of a capital crime,  you're dead within a few weeks. 
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwafsx</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Str8tuptrollin</author>
                <ReplyBody>In America it's more expensive, not necessarily other countries like Malaysia or China. 
 </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwcg1m</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>12</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think that idea is that if a state doesn't value human life enough to preserve it even when someone commits a horrible crime then they shouldn't be trying to preserve it when someone is in pain and dying.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvsx5v</id>
            <upvotes>9</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; There will be devil's advocates when this is how you present your argument. 

Okay fine. Then theoretically, if a person wanted to kill themselves enough that he is willing to commit a horrible crime to receive the death penalty, what then assuming no one knows that that person is willing to?

&amp;gt; There are reasons why a nation would have the death penalty on the table that are completely independent from whether or not helping someone else kill themselves should be legal.

Please specify.


</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvjqjx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>thesorehead</author>
                <ReplyBody>Without meaning to step on /u/workinglol's toes, the basic reasoning comes down to the use of State-committed/sanctioned violence.  
  
State-sanctioned violence is supposed to be reserved for those individuals and groups that threaten the State in some way. Criminals, aggressor nations, terrorists etc. We have a long tradition of very high standards for a finding of guilt, such is our opposition to the violence (coercion really) of imprisonment. Police are rightly vilified when they overstep their bounds - so much so that it is hard for their own voices to be heard when the public makes assumptions about their behaviour before having all the facts. The point is that the State exists to protect citizens from harm. The death penalty is very cautiously applied because of its permanence and because this ultimate harm to an individual has to be justified against the interests of the State.
  

If you're healthy and you genuinely want to end it, there are hundreds of options that don't require State assistance. Most of them are ugly and messy, but what the hell do you care? Euthanasia is really only worth discussing in the realm of assisted suicide, where someone who is terminally ill or infirm in some way wants to end their life but is unable to do it themselves. In these scenarios the main question is whether or not State-sanctioned violence can be justified against someone who has not harmed or threatened the State. There are also very important ethical concerns, especially for the mentally infirm.

  
So the two things really aren't connected. I don't think it's necessary to go through the reasoning in it's entirety because this CMV is not about whether euthanasia is a good idea but rather that the existence of a death penalty in a given State indicates something about the value of human life which should be reflected by euthanasia laws. I personally think that euthanasia should be an option in certain circumstances, but it has zero connection with the death penalty. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvkozm</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>hikikomori911</author>
                    <ReplyBody>This whole response very nearly convinced me to CMV. But after I read it several times, when these two sentences that you wrote are next to each other, they stood out:

&amp;gt; We have a long tradition of very high standards for a finding of guilt, such is our opposition to the violence (coercion really) of imprisonment. 

and 

&amp;gt; The point is that the State exists to protect citizens from harm. 

I find this first statement questionable. If there are "very high standards for finding guilt", why is it then that [DNA evidence exonerates 300th prisoner nationwide](http://articles.latimes.com/2012/oct/01/nation/la-na-dna-evidence-20121001)? That means 300 people who were sentenced to the death penalty just in the US alone were found to actually be not guilty of the crime they were found guilty of.

When I understand that, the second statement becomes somewhat contradictory. I do think the state exists to protect the citizens; or at least that is its intention. However, the state exists to protect the state from harm first and foremost before it exists to protect citizens from harm. 

I can justify the rationale that euthanasia should be made illegal in states that bans the death penalty as it is logically consistent. However I can't buy it when it comes to countries/states with the death penalty. 

You say:

&amp;gt; Police are rightly vilified when they overstep their bounds

The bounds for places that legalize the death penalty then is broad. The bounds include the fact that it is okay to kill a living human being who has committed a crime. So therefore killing people under certain circumstances rather than rehabilitating them is okay in this particular place. If so then it is only logically consistent to allow euthanasia in a state that allows the death penalty if the death penalty is already justified to be in the bounds of its laws.

&amp;gt; If you're healthy and you genuinely want to end it, there are hundreds of options that don't require State assistance. 

That's the thing. It should be officially allowed by the state that allows the death penalty so that the person trying to commit suicide isn't put in prison for failed attempts. I reason it this way because I am aware that the state can choose three things: to help the person through rehabilitation, punish the person, or do nothing. In places which legalizes the death penalty, in most cases, the person who attempted a failed suicide is punished. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvl8d8</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>thesorehead</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I have tried to crystallise the purposes and rationales that are most relevant - naturally there are other reasons for the State to exist, and failures of justice in the making, application and routine practice of the law. My point was really that the two things are not connected.  
  
The rationale for euthanasia centres around a person's right to self-determination. Advocates usually reason that they seek to have the State restore the choice to die to those who no longer have that option. They will also bring up that prolonging lives that do not want to be prolonged is a cost to the State, but they are always side points. The disagreement surrounding euthanasia is largely about whether and how such a system would be abused - greedy beneficiaries or con-men convincing Granny to die early for their own gain; the mentally infirm being unaware of what they are agreeing to, or unable to express themselves; psychopath doctors pushing death as the best solution to patients who are in a vulnerable position. The interests of the State barely rate a mention.
  
The considerations re: capital punishment are completely different. They are entirely concerned with the State's interests and responsibilities.  
  
I guess what I'm trying to get at here is that your premise is flawed. Justifying putting someone to death in one circumstance does not mean the same arguments can apply in another. Surgeons are not (usually) prosecuted if a patient dies on their table. IANAL but in most places (including those without a death penalty :P) self-defence is also a defence for ending someone's life. These are two scenarios where a person's death at the hand of another is excusable by the State, and each of them uses vastly different reasoning to each other, and to that which applies to the death penalty. If you accept that this is true, then I think you have to consider the possibility that completely separate reasoning could apply to euthanasia as well.  
  
I'm not going to try to convince you that States with a death penalty should or should not have euthanasia. I'm trying to say that the two are nowhere near as connected as you think, so you should reconsider your starting point.   
  
:)</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvm9nx</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hikikomori911</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The disagreement surrounding euthanasia is largely about whether and how such a system would be abused 

I have to admit, so far you always come close to convincing me to CMV. However, just because a system can be abused, that doesn't mean it shouldn't be implemented. Especially if, as I have said, there is plenty of abuse with the death penalty; and a sizeable amount of people who were sentenced to death were later found to be innocent. 

Remember, we are talking about places that legalize the death penalty and continue to use it. They obviously don't care that much that innocent people are being killed by the death penalty as they have not yet removed the death penalty. 

If a society understands that the death penalty can be abused, and has been many times and yet still decides the death penalty is justified, abuse that can occur with euthanasia in said society should be irrelevant using the same logic for justifying the death penalty as the death of innocent people via death penalty does not deter said society from implementing the death penalty.

Also, I know the death penalty and euthanasia are two different things. But they are still very much related as they both are about officially ending a person's life legally.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvqejo</id>
                            <replies>
<author>markedConundrum</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Remember, we are talking about places that legalize the death penalty and continue to use it. They obviously don't care that much that innocent people are being killed by the death penalty as they have not yet removed the death penalty. 

But that's not necessarily the case.  Ask yourself:  why do the people in those places think the death penalty is a reasonable thing to institute and practice?  Why do they have safeguards?  If they don't care much for the possibility of someone innocent being executed, then why do they have such a huge barrier to execution?  How much money do criminals spend as they work their way through the death row appeals process?  Would it not be simpler for the process to be easier?  The people who live in those places care a great deal, which is why the death penalty can take around two decades to actually be implemented.  The whole idea behind the caution is to avoid executing innocent people.

You're dealing with two entirely different types of people.  One is regarded as a horrific threat to the populace because that person murdered a thousand kids, and the other is suffering in the last throes of illness.  You decide to kill both of them, and you have to explain to your peers and their respective families, why you did it.  Are you really saying that you would give both parties the same explanation, "They had to die," and that the difference in how you got to that conclusion for both individuals is irrelevant?

The conclusion, yes, is the same, but the *rationale* is different.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvsuzj</id>
<replies>
    <author>hikikomori911</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Ask yourself: why do the people in those places think the death penalty is a reasonable thing to institute and practice?

I've thought about this before. [both the Islamic religion and the Christian religion as well as other common religions strongly denounce suicide](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious_views_on_suicide). 

I find that when I compare the countries that still have death penalties, they are usually very religiously inclined and my guess is that religion has a major influence.

&amp;gt;  If they don't care much for the possibility of someone innocent being executed, then why do they have such a huge barrier to execution? 

They do to a certain extent, but not enough to make sure that no one who is innocent gets on death row. Maybe I can excuse it if it was 2 wrong executions every 50-100 years. But hundreds of people die innocent on the death penalty and are still being exonerated to this day.

&amp;gt;  How much money do criminals spend as they work their way through the death row appeals process?

Well killing people through state sanction is expensive in and of itself. Instead of that question, we should ask "why not use that money to rehabilitate rather than to kill?" But these people really prefer retribution over rehabilitation. I don't know why for sure, but I will guess that it stems from religious origin.

&amp;gt; The conclusion, yes, is the same, but the rationale is different.

Oh okay. I can get behind the fact that there are unique reasonings that can apply to the legaization of the death penalty that can't apply to the legalization of euthanasia and vice verca. i didn't deny or explicitly make a statement regarding this (i think?) so sorry for the confusion.

&amp;gt;  You decide to kill both of them

Actually no. People on the death penalty have to take death. There is no two ways around it. People who want euthanasia will have to decide on their own if they want it and they will have to meet all the stringent requirements by themselves.

I didn't say the state would have to necessarily administer the euthanasia, I'm saying that the state should legalize euthanasia. It is up to the individual to go about doing it and providing the funds necessary to do so.

</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckvtf4k</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hikikomori911</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I actually typed up a very good response but for some reason it didn't post so I'm not typing it all again so I'm just simplifying my reasoning. If you require further explanation please ask.

&amp;gt;  The disagreement surrounding euthanasia is largely about whether and how such a system would be abused

Like last time, this came very close to CMV. The problem is places that legalize the death penalty already know that innocent people are being killed via death penalty who are later found to be innocent.

This means that said society thinks that despite the fact that innocent people are killed by the death penalty, it is still worth having. Therefore, if innocent people being killed by the death penalty doesn't deter said places from having the death penalty in the first place, they should have no problem with the fact that euthanasia can be abused. 

In other words, their logic for continuing to implement the death penalty is "well, a few innocent people might be killed, but that's just a small amount compared to the amount of people we've punished." Remember, this is considering that this same authority that implements the death penalty can also choose to rehabilitate these members of society but chooses not to in favor of killing them.

Finally, I am aware that the death penalty and euthanasia are two different things. But on this particular issue, I think they intertwine because they are both about ending human lives by making it acceptable to society by legalizing it. 

I hope this is posted, because I am not typing this up again.

**Edit:** apparently, it just took an extra few minutes for the post to be added. Oh well. I'm leaving this up here to show that I actually wrote another response because the other post didn't show for quite a long time.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvqmxh</id>
                            <replies>
<author>thesorehead</author>
<ReplyBody>well, I'm glad I came close anyway :). I think where you and I disagree fundamentally is how important the difference is between one type of legal death-causing and another. I think we even agree that euthanasia is actually a good idea (although no doubt we each disagree on how/when it should be made available).  
  
You offered further explanation, so if I may: what do you have to say about the other two examples I gave, namely surgeons and self-defence? I pointed them out because your view seems to centre around the idea that if one form of legal killing is OK, then another form should be OK. As I said surgical complications and self-defence are both socially accepted legal defences when someone dies by the action or inaction of another. By your logic, it should follow that euthanasia should be allowed in all jurisdictions where this is the case, but I think that very idea is flawed as it compares two things that can't really be compared.  
  
Glad to have almost CYV, maybe you can make your view clearer for the next person :P</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvupkf</id>
<replies>
    <author>hikikomori911</author>
    <ReplyBody>Thanks! I sure enjoyed our conversation too.

For the surgeon: it depends on how clear cut the evidence is. But generally no. It would just deter surgeons from undergoing risky procedures ever and the person undergoing the surgery has probably already consented that she will be at a minimal risk of dying.

About self-defence, I don't know what I could add to that other than sure: they are vastly different reasoning but they are both very much justified.

&amp;gt; By your logic, it should follow that euthanasia should be allowed in all jurisdictions where this is the case...

I think after reading your explanations several times I'm sort of seeing where you're going with how it can be unfair to put a blanket viewpoint on a complex issue as euthanasia.

But once again, to me the point is moot when you consider the death penalty. There is no such thing as "murdering someone by stabbing them because that person who was stabbed wanted to or asked for it". By law, that murder is a murder. A surgeon who accidentally kills a woman who consents that she might risk death by undergoing a procedure is not murder because the woman gave wilful consent under no threat. So the surgeon who accidentally causes the death of a woman bearing a child that consents that she could be killed by the operation is not considered a murderer under the law.

It's actually clear cut for a reason. Euthanasia isn't murder if the person wanting to die gives consent under no threat. And this can obviously be one such requirement: that you must consent to death for X amount of time and it will be investigated that you are not under any direct threat, etc. 

This probably doesn't exactly justify euthanasia worldwide, but it certainly justifies it for places that already allow the death penalty.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckvwfuj</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>The point here isn't to argue the merits of euthanasia and the merits of the death penalty. Your view is that a state which has the death penalty *must also* have euthanasia if it is to be fair.

Euthanasia and the death penalty are two separate issues.

The argument pro-euthanasia involves ending suffering and individual liberty (choice)

The argument anti-euthanasia involves the sanctity of life, and in your examples the validity of choice when it involves ending one's life (are they depressed and can be helped? Are they homeless and can be helped in other ways that do not involve death?)

The argument pro-death penalty is punishment and deterrence. You are a bad person, you have done evil things, you should not live.

The argument anti-death penalty is the authority of the state to kill its own citizens, and the imperfection of any justice system.

While certain points of the pro and anti groups do intersect (sanctity of life), one is not necessarily contradicting themselves if they are anti-euthanasia and pro-death penalty.

For example: I may be pro-death penalty because I believe some crimes and so heinous that they warrant death. I might believe an individual who commits those crimes has forfeited their right to life.

I may also be anti-euthanasia because I believe assisting an innocent person in suicide is wrong (even through indirect assistance, such as providing drugs). I may believe innocent life is sacred and should be preserved at all costs.

You mentioned 'what if a person commits a death penalty offense as a loophole.' That would be irrelevant to me in this example - whatever the reasons for them committing the crime, they are guilty and should be punished accordingly.  </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvmyd4</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hikikomori911</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I understand that euthanasia and the death penalty are two separate issues, but I also know that they are closely related to each other as they are both about ending human life.

Typically, in a society that justifies the death penalty, they are literally saying, "Hey, we can totally attempt rehabilitation to bring you back as a productive member of society. But we think what you did was so horrible, we want to kill you for it." 

This is a form of retribution. It is deliberately choosing retribution over rehabilitation even though rehabilitation can be attempted. I'm saying that if a society does not mind killing a person through legal processes justified by retribution for committing a crime, this same society should then allow a person to kill themselves because it is clear that even though this society has the ability to help the person, they are unwilling to help them (rehabilitation) and would rather just kill him (retribution). 

A society that justifies retribution via death penalty shouldn't have a problem with same logic applied to biologically healthy citizens if they are unwilling to provide satisfactory social structures to help people who for various reasons don't want to live anymore.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvq62e</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>The connection between the two issues can still be broken and be logically sound. It could be that someone values retribution/justice over the sanctity of life, but still has high regard for the sanctity of life and only justifies ending life when absolutely necessary (And absolutely necessary for them would include retribution, or for what they deem un-rehabiliatable criminals).

Again I'm not arguing the pros or cons of any position, I'm saying that holding opposing positions on these issues together is not necessarily inconsistent. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvqipo</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>markedConundrum</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Even the state makes mistakes.  Having a flawed process doesn't imply the state hasn't been trying to adhere to high standards.  And making mistakes doesn't mean the state thinks that making those mistakes is ok.  This is why we improve the process:  so that we can better follow those lofty values we've set for ourselves.

And you're totally ignoring the specific criteria under which killing someone for a crime is legal.  Those certain circumstances are why we look at killing a criminal and killing a beleaguered citizen as different propositions.  An action is not necessarily justified for other reasons just because it's justified for a few.

A person who attempts suicide is rarely punished and often put through rehabilitation and counseling.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvsiip</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Grahammophone</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Woahwoahwoah. Where are you that they put suicidal people in prison? I'm not aware of any government (at least within the western world) where people can be incarcerated for a failed suicide attempt.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvttmw</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>22</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>lotu</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Okay fine. Then theoretically, if a person wanted to kill themselves enough that he is willing to commit a horrible crime to receive the death penalty, what then assuming no one knows that that person is willing to?

Are you really suggesting that there exist, even it theory, mentally stable people who would be willing to commit multiple murders, in a decade long ploy to receive the death penalty that would also be unwilling to kill themselves in a conventional fashion.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvnc5v</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>celticguy08</author>
            <ReplyBody>It's interesting how the replies to your comment seem to have dichotomized into the two arguments you specified.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvun4n</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>cloakingdevice</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; or just saves money compared to life in prison.

[Erm, what?](http://www.forbes.com/sites/kellyphillipserb/2011/09/22/death-and-taxes-the-real-cost-of-the-death-penalty/)</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckw6ttd</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>If you check out the rest of the thread, the "Execution is cheaper -&amp;gt; Not in the US -&amp;gt; we're not just talking about the US" exchange has already happened a few times. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwd46f</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>smestad1</author>
            <ReplyBody>Death penalty is in fact a good bunch more expensive than a lifetime in jail because of the judicial process that has to be made before someone ever gets sentenced to death.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cl2shia</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>This point has been discussed half a dozen times in this thread, and is only relevant to the US justice system. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cl3kman</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>cleantoe</author>
            <ReplyBody>There is [no evidence](http://www.amnestyusa.org/our-work/issues/death-penalty/us-death-penalty-facts/the-death-penalty-and-deterrence) that the death penalty acts as a deterrent to crime. It actually has to do more with ideological beliefs, like how owning firearms [deters crime](http://www.theguardian.com/science/blog/2013/mar/25/guns-protection-national-rifle-association) (hint: It increases the likelihood of the owner getting shot), or [how men think they know](http://www.gallup.com/poll/170249/split-abortion-pro-choice-pro-life.aspx) what's [best for a woman's body](https://www.govtrack.us/congress/bills/subjects/abortion/5897).</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckw6nik</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>123456seven89</author>
            <ReplyBody>It would be foolish to have the death penalty to save money since it's way more expensive than keeping someone in prison for life. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvpimx</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Deku-shrub</author>
                <ReplyBody>In the US yes, not China AFAIK</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvtc25</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvthus</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>123456seven89</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The court costs for death row inmates is super high. Idk specifics. google it. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvux0f</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>103</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Shadoe17</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Just on Reddit alone there are many people wishing they could just end it. They have not committed any crimes but they don't really enjoy living, so why not allow them to end it if they so desire?

These are cries for help, not true desires to end it. Killing yourself is one of the easiest things to do, if that is really what you want to do. 

Also you are very expressive about "biologically healthy", what about their mental health? Wouldn't they need to be mentally healthy to make that decision? We don't allow mentally ill to be put to death in our legal system, so this would fall inline with your theory. Depression is a mental health issue, therefore it would preclude those people from being "allowed" to die by their own hands. Most people that recover from depression will tell you that they are glad they didn't do something foolish (suicide) because the world can be better once they get the help they need. 

People that are mentally healthy rarely, if ever, truly want to commit suicide. Our natural instincts push us in the other direction, survival. So, unless you are advocating euthanasia for the mentally ill, your original question has no merit, or at least no takers.
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvk9pw</id>
        <replies>
            <author>ArtifexR</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Killing yourself is one of the easiest things to do, if that is really what you want to do. 

I don't think that's really the case. Many methods are dangerous and potentially extremely painful in the process. If you fail or mess up, you could end up crippled, in chronic pain with no way to escape an even worse life than you had before. In addition, there can be unintended consequences from suicide: jumping in front of a car could kill the passengers, killing yourself can send friends and family into their own spirals of depression, and sometimes there are even legal consequences. 

If it was as simple as "take this prescription pill to end it all," then yes, that would be easy. That's illegal, though. Instead, you have to have the balls to put a gun into your mouth and pull the trigger, slit your wrists, hang yourself, down a mishmash of dangerous medicine and hope it's enough, etc.

I'm not advocating for suicide here, just trying to point out that it's not "easy."</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvwapx</id>
            <upvotes>12</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>howbigis1gb</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think whether people truly want to kill themselves is not of particular importance when it comes to the legality of euthanasia. It is pertinent when administering it. 

This does not mean that people who want to commit suicide can walk into a store and have someone euthanise them. 

/r/suicidewatch will do their work just as before. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvlth9</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Shadoe17</author>
                <ReplyBody>Speaking from a strictly legal standpoint, suicide is murder in the first degree, which is illegal in every state. The death penalty is the only exception, which requires that a jury of 12 people deliberate on the facts to decide if the crime is heinous enough, and the person so far beyond rehabilitation, to deserve the death penalty. How would you suppose to put this level of scrutiny on suicide? You must determine first if the person is even mentally capable of being put to the test, a determination which they will almost certainly always fail.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvnboz</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>howbigis1gb</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I mean - is the discussion about legality pertinent when we are discussing whether the law is to be amended?

How would you decide if someone is mentally competent and capable of determining if they want to die? 

I assume an ethics board would oversee the determination of this, and in places where euthanasia is legal there exist exactly the safeguards you speak of. 

Yes you are correct that it is a hard determination to make, but that doesn't mean it is something that it is an opportunity that ought to be denied. 
</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvnhrt</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Shadoe17</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Again, I believe the concept is clear. Euthanasia is the taking of a life, not in self defense or the defense of others. It is therefore murder. The death penalty is considered to be in defense of others based on the convicted's past record and the overwhelming evidence that they cannot be rehabilitated, and will therefore offend again if ever they should be free to do so. (I don't believe being convicted of treason should carry this punishment)

Should laws be amended to allow one type of murder? I don't believe so. If they were, should they require the same scrutiny as the death penalty? I do believe so. 

So if euthanasia were legal under the existing framework, a person would have to prove mental fitness to make that decision, then stand before a jury of 12 of their peers an show that there was no other option, as their life could never get better. Can you imagine what a waste of time that would be, as no one could pass the mental health test, and even if they did they couldn't convince 12 people that nothing could ever make their life worth living. 


&amp;gt;Yes you are correct that it is a hard determination to make, but that doesn't mean it is something that it is an opportunity that ought to be denied. 

Yes. Sometimes common sense should win out over pure logic when it comes to making laws. To make a law where the bar is so high that no one will ever pass it is a waste of time and the tax payers money.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvoy68</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>howbigis1gb</author>
                            <ReplyBody>By your definition no one in confinement should ever be executed if they can just indefinitely be contained. 

How is killing them defending anyone?

However I think most people would not equate euthanasia with murder just because the law may do so. 

The death penalty and euthanasia are sufficiently different that they can be treated differently. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvqbkp</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Shadoe17</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; By your definition no one in confinement should ever be executed if they can just indefinitely be contained. 

But they can't always be indefinitely contained.

&amp;gt;How is killing them defending anyone?

It is defending future victims. If it has been determined that they will re-offended, then it is the only way of guaranteeing that they can't get free to commit another crime.

&amp;gt;However I think most people would not equate euthanasia with murder just because the law may do so. 

But that is what we are discussing here, the law.

&amp;gt;The death penalty and euthanasia are sufficiently different that they can be treated differently.

True, and they are. Death penalty is a last resort for repeat offenders that it has been determined there is no hope of rehabilitating. Euthanasia is murder.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvrdbn</id>
<replies>
    <author>howbigis1gb</author>
    <ReplyBody>I think you are convinced that Euthanasia is murder, and most people would disagree. Euthanasia includes an element of consent which is notably absent in murder. 

&amp;gt;But they can't always be indefinitely contained.

&amp;gt;It is defending future victims. If it has been determined that they will re-offended, then it is the only way of guaranteeing that they can't get free to commit another crime.

We don't live in a comic book universe that people break out of prison every day. We can and do indefinitely contain people. We call it life imprisonment. 

Furthermore it seems like you are suggesting that we eschew trying to contain prisoners and execute them instead, which seems like a pretty scary idea to me. 

People aren't sentenced to death because their captors are afraid they can't be held. 

Even if we are discussing the law, it is not pertinent to discuss what it is when discussing how it *ought* to be.

</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckvs40b</id>
    <upvotes>6</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>10</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; These are cries for help, not true desires to end it. Killing yourself is one of the easiest things to do, if that is really what you want to do.

Sure that's debatable but it's also a strawman over the actual debate.

&amp;gt; Also you are very expressive about "biologically healthy", what about their mental health? 

This is to put it in context: because a lot of places which already legalizes euthanasia only allow euthanasia for those with crippling health problems and I think that euthanasia should be legalized for any adult person who so chooses who is a citizen of a place that legalizes the death penalty; with stringent rules and requirements, of course.

&amp;gt; People that are mentally healthy rarely, if ever, truly want to commit suicide.

I don't think anyone truly wants to commit suicide. People want to commit suicide because of situations in their life that they hate. A person with crippling health problems would probably not want to commit suicide if he didn't have crippling health problems. Same goes for depressive people: depressive people wouldn't want to commit suicide if they didn't have depression. But then again, they do have these issues and they feel like society hasn't been able to adequately help them nor are they able to get adequate help. 

If they feel that way in a society that already allows the death penalty, what is wrong with that? That society has deemed killing another "biologically" healthy human being as acceptable so long as that individual has broken a serious enough crime, regardless of whether that individual has learnt from his mistakes or regrets it or has family members he needs to look after. So in context, it's justifiable.

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvkpy2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Shadoe17</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; with stringent rules and requirements, of course.

Would one of those rules be that the person is mentally capable of making that decision? If so you have ended your own argument. 

&amp;gt;I don't think anyone truly wants to commit suicide.

So if no one wants to commit suicide, only those that aren't mentally sound would opt to do so, and if being mentally healthy is one of the requirements, then no one would ever qualify for this euthanasia allowance. 

Again, anyone that really wants to commit suicide can, the laws only kick in after the fact, which is too late to be of any use. The one thing they can't do is have someone assist them, but that is an entirely different debate.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvl8q9</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>hikikomori911</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; So if no one wants to commit suicide, 

People are driven to commit suicide by different things: money issues, health problems (both mental and physical), family issues, etc. 

The state has three choices when dealing with people who attempts to suicide: they can attempt to rehabilitate the person, punish the person, or they can do nothing. In states/countries that allow the death penalty, they mostly decide to punish the person by sending the person to jail or to an expensive private mental health facility that saddles them with crippling debt. 

Either way, they are not helping the person. If a place decides death is a suitable punishment for someone who has committed a horrible enough crime, they should allow people who have not broken the law to have the option if they so desire if the state is unwilling to provide suitable rehabilitation in the first place? I do not consider confinement in prison as rehabilitation.

</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvljrs</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Shadoe17</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; People are driven to commit suicide by different things: money issues, health problems (both mental and physical), family issues, etc. 

One of those issues goes against your original question, health issues, so we must disregard that entirely. Other issues mentioned all are leading causes of depression, which is a mental issue, so again I ask, are you advocating euthanasia for the mentally handicapped?

&amp;gt;In states/countries that allow the death penalty, they mostly decide to punish the person by sending the person to jail or to an expensive private mental health facility that saddles them with crippling debt. 

I can only speak for my own country, but I've never heard of anyone sent to jail for attempted suicide, even though it is illegal, because in every case a mental health related issue has been found to be to blame. And if they are found to be a danger to themselves, due to mental health issues, they are placed in a hospital at the states expense, not theirs, until the situation can be corrected. 

&amp;gt;Either way, they are not helping the person.

Assuming you were correct, death isn't helping them either, so this is a non-starter.

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvn5c5</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>[deleted]</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; are you advocating euthanasia for the mentally handicapped?

I can't speak on OP's behalf, but the answer to this should emphatically be *yes*. The mentally ill, just like everyone else, should have the option to kill themselves, if they choose. And doctors should be permitted to assist in the suicide to make it as painless and dignified as possible. Just because someone is mentally ill, doesn't mean they lack rationality or the ability to make informed decisions. Severe depression for example isn't an absence of rationality, it's living in a perpetual state of torture. Someone who has been severely depressed for decades on end, who has tried every available treatment (or ran out of money), and who is still perpetually miserable would be completely rational in wanting to die to escape the pain. What right does the state have to intervene, forcing them to suffer against their wishes?

The OP is essentially correct in pointing out the absurdity of a state whose justice system is the only authority permitted to kill any of its citizens.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvot8h</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Shadoe17</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; And doctors should be permitted to assist in the suicide to make it as painless and dignified as possible.

As I said above, assisted suicide is a totally different debate.

&amp;gt;Just because someone is mentally ill, doesn't mean they lack rationality or the ability to make informed decisions.

Umm, Yes, actually that is exactly what it means.

&amp;gt;Severe depression for example isn't an absence of rationality,

After living with someone for 25 years that is severely depressed and bi-polar I can honestly say that yes, while in a state of depression you are incapable of making rational decisions. 

You are one that believes that the state determines who will live or die under the death penalty. This is an incorrect assumption, it is a jury of 12 men and women, gathered from the community, that listen to the facts, consider the offenders history, and make the determination. The state only sets forth guidelines to limit the action of the jury to consider this only in the most extreme cases.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvp7pi</id>
<replies>
    <author>[deleted]</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; After living with someone for 25 years that is severely depressed...

Quoting anecdotal evidence is a waste of everyone's time. Obviously, some depressed people aren't rational, but some are...just like the rest of the population. That has nothing to do with the illness itself. I could list off dozens of examples of severely depressed individuals who can think very clearly (Stephen Fry, Thom Yorke, Aaron Schwartz, Sia, Christopher Hitchens, etc, etc) but it would prove nothing.

&amp;gt; Umm, Yes, actually that is exactly what it means.

So, basically, you disagree with the [DSM's definition of depression](http://www.psnpaloalto.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2010/12/Depression-Diagnostic-Criteria-and-Severity-Rating.pdf) then? Nothing on that list of criteria says "is incapable of thinking rationally." 

&amp;gt;  it is a jury of 12 men and women, gathered from the community...

So what's your point? It's up to the state to determine whether or not the jury is allowed to choose death as a punishment, but that doesn't affect my previous point one way or the other. 

Again, what right does the state and/or the jury have to intervene if someone decides rationally, that they want to die? It's a decision that people can make rationally, and its a decision that they do make rationally all the time. People who enjoy nothing and are constantly miserable are rational in wanting to die.  </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckvqe2p</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hikikomori911</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; so again I ask, are you advocating euthanasia for the mentally handicapped?

Provided the society isn't willing to, on a societal level recognize and help rehabilitate the problem, and this same society legalizes the death penalty, and the person is a legalized adult (according to society), yes. Because to just allow the person to endlessly suffer until death even though the person has consented and not wanting to live is wrong when you consider that the society which institutes the death penalty is already willing to take the retribution stance on criminals. 

If the retribution stance is justified for criminals and there is no rehabilitation structure in society that can be reasonably accessed, then yes.

&amp;gt; 

You can [search Wikipedia](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suicide_legislation) and see that there are countries that will imprison you if you attempt suicide. Also, even for countries that have decriminalized suicide, you are forced to get help, usually through privatized mental health facilities that cause you to go into crippling debt and ruin your life as a normal citizen anyway. 

&amp;gt; Assuming you were correct, death isn't helping them either, so

You are making it easier for them to end it. Remember, the context is, the society in question allows retribution (death penalty) for criminals meaning this particular society already allows revenge killing ("you killed someone, so therefore, you must die") when rehabilitation is an option. 

</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvp75h</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Shadoe17</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Provided the society isn't willing to, on a societal level recognize and help rehabilitate the problem, and this same society legalizes the death penalty, and the person is a legalized adult (according to society),

Ah, now come out the endless list of caviots. Typical of someone that has backed into a corner but doesn't want to admit their original premise was flawed.

&amp;gt;retribution stance is justified for criminals

It is not a retributive stance, it is a stand of defense of others. Only when a person is deemed beyond rehabilitation can the death penalty be brought in. This means that the jury must be convinced that if this person is ever freed that they will kill again. 

The last two paragraphs have already been covered, I can only speak for my country as I don't know the laws in other countries. And you are again adding more stipulations to the debate in order to change the course. In the USA if you are found mentally deficient the state pays for your treatment unless you choose to use private healthcare and provide some means of payment.

</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvpjo2</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>hyene</author>
            <ReplyBody>most people kill themselves because they can't stand living in and being part of an unhealthy global culture where hundreds of millions of people are being beaten, murdered, robbed, raped, and tortured every day. it's not a mental health problem, it's a *social* health problem. some people kill themselves because they are in unbearable, incurable physical pain. that's not a mental health problem, it's a physiological problem. some people kill themselves because they are old and close to death anyway and simply want peace of mind, and to say goodbye to all of their friends and family before they degenerate to babbling adult infants. that's not a mental health problem, it's a geriatric problem.

most people i know who have confided in me (and my own feelings on the subject as well in my darkest moments) that they have thought about or want to kill themselves *not* because they're crazy but because they're sick to death of all the violence, pain, and misery they're exposed to any day. and this is in canada, one of the best countries in the world.

the people we really need to worry about aren't the ones who - of their own volition, as sole owners of their bodies - want to end their lives peacefully and without pain. we need to worry about people who are both suicidal and so angry at the world because of the violence, despair, and oppression they have experienced that they desire revenge or retribution.

The only argument that can be made, really, is that we should prevent otherwise healthy people from killing themselves because we are all actively making an effort to create a better global society and culture, and that if they just hold on a few more years it's going to get better. because, historically, it really is getting better. global society, i mean. (or at least that's what i tell myself to get me through).
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvqzzl</id>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>24</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Moofishmoo</author>
        <ReplyBody>Death is something you can't come back from. There is no room for regret when it comes to death. Yet a lot of people who have had suicide attempts and almost die, are glad they're alive when we resuscitate them at hospital. 

     especially considering society doesn't actually care enough about the well being of these people who want to kill themselves: the homeless, people who are depressed, those in poverty and those who just don't find any meaning in their lives, etc.

Really? You think homeless people want to die? You think depressed people are the right mind to determine if they want to do something that permanent? You think poor people, strive to find work and to eat everyday because they want to die??? 

Too many people in today's society, go through periods of depression, where they might want to die. If suicide was as easy as 'Oh I will sign a form' then many people would be dead, even if they would have had a perfectly happy fore filling life if they hadn't. But they can't go back on death. They can't regret their decisions and choose all over again. If you made it that easy they would simply just die. It's equivalent to saying 'Oh I broke my leg, well better just die'. 

The current cost to raise a kid properly to the age of 18 is about a million bucks. Literally a million dollars. Can you imagine just signing a form and deleting a million dollars? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvk7xd</id>
        <replies>
            <author>ArtifexR</author>
            <ReplyBody>What you're arguing for, though, is that we shouldn't have control over the most basic aspect of our own lives: whether we're alive or not and want to continue to experience life. If someone is chronically ill, causing their family personal and emotional expenses, and doesn't feel like dying a slow death or ending up half-brain dead and locked up in an old folks home, is it really that offensive that they want to exit life on their own terms? </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvwd9a</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckw7l01</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>ZirunK6AUrg</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; It's not like you can arrest someone for dying.

You *can* arrest someone for helping another person die (killing them, in other words), even if it's what that person wishes. The last thing a chronically ill person is likely to want is for their attempt to end the suffering of their loved ones only cause more suffering. The legality of assisted suicide most certainly matters.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckw96r3</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>ArtifexR</author>
                    <ReplyBody>In addition to what the other commenter said - you can also impose strict legal and financial consequences for their family as a strong deterrent. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckwyo8l</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>6</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>TargetTango</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; The current cost to raise a kid properly to the age of 18 is about a million bucks. Literally a million dollars. Can you imagine just signing a form and deleting a million dollars? 

That's a very terrible way of looking at things. So you should be forced to stay alive only because of the financial implications. You have to carry a debt that you never agreed to sign? People are easily replaceable on an economic and financial standpoint. Look at the unemployment rates, for every job opening there are hundreds of fully qualified people who can take that job. And that's just unemployed, take all people and there are millions of people who can take that job. Not to mention in 20 years or so, most of the jobs today will be automated.

People fall through the cracks all the time. Some die as babies, other die as children from cancer, young adults are murdered and die in car accidents. It's the fact of life. Money is wasted all the time. 1 million dollars is nothing compared to an economy of 17 trillion. Many people default over their debt, declare bankruptcy and sometimes companies end up losing money. But on the whole, one debt or loan means nothing to a multinational bank who controls millions of loans which most of them will be paid back. The same way 1 person does not matter in a nation of 320 million. If the nation loses one person, oh well, it happens all the time. The same way a bank is not going to go belly-up if one person defaults on their mortgage. 

And what about the person being executed? Don't your arguments not apply to them? Do you think prisoners want to die?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvwexf</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not talking about societies that have banned the death penalty. It makes sense that euthanasia is banned from a society that does not allow the death penalty.

I'm talking about societies that have the death penalty but bans euthanasia.

&amp;gt; If suicide was as easy as 'Oh I will sign a form'

That's not even how euthanasia for people in crippling physical pain works in today's world. There are many stringent laws, fees and procedures that the person would still have to go through.

So the laws could be even more stringent for a biologically healthy individuals to legally be allowed to do euthanasia. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvkebl</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Moofishmoo</author>
                <ReplyBody>Right and who would pay for those stringent laws, fees and procedures? Do you really think a homeless person/depressed/poor people can afford that? Do you think any country is going to happily go, oh yeah we're gonna fork out $40k to euthanize this person that society as a whole paid a million dollars to raise? America has the death penalty because these people have done such bad deeds that they are deemed no longer fit to remain in society and deemed to be a danger to society. Of course society would want to pay to have them removed. But why would society want to pay to allow someone they've invested a million dollars into... but just who had a mental illness that caused a chemical imbalance in their brain to just abort themselves? While at the same time, paying even more for the laws, fees and procedures that the person would have to go through? </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvkwnd</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>i_lack_imagination</author>
                    <ReplyBody>So the real defense you are arguing here has nothing to do with mental capabilities, its entirely to do with financial reasons. Arguably, if society invested this money in people, they invested poorly and fucked up and now that person isn't capable of returning society's investment. So instead of just admitting society fucked up, society just wants to hold them hostage and attempt to force them to make the money back that was invested in them.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckw871m</id>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>hikikomori911</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Legalized euthanasia is already pretty stringent, and I don't think any government pays for it. The government just sets the rules: whether it is legal or illegal and what requirements must be followed. 

&amp;gt; Of course society would want to pay to have them removed.

That's kind of twisted - that society is willing to pay to have horrible people removed but not willing to help certain troubled people that needs help - that is of course, assuming euthanasia is government funded, which it probably won't be in the first place. 

&amp;gt; Do you really think a homeless person/depressed/poor people can afford that?

If people can't afford it, then they simple don't have that option to die legally. But people will still do it if they want to badly enough.

&amp;gt; why would society want to pay to allow someone they've invested a million dollars into... but just who had a mental illness that caused a chemical imbalance in their brain to just abort themselves? While at the same time, paying even more for the laws, fees and procedures that the person would have to go through?

Well, I could also ask why places that legalize the death penalty want to spend all that money killing a person (the death penalty is expensive) when they could otherwise spend that money rehabilitating the person to become a productive member of society. But that would be off on a tangent. I am not talking about the state/country administrating the actual process of euthanasia for citizens. I'm talking about the state/country legalizing it so that people who have not committed crimes have the options to do so if they so want.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvlvlq</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>qtj</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Well, I could also ask why places that legalize the death penalty want to 
spend all that money killing a person (the death penalty is expensive) &amp;gt;when they could otherwise spend that money rehabilitating the person to become a productive member of society.

But the death penalty is only an option for people that have shown that they can't be rehabilitated anymore.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvu0xb</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>IronicButterfly</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Death is something you can't come back from. There is no room for regret when it comes to death. Yet a lot of people who have had suicide attempts and almost die, are glad they're alive when we resuscitate them at hospital.

All this means is that dying is scary, and its scary enough for most people that the fear of dying becomes greater than the pain they experience in life. It also doesn't change the fact that suicide can be a good option depending on your priorities.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvo0fd</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Ezada</author>
        <ReplyBody>People who are truly set on killing themselves, will inevitably find a way to do it with or without a law surrounding it. There is literally nothing that can be done to them once they are dead.  I am not sure how an euthanasia law would help anyone other than someone who has an illness that they will never recover from. 

Enacting a legal euthanasia law (in the US anyways) would require a lot of red tape, then getting insurance companies on board to pay for the initial procedure, putting laws into place regarding legal methods of euthanasia, setting up a whole new board of rules for people performing the euthanasia , then you have the religious that will argue that it is immoral etc. It is basically a lot of work for the government to give it's tax payers (the people who give them money) a ticket out of life. I know that sounds incredibly morbid and uncaring, but I am fairly certain that is how big government would see it. You are dead, so you can't be a "productive" member of society anymore, why should they help people out of it? Even those that have a life threatening illness are paying money to hospitals, which generate revenue, which they pay taxes on to the Government. Even the most depressed people usually still have a job and create revenue for them.

Most of the time (not always) people who post on message boards about ending their lives are usually crying out for help. I know that is why I sought them out when I was going through a very rough time in my life. I felt like suicide was my only option, but I didn't want it to be, despite how I was feeling then. 

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvlnkw</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think the two big reasons in favor (they may not be enough but you do not address them) and a third item.

&amp;gt;People who are truly set on killing themselves, will inevitably find a way

Not true, many of these people are bedridden and VERY ill. Often their meds are administered by a professional or a relative. And some of them may not even get meds that could kill them.

1) Relatives are normally involved, or at least often enough that prosecutions are a risk, remember these people are very very sick.

2) Human bodies are surprisingly resilient and if you just look at the US and the issues it is having enacting capital punishment as EU firms are refusing to make very specific drugs (that would not be available to sick people) They have had horrific executions, and this is a state institution designed to execute people, this is this year not historical. Can you really believe that legalizing this would not reduce suffering?

&amp;gt;It is basically a lot of work for the government to give it's tax payers (the people who give them money)

Lastly the cost issue is really weird? Why would you think it was more expensive to allow people to OD on morphine than live another five years with cancer? The taxpayer part... you do realize they paid their taxes (most at least whatever) so they paid for that care to start with. Why the hell should they die in pain so you can be treated on the tax dollars they paid?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvmbvv</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Ezada</author>
                <ReplyBody>Oh with the illness part, I totally agree on that which is why I only tackled the depression portion and people that can actually still get help, like veterans, depression, etc.  

My mother has ALS and I have Cancer, so I didn't tackle those specifically because honestly, if it came down to it, i would rather be euthanized than be chronically ill for 5 years and in misery. 

Sorry, I should have clarified in my original post about that. 

As for the taxpayers part, I think I worded that poorly as well. It wouldn't be more expensive for the governement to allow people to euthanize themselves. But it would cause them to lose revenue because now that person is no longer contributing to society (I am not 100% sure that this would happen, but after watching the way the government works, I wouldn't be surprised) It's just a hypothetical scenario, no need to get upset about it. 

I'm not sure where you live, but in the US the taxpayers dollar doesn't go towards any health care. We have to pay out of pocket, so our taxes doesn't help us in any way when we do become sick. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvmqv4</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I think in CMV you should give personal disclosure, which I did not see.

Sorry to hear about your mother and yourself, I hope the outcome is as good as possible given the situation.

OK So I live in a socialist hell hole so as you can imagine I take great doctors and free healthcare for granted. I am however very familiar with the US system and what you describe is not accurate. Emergency procedures and other such things required to prevent death are tax payer funded and the new laws (although they will obviously save money like they have in every country with nationalized healthcare) will also cost (but actually save under new plans) money, it is not a pay or die system even in the US, it is just a pay when it is REALLY expensive and not a good time to treat people system.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvntjs</id>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; People who are truly set on killing themselves, will inevitably find a way to do it with or without a law surrounding it. 

True. But some people aren't "truly set on killing themselves." They feel like they are just in limbo and find major difficulties in their life that they are unable to overcome or they feel that society hasn't/can't help them adequately enough. 

&amp;gt;  I am not sure how an euthanasia law would help anyone other than

Just to note, I'm not talking about absolute legalization everywhere of euthanasia. I'm only talking about euthanasia in places that already allow the death penalty. 

&amp;gt; It is basically a lot of work for the government to give it's tax payers (the people who give them money) a ticket out of life. 

I'm not talking about the government being the one actually paying for it, I'm just talking about the government of those places which have legalized the death penalty, to legalize euthanasia for biologically healthy citizens. The government of countries that have already legalized certain types of euthanasia with specific conditions, doesn't pay for the euthanasia itself. They just allow it by law with specific conditions, and what I'm saying is that these governments with legalized death penalty laws should legalize euthanasia. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvm6fm</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Ezada</author>
                <ReplyBody>Oh I didn't think you were implying that the government would pay for it. But I can see them using that as an excuse not to allow it. Inmates who have committed crimes that warrant the death penalty are already eating up resources that could be put to better use, just sitting in the prison systems. Whereas people who simply want to end their life (chronic illness, or no) can still financially contribute to society. Sorry if I explained that poorly. 

To question the "Truly set on killing themselves" how would one decide if someone was truly set on killing themselves vs, just over life? I think that there is a very fine line between people who can actually be helped and people who can't. Which is why I stated that anyone who really feels the need to die will do it regardless of if there is laws put into place to help them end their lives. 

People with Chronic illnesses that have a set amount of time to die though, I do agree on legal euthanasia for those instances. My mother has ALS, she has come to the decision that she will NOT be put on a respirator, she will not be tube fed, and she wants to die with some dignity, and if I was able to put her out of her misery without legal backlash if she asked me to do it, I would find a doctor that would. Of course, I could always fly her to Sweden where it is actually legal. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvmldk</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>TargetTango</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; People who are truly set on killing themselves, will inevitably find a way to do it with or without a law surrounding it. There is literally nothing that can be done to them once they are dead. I am not sure how an euthanasia law would help anyone other than someone who has an illness that they will never recover from. 

Most methods are difficult, messy and more often than not fail. And if someone fails at suicide, hell, even if they threaten it, the police are called and they are arrested (and that's in a good scenario, we all know how cops love to wave their guns around).</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckwjo9z</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>tsatugi</author>
        <ReplyBody>First of all, I think your first paragraph is silly. If someone plays the devil's advocate is the point they bring up necessarily not serious? I don't think so. In fact, this is a great way to develop your thoughts and come to a better understanding of the issue you're examining.

Anyone who actually wants to end their life won't let the law hold them back. To imply that someone won't commit suicide because of the consequences of the law doesn't make sense to me: if I'm dead the law has no effect on me.

To be fair, one could argue that the law does hold them back because there are no suicide assistance clinics and the culture of our society is generally opposed to it, but you didn't address this in your post.

Finally, as much as this is an argument in favor of euthanasia/suicide, it's also an argument against the death penalty. Suicide is illegal because many people think that it is wrong to kill one's self. Most of us all agree it's wrong to kill another person, although some people make distinctions based on the situation (e.g., in war, if you're being attacked, or if someone has committed a "bad enough" crime). Therefore, murder is illegal in most cases. Why don't we make capital punishment illegal, too? Basically, you say suicide should be legal because capital punishment is legal. From the same logic it follows that capital punishment should be illegal because suicide is illegal.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvnemw</id>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>Fair enough. I just meant it was preferable that people give their own opinions. If people want to give devil's advocates, that's also fine with me, and I already responded to one devil's advocate. 

&amp;gt; Anyone who actually wants to end their life won't let the law hold them back...  but you didn't address this in your post.

That's because euthanasia isn't necessarily for people who are hard-pressed on killing themselves. It can also be for people who are just simply existing and don't enjoy the life that they are given. Which I admit, might not be a good reason for legalizing euthanasia in itself; but when the context of a society that legalizes the death penalty is added into the mix, it starts making sense.

&amp;gt; Basically, you say suicide should be legal because capital punishment is legal. From the same logic it follows that capital punishment should be illegal because suicide is illegal.

This almost made me CMV. Until I realized that capital punishment is already outlawed in many countries/states. The states that still support the death penalty well into the 21st century are ones that really stand behind the retribution notion and are not going to change as a society on this particular issue.

I too, think it's preferable that capital punishment is removed from modern civilization altogether but I don't see these societies changing any time soon. I do however see legalizing euthanasia in societies that legalize the death penalty as a step towards progress in these societies once they realize that people who appear "normal" in that society are suddenly wanting to kill themselves. Then I'd say it would eventually become more lacks and capital punishment is banned altogether; thus banning euthanasia way into the future. But for now, I think euthanasia is a good stepping stone.
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvov8n</id>
            <replies>
                <author>tsatugi</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think capital punishment is on its way out. Most developed countries have outlawed it. The death penalty used to be common practice everywhere. We are witnessing it's phasing out. I would not expect such a shift to happen in a single generation, but that does not mean that it's not occurring.

While I agree that, from a logical point of view, euthanasia should be legal if capital punishment is legal (i.e., if the government can kill me, then I can kill myself), I don't think I can condone this:

&amp;gt; It can also be for people who are just simply existing and don't enjoy the life that they are given.

Regardless, I would agree with your view as defined in the OP if it said "Any entity which legalizes the death penalty may legalize euthanasia." But to say that it *should* implies an obligation to take action, and I don't agree with this. To say anything more we would first need to define some terms; I think specificity is necessary to go deeper here.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvy1mj</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>TargetTango</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Well the US and Japan are the only developed countries that have the death penalty. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckwjpvy</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>tsatugi</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Like I said, "capital punishment is on it's way out. Most developed countries have outlawed it." Thanks for specifying which countries haven't.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckwmlsx</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>TargetTango</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I don't see it ever being outlawed in the US or Japan. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckwmrfs</id>
                            <replies>
<author>tsatugi</author>
<ReplyBody>Ever? Why not?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckwmxeu</id>
<replies>
    <author>TargetTango</author>
    <ReplyBody>Because American politicians have a hard-on for "tough on crime". Largest prison population and a heavy Conservative base that loves the death penalty. In Japan, they don't like change and still hold onto their old values.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckwn40a</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>gooberfishie</author>
        <ReplyBody>I agree with OP for one big reason. If the death penalty is legal but assisted suicide is not, then if somebody wants a to have an assisted suicide they either need to go black market or they need to commit a horrible crime. Lets just skip the horrible crime step.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvn4wm</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>frotc914</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; if countries and states don't give a damn that they are killing human beings - even if the human being commits a "horrible" crime, what is wrong with (biologically) healthy individuals killing themselves if they so choose?

These two issues are not logically linked. To your point, I agree with your position on both. But the two are separable issues. 

The death penalty is a reaction to a decision on the part of the criminal. It is the breaking of the social contract. We essentially say "Life is sacred. That's why when you take someone else's, you forfeit your right to your own." The death penalty, while still barbaric to some, is reserved for only the worst crimes. There hasn't been a non-murder related capital punishment in the US since...I can't even think of one. To say that the punishment is the result of the state "not giving a damn that they are killing human beings", is a stretch at the least.

What about other nation's armies? They kill people all the time and then somehow they are "too good" for capital punishment. Is the UK and France dropping bombs on ISIS because they "don't give a damn that they are killing human beings"? Of course not. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvnn7k</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Sadnot</author>
        <ReplyBody>Would this be an accurate representation of your argument?

1. States which allow the death penalty do not care about the value of life.
2. States which do not help suicidal humans properly do not care about the value of life.
3. If a state doesn't care about the value of life, it should permit Euthanasia.


4. States which allow the death penalty should legalize euthanasia. 1+3
5. States which do not properly help suicidal humans should legalize euthanasia. 2+3</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvorhs</id>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>Well, I don't know if you're parodying the view point, but other than it being slightly skewed to make fun of the view point, sort of. It's more:

1) Countries/states/etc. which allow the death penalty justify the retribution stance (death penalty) for criminals even though they have the ability to pick the option of rehabilitation.

2) If said country/state is willing to justify the killing of another human being regardless of whether he is healthy, anything else he's done that could be done, whether he has relatives that rely upon him, etc, then it is only logically consistent if the state allows euthanasia, as they already agree on a societal level that killing another biologically healthy human beings, possibly against their will is justified.

3) Therefore, all consenting adults, biologically healthy or not that meet certain stringent requirements should be allowed to end their lives legally because said society prefers to either do nothing to help suffering individual or would rather  impose retribution methods than actually trying to rehabilitate the person to become a productive member of society.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvpiuy</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Sadnot</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Well, I don't know if you're parodying the view point, but other than it being slightly skewed to make fun of the view point, sort of.

I'm not doing anything of the sort, I'm instead trying to make perfectly clear the premises and conclusion of your argument.

So, your view could be summed up as: 

If a state ever considers killing healthy non-consenting adults to be justified, it should consider euthanasia of healthy consenting adults acceptable.

This raises the issue, what about defensive warfare for example? Defensive warfare is also killing healthy adults who are not consenting to be killed. If a country is willing to defend itself in war, is that inconsistent with banning euthanasia?
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvueix</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>hikikomori911</author>
                    <ReplyBody>No. Personally, I think the fact that society believes killing people is more beneficial than rehabilitation is sick (as in terrible). Especially when the society has the resources available to attempt to rehabilitate the person first.

However I guess I can accept:

&amp;gt; If a state[/country] **that has legalized the death penalty and is not ever planning on removing it from its law** considers killing healthy non-consenting adults to be justified, it should consider euthanasia of healthy consenting adults acceptable.

That would be my view point.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvvzc5</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Sadnot</author>
                        <ReplyBody>What is it that makes the death penalty different from the other ways in which the state kills adults?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvwkds</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hikikomori911</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Could you explain what you mean by that? What other ways does the state kill its citizens? Are you referring to  structural violence? Well the state in its current state (excuse the pun) doesn't actually punish structural violence, only direct acts of violence.

</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvwr16</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Sadnot</author>
<ReplyBody>For example, we generally think it's acceptable for the state to kill people for a variety of reasons including the use of the police and military. Why is it acceptable for a state to give the police and military lethal weapons, but not to use the death penalty?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvx7m6</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Mirisme</author>
                <ReplyBody>States that kills people as punishment deem this people undesirable to the point of killing them, it has little to do with health or other concern. On the other hand killing oneself or assisting is not killing someone which is undesirable at a sufficient degree.

More to the point, someone which support the capital punishment is more likely to believe (on a subconscious level) in the [just world hypothesis](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just-world_hypothesis) which validate capital punishment and not rehabilitation. Euthanasia is on the other hand still the act of killing somebody which is in pain. In the just world hypothesis view of the world, if you're in pain you are somehow responsible so why help someone responsible for his suffering?

tl;dr: Just world hypothesis is a fitting explanation for the discrepancy between euthanasia and capital punishment law.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvrt4o</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>hikikomori911</author>
                    <ReplyBody>That's not necessarily true. In Malaysia where I live, and Singapore, drug trafficking is punishable by death and it's actually enforced. It's not justified  as X person is so reprehensible he deserves to die, but as a deterrent for further crime.

But yes, you're probably right. They think "the only reason why that person did that crime was because "he is just innately horrible" which most likely isn't true because like you describe with an explanation of the just world fallacy, people sometimes do things for multi-faceted reasons that are just not that clear cut.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckvs6lf</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Mirisme</author>
                        <ReplyBody>If trading in drug is a crime then it must be punished and all punishment is a deterrent for further crime. So yeah in this case the punishment is harsh but i dont see how this contradict my point.

So did i change your view? ;)</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckvsrpp</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>hikikomori911</author>
                            <ReplyBody>See, this is why I didn't want devils advocates in the first place. Oh well.

No, you didn't convince me of anything. A crime should be punished with just consequences. No one should suffer more to be made "an example of" when that person suffers permanent harsh conditions of well... death.

It also doesn't deter crime if it doesn't resolve the reasons why the people committed the crime in the first place. If someone traffics drugs because he is desperate for money to feed his family, then why should he be killed because of it? And how is it fair for society to determine that trafficking drugs for money is equally as bad as killing another human being in cold blood?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>ckvsz7r</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Mirisme</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; See, this is why I didn't want devils advocates in the first place. Oh well.

Hmm it was just to see if you were convinced or not, your last post was quite ambiguous about that.

&amp;gt;No, you didn't convince me of anything. A crime should be punished with just consequences. No one should suffer more to be made "an example of" when that person suffers permanent harsh conditions of well... death.

I do not follow you here, death is a consequence. And punishment in a judiciary system is about making an example (what you can expect to have if you behave in that way) not about rehabilitating the person in question.
What you think should be is not what the people who made these laws think should be (just world hypothesis most likely).

&amp;gt; It also doesn't deter crime if it doesn't resolve the reasons why the people committed the crime in the first place. If someone traffics drugs because he is desperate for money to feed his family, then why should he be killed because of it? And how is it fair for society to determine that trafficking drugs for money is equally as bad as killing another human being in cold blood?

You're arguing with the point of view of someone not ingrained with the just world hypothesis. In this view if someone is poor, ill, resorting to thievery or drug dealing it's their fault and not society's fault hence they are bad person and should be killed if the behavior is deemed evil (drug in this case).

The problem at hand is a logical loophole in your world view but not in the world view of someone with just world hypothesis as a base tenet. If you think illness and crime are what you get if you're not good why ban capital punishment (bad people ought to be punished) and why adopt euthanasia (good people cant need it and bad people sure deserve to die in pain or live with it).</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>ckvuzmu</id>
<replies>
    <author>hikikomori911</author>
    <ReplyBody>Just consequences means fair consequences. If someone commits a crime under the law, it should be punished with equal measure. The law shouldn't be draconian and unreasonably inhumane. That would be classified as "cruel and unusual punishments" and is banned practically worldwide. So if someone steals food and their hands are chopped off in the 21st century, that would indeed be considered "cruel and unusual punishment".

You might be thinking (I'm guessing here) that well, the death penalty can be considered cruel and unusual punishment. And well, I think so too, but once again we're talking about societies that already allow death penalties.

&amp;gt; In this view if someone... 

No I think you've got it backwards. I was giving an example of how those who justify the death penalty rationalize the legalization of the death penalty.

</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>ckvwnsx</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>vl99</author>
        <ReplyBody>While the two items you are putting forth in your argument may seem similar (death penalty vs assisted suicide) they are effectively different. Suicide is its own thing, the death penalty is a form of punishment. 

Your argument is akin to saying "countries that sanction locking people up in jail for committing crimes should make it legal for people to voluntarily enter the prison system whenever they want."</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvp113</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>yayaja67</author>
        <ReplyBody>What does one have to do with the other? Capital punishment and Euthanasia are two completely separate issues, and conflating them is only going to make social progress in either of them more difficult. Any similarities these two issues share is purely superficial, as the deeper motivations behind them are completely different.

In 10-20 years we may finally decide as a society that there is no point in executing criminals because it doesn't do society any good.  We may also decide that under certain circumstances euthanasia *does* do good.  We may arrive at these conclusions independently and decades apart. If the two issues are linked, it means that when society reverses its opinion of one, it must *necessarily* reverse its opinion of the other.

I don't see how mashing the issues together into a sloppy "if this then that" argument benefits anyone.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvsjz0</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CaptnCarl85</author>
            <ReplyBody>  Well said.

I would also add that the common thread in both topics is the state's monopoly on violence. Suicide is considered by some to be a natural right. But you were depriving the right of the King to use you for his bidding or the Church to collect tithing ... hence our laws evolved from collectivist notions of you being of value to a larger entity.

Aristotle felt it robs the community of the services of one of its members. That seems to be the origin of modern legislation.

Source: 
Plato. Laws, Book IX
Durkheim, mile (1897). Suicide. New York: The Free Press (reprint, 1997), 327.
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_suicide#Antiquity_and_Middle_Ages</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckwpues</id>
            <replies>
                <author>DeltaBot</author>
                <ReplyBody>Confirmed: 1 delta awarded to /u/yayaja67. ^[[History](/r/changemyview/wiki/user/yayaja67)]

^[[Wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/deltabot)][[Code](https://github.com/alexames/DeltaBot)][[Subreddit](http://www.reddit.com/r/DeltaBot/)]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwr13k</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>bam2_89</author>
        <ReplyBody>Not a devil's advocate. I disagree with the death penalty and support euthanasia, but I reject the equivalency.

Euthanasia and the death penalty differ in that euthanasia is a wholly medical procedure. A great deal of the euthanasia controversy is rooted in the fact that it would have physicians ending the lives of patients, which most physicians argue is a breach of their role. The death penalty almost never involves a physician in administering the lethal agent, whereas euthanasia in places where it is legal, may require a physician.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvwjqf</id>
        <replies>
            <author>hikikomori911</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Euthanasia and the death penalty differ in that euthanasia is a wholly medical procedure.

A medical procedure that 99% of the time ends in the patient's death, just like the death penalty.

&amp;gt; The death penalty almost never involves a physician in administering the lethal agent

Do you have a source for that?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvwuwt</id>
            <replies>
                <author>bam2_89</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; A medical procedure that 99% of the time ends in the patient's death, just like the death penalty.

The death penalty is not the practice of medicine. Only the administration of drugs per se during lethal injection may be considered as such. Hanging, electrocution, firing squad, and the gas chamber don't even involve a low-level medical professional. The state of Georgia passed a law stating that even the administering of the drugs was not the practice of medicine.

States which require physicians to administer the drugs have a difficult time recruiting anyone willing to do it. http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/node/2264 Regardless of state requirements, in practice, almost all executions are performed by just four states: TX, VA, FL, and NC. Texas has a medical technician to do it. In VA, the warden does it personally. FL is apparently the only major state in which a physician participates, but they have to conceal their identity in order to prevent AMA sanctions. North Carolina flat-out forbids participation by physicians. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckvy08i</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>0100101010110</author>
                <ReplyBody>While i agree that countries that have the death penalty should also legalize euthanasia,  they wont. They are similar things with very different arguments behind them, both largely political. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwfdb0</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>TheAngryBrian</author>
        <ReplyBody>There's a big difference between removing people who are very likely to be potentially harmful to others and allowing people who are depressed to kill themselves.

Suicide is a completely irrational decision made by very, very desperate minds. I recall reading somewhere that almost every single person whose ever jumped off of a bridge and lived said that they IMMEDIATELY regretted the decision once they'd gone past the point of no return. They didn't really want to kill themselves, they just wanted their issues and those nagging emotional pains to go away.

Depression is treatable, and allowing people who are mentally unstable to do that to themselves is cruel. These people need treatment for their issues. They do not need to kill themselves, and we should not present that as an option to people suffering with depression and suicidal thoughts.

I'm not arguing that the death penalty is a great thing for helping to keep society safe, but I absolutely loathe it when people say we should just let the suicidally depressed kill themselves.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvx5vt</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Direpants</author>
        <ReplyBody>The death penalty does not exist because the state does not believe that human lives are valuable. In fact, it only exists because the state believes that human lives are extremely valuable, and that the worst thing that it could do to someone is to take that away. You can see why they would think that robbing someone of this immensely valuable thing should only be a punishment for egregious crimes, right?

For the record, I am anti death penalty and for the right to commit suicide. But my argument against yours is not that states which allow capital punishment *should* allow euthanasia, but that the motivations for either legalizing or illegalizing these two things are entirely unrelated and should not be eupquated.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvzoy3</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>LegatoBlue</author>
        <ReplyBody>You are making the argument that the death penalty is equal to euthanasia. Death = death. Therefore it would be logical to say that both instances would get the same legal process. 

We would need a jury to assess euthanasia. It would be like the Obamacare alarmists' worst nightmare. Literal death panels.

This strikes me as too distasteful to be accepted. Your argument doesn't fully stand. Death =/= death in this case. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckw0lw9</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Dharma_Monkey</author>
        <ReplyBody>Technically, any state with the death penalty *does* have euthanasia. If you want to die, just commit murder in the first degree. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckw0sz2</id>
        <replies>
            <author>[deleted]</author>
            <ReplyBody>I can't quite tell if this is sarcastic or serious, but it sure as hell doesn't add anything to the argument</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckwxtke</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Dharma_Monkey</author>
                <ReplyBody>Well it is sort of an argument ad adsurdum. If you're willing to kill people against their will as a state, then you should at least kill people if they want to be killed as a state. 

It also raises a question of practicality: "If I want to die, the state will kill me, but only under one circumstance."</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwy9c9</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Knowltey</author>
        <ReplyBody>Deaht penalities are considered the ultimate punishment by places that use it. Such a place wouldn't want to admit that some people may actually want it.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvn5zx</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Kameron635</author>
        <ReplyBody>Euthanasia/Assisted Suicide while nice in theory for the terminally ill, would end up being abused by the suicidally depressed. I realize that a system could be created that would get help to those with mental illness seeking assisted suicide but the very fact that such abuse could happen renders the requisite legislation controversial and difficult to pass. There is also the religious factor, Suicide is a sin and is culturally taboo, therefore it would be difficult to pass due to conservative/religious opposition.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvokln</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Kameron635</author>
            <ReplyBody>Also you make it sound like there is no help for the homeless, impoverished, and depressed, when in fact there is, for the depressed much more so than the homeless or impoverished at least.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckvoodc</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Trimestrial</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; ... I will assume that you yourself personally disagree with what I have to say.

Yes I personally disagree with your position...

Proponents of the death-penalty, and proponents of euthanasia, use different arguments to support their position, as do opponents.

For instance: I do not support the death penalty for the reason that a justice system can and will make mistakes. And I support euthanasia, ONLY under very limited circumstances, such as an incurable disease, that causes suffering, when the person is **sane** while making the choice. Not just someone who doesn't like their life...

At the same time, there is NOTHING hypocritical about someone who is an opponent of euthanasia for the reason that God created life, while supporting the death penalty because God said "Thou shall not kill."</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvpds0</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>rustyarrowhead</author>
        <ReplyBody>a collective right to punish through death is fundamentally different from the individual right to escape/mitigate through death. the two rights are not linked at all (whether or not they deal with "death") as one deals with the right to death (individual right) and the other deals with the right to life (in the case where the death penalty is illegal) or, more importantly, the right to security (a collective right, where it is legal). a legal right to death is not necessarily needed as suicide is not criminalized and must be undertaken by the individual. if society removes barriers to suicide, it could be argued that it is not fulfilling its duty to guarantee the right to health (physical and mental), especially in the cases that you're mentioning. if we move the discussion to the terminally ill, you could reframe euthanasia as a form of healthcare. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvtl7s</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MrMercurial</author>
        <ReplyBody>If killing people is bad, one can consistently oppose euthanasia while supporting the death penalty, simply on the basis that it is good to inflict bad things on bad people, but not on innocent people. I don't agree with that claim, but it's not inconsistent. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvzbn8</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>actualsnow</author>
        <ReplyBody>I believe in banning the death penalty and allowing euthanasia. Why? Because a free man in pain should have the right to be released, and a man in prison has a probability of being innocent.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckwavwb</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CaptnCarl85</author>
            <ReplyBody>Or even one step further. Allow those in prison the option too. Innocent or guilty, if I were in prison for more than 20 years, I'd prefer the Painless Pill.

I even think we should give them a delux last meal for taking the option. But absolutely no pressure. 

Instead, we stop prisoners from suicide at great expense to taxpayers, victim's families, and the inmate. I'm up in NH. Man killed his wife and baby and tried to kill himself. He was a monster. (Grand)Mother of victims wanted him dead. But paramedics performed heroic efforts to save him. Then because this was pre-Obamacare and he was uninsured, we all had to pick up the expensive bill (not to mention the court costs, and his public attorney).  He tried to commit suicide in prison two more times. Both times the state put in a lot more of an effort than they do for crazy people who are freezing to death on the streets. It's a flipped around system of priorities.

And many people say "They should suffer in jail. Death is too easy" ... stfu you crazy people. I don't want to pay for prison torture because some weirdos sick fantasies. The victim's want him dead, he wants suicide, and he's kept alive until he's 90 now. The pill and last meal would cost no more than a thousand bucks.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckwpefw</id>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>Sorry if I'm late to the party here. I'm not going to read all the comments, so if I'm redundant, again,  my apologies.

As a little background, I'm actually against the death penalty and for euthenasia, but my reasoning is different.

Anywho, I think we are looking at two different things. The death penalty goes under the presumption that death is the ultimate punishment and a deterrent. Euthenasia goes on the assumption that death is actually a relief. 

Can the same thing be both a relief and a punishment?

Societies tend to treat it as an unambiguous punishment, and while I see this as an error, the logic behind it is consistent.

I think the better option would be for governments to admit that they don't really know, and that the perception of death differs from person to person, and their should be laws that force someone to either live or die for any reason. 

So I agree with your conclusion, but I see your reasoning as flawed. A government can't "care" for anything. It is a system.

*multiple edits for content. 
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckwftbn</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>I have left reddit for [Voat](https://voat.co/) due to years of admin mismanagement and preferential treatment for certain subreddits and users holding certain political and ideological views.  

   As an act of protest, I have chosen to redact all the comments I've ever made on reddit, overwriting them with this message.  

   If you would like to do the same, install [TamperMonkey](https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/tampermonkey/dhdgffkkebhmkfjojejmpbldmpobfkfo) for Chrome, [GreaseMonkey](https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/firefox/addon/greasemonkey/) for Firefox, [NinjaKit](https://github.com/os0x/NinjaKit) for Safari, [Violent Monkey](https://addons.opera.com/en/extensions/details/violent-monkey/) for Opera, or [AdGuard](http://adguard.com/) for Internet Explorer (in Advanced Mode), then add [this GreaseMonkey script](https://greasyfork.org/en/scripts/10905-reddit-overwrite-extended).   

 Finally, click on your username at the top right corner of reddit, click on comments, and click on the new OVERWRITE button at the top of the page. You may need to scroll down to multiple comment pages if you have commented a lot.  

   After doing all of the above, you are welcome to join me on [Voat](https://voat.co/)!</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvurok</id>
        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Ponox</author>
        <ReplyBody>There is no such thing as a mentally competent person who wants to kill themselves.

The cases of terminally ill people are another story.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>ckvtmte</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CaptnCarl85</author>
            <ReplyBody>Explain your first point. I genuinely don't understand it. I've met people that have said, "if life grows intolerable, I want to end it." And I understand that as a rational man. How does that make them incompetent? Suicidal ideation can be a sign of mental defect ... but does that make them irrational in their pain? Pain is real, including mental anguish. 

Explain, please.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>ckwplsy</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Ponox</author>
                <ReplyBody>I concede it is *possible* for a mostly healthy person to desire (and indeed go through with) suicide. However the number of people who do is extremely small.

Those with severe depression (although their pain is real) the reasons behind it are often not rational.

Suicide in itself goes against every survival instinct a living thing has, so by definition you can not desire to kill yourself and at the same time consider yourself mentally healthy.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>ckwprqv</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CaptnCarl85</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I guess you and I would disagree about what is rational. Pain avoidance, I believe, is rational. The higher the degree of pain or mental anguish, the increased need to alleviate it. It's the humane thing to allow it to be done painlessly and in the most dignified way possible. Belgium is doing it right.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>ckwuuth</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Ponox</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Why treat depression with death? That sounds more inhumane to me. I agree that dignified death should always be an option regardless, but it shouldn't be taken lightly.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>ckyefpk</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
