<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>98</commentCount>
    <id>41a86a</id>
    <permaLink>/r/changemyview/comments/41a86a/cmv_why_dont_we_conduct_statesanctioned_capital/?ref=search_posts</permaLink>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Madplato</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'd argue a guillotine would offer much more reliability and better results for much cheaper. There's no chance for unfortunate survivals, it requires less maintenance than guns, can be maintained by just about anybody, cannot misfire, does little noise (which is important in enclosed space) and has very little chance of mechanical or human failure. Additionally, it's insanely cheap. It can be rigged to operate itself easily, much more easily than a gun. 

So, why should we use a gun and not a guillotine ? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz0snbj</id>
        <replies>
            <author>DrWhiskeydick</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think the problem with both guns and guillotines is that they're horrendously gruesome.  With a lethal injection, or even a hanging, there isn't a bunch of arterial blood spray showering the surroundings.  Reliability isn't the issue, and the humaneness isn't the issue.  It's the appearance.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz15f4g</id>
            <replies>
                <author>getfuckingreal</author>
                <ReplyBody>Humaneness is the issue, for the executioner not the condemned.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1jsf5</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Humaneness is not the issue, there is absolutely nothing humane about execution, regardless of the form it comes in</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1oqid</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Gladix</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I would argue that it is more humane to execute selected few, than to leave them to general population or even prison population.

Since the latter produces more deaths and suffering, not to mention economic cost overall.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz2q0x6</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Why is it humane? What if they are wrongly convicted? The humane thing to do is punish them, rehabilitate them, and when safe put them back into society. Execution is what you do to rabid dogs, not ill human beings.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz2qdpw</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Gladix</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Why is it humane? What if they are wrongly convicted? The humane thing to do is punish them, rehabilitate them, and when safe put them back into society.

Yeah I know. The problem is there are people that are not rehabilitable. I assume you will aggree to that. People who will do evil things no matter through which program you put them, no matter for how long you will lock them out. And they will be a danger for everyone in the meantime. What will you do with these people?

Keeping them locked out, getting other inmates in danger. Keeping them in isolation for the rest of their lives? Effectively torturing them with isolation? Costing significantly more than any other detainment method.

Letting them out, obviously is out of the question.

&amp;gt;Execution is what you do to rabid dogs, not ill human beings.

I'm sorry but that's non sequitur. I can just as say that rabid humans deserve fast and painless execution, rather than linch mobbing.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cz2r3zl</id>
<replies>
    <author>Tinie_Snipah</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The problem is there are people that are not rehabilitable.

And they will stay in jail for as long as the law allows it. 

&amp;gt; What will you do with these people?

Send them to jail. If they are truly ill then have them sent to a psych ward. 

&amp;gt;Letting them out, obviously is out of the question.

Why is it? We have psychiatric wards which are built specifically to solve this exact issue. And when people are deemed no longer ill they are allowed to leave. That is humane society.

There's nothing humane about execution.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cz2spcw</id>
    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>TheRingshifter</author>
                <ReplyBody>I consider that a pro and not a con. If you are killing someone it probably should be gruesome. And if you're worrying about how gruesome it is you've really got backwards priorities. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1h97o</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Madplato</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Why should it be gruesome ? Considering it's a poor deterrent and quite costly, the only reason to kill a prisoner is to permanently remove it because he's a threat. Is he less remove if the execution isn't gruesome ?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1mqtp</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>TheRingshifter</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Nah. It's more just that, I think if executions were more gruesome, they would seem more like what they really are: killing someone. It's not super-important but I definitely don't think it's very important that the execution *isn't* gruesome. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz1myrg</id>
                        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>DrWhiskeydick</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Yeah, but it's not entirely up to the prison or the people performing the executions.  They need to appease the rest of society, who apparently have a problem with bloody executions.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1qj9y</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>TheRingshifter</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Pretty much my point exactly. If people have a problem with bloody executions, they really shouldn't be executing people.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz1sfvy</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>matt-the-great</author>
                            <ReplyBody>This is the wrong argument. People have a problem with bloody executions because, in general, people hold a value that gore and destruction of the human body is wrong. Illogical or irrational it may be (a dead man is a dead man, whether he has his head or not), the justice system is based on the value system of the population that employs it.

Besides, there are other considerations to be made when discussing bloody and gruesome executions--should human beings have to preside over those? You realize that that's probably a pretty traumatic thing to have to endure as an executioner if the guy you just guillotined's blood just splattered all over your face, right? Besides--our society values funerals and the burial of human remains--a bloody and disfigured corpse would be cruel to the innocent bereaved.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz224i0</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>10</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Milkyway_Squid</author>
            <ReplyBody>What about asphyxiation by nitrogen or other inert gas other than CO2?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz14sui</id>
            <replies>
                <author>TagaKain</author>
                <ReplyBody>How fast would it kill you?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz16prr</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Sungolf</author>
                    <ReplyBody>2 minutes.. 5 if you are in peak physical form. It is also painless and not noticeable unless you are paying attention. This is because breathing is controlled by [CO2 concentration in the blood](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breathing#Unconscious_control) rather than by O2 saturation.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz190dz</id>
                    <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Genoscythe_</author>
                <ReplyBody>Gassing people is gennerally a no-no. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1h7oe</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>eye_patch_willy</author>
                    <ReplyBody>It's not poisonous gas. We breathe in nitrogen with every breath. This is breathing in regular air without oxygen. You get high and then you go to sleep, forever. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1i2ch</id>
                    <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>5</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>I can't offer a mechanical reason why, just my personal preference. A guillotine looks far, far more menacing than a gun, and would invoke more dread and fear in me. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz0spz8</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Madplato</author>
                <ReplyBody>You don't really need to see it however, it can be made has subtle as being strapped to a self-aiming self-firing gun. More importantly, however, is that there's *no way* you can survive a guillotine. Also, I feel like cutting a head clean off would be much less gruesome than blowing someone's neck. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0sums</id>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>AmoebaMan</author>
                <ReplyBody>A modern guillotine would probably look far different. A relatively small blade probably, driven by maybe a pneumatic piston or something. Likely very compact.

In effect, it wouldn't be that much different than your gun actually.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0tbz5</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>12</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Talibanned</author>
        <ReplyBody>The main opposition towards capital punishment isn't as much the method as it is the notion of killing someone. I think the two strongest counterarguments is that is is often times far more expensive to execute someone compared to keeping them locked up for life, as well as the shockingly common incidents of executing people who were later found to be innocent. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz0qodt</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Smudge777</author>
            <ReplyBody>You're right, but this has practically nothing to do with the topic of this thread.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz1c2fu</id>
            <upvotes>5</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>moonflower</author>
            <ReplyBody>How can it possibly be more expensive to kill someone than to feed and house them for life?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz0rdhz</id>
            <replies>
                <author>SC803</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Cases without the death penalty cost $740,000, while cases where the death penalty is sought cost $1.26 million. Maintaining each death row prisoner costs taxpayers $90,000 more per year than a prisoner in general population. There are 714 inmates on California's death row.

http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/costs-death-penalty</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0rqbj</id>
                <upvotes>12</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>DHCKris</author>
                <ReplyBody>Because often you still have to feed and house a death row inmate for life, because they don't want to die and will continue to appeal to save/prolong their lives for decades. The appeals process is an added expense, making death row inmates costlier.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0uwm7</id>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Talibanned</author>
                <ReplyBody>Legal fees from appeals, etc. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0rlc8</id>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>thelordpresident</author>
                <ReplyBody>A system that's really inefficient at killing criminals but very streamlined at putting them in prison</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz12tdx</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>RasslinsnotRasslin</author>
                <ReplyBody>You let them have ten thousand appeals </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz240ji</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Because in capital cases they always max out their appeals, which costs hundreds of thousands of not a million in court fees</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz2yan5</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>5510</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't understand how that is relevant to the OPs post?     
      
I think they are just saying that given that the death penalty exists, which methods we use to carry it out.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz1djzi</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>SC803</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; why don't we use a method that is 100% fatal and completely humane

People can survive gunshots to the head and if they don't its messy, people go to executions for whatever reason, watching some die from lethal injection way different than someone being shot in the head

</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz0quqo</id>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>Has anyone survived a gunshot to the spinal cord at the base of the neck? </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz0r0s1</id>
            <replies>
                <author>NuclearStudent</author>
                <ReplyBody>Being shot in the spinal cord wouldn't kill you immediately. As the brain would still be intact, there would be seconds while the brain ran out of blood and oxygen. If the bullet penetrated without destroying an artery, then the person could die relatively slowly.

To avoid pain, the gun would have to shoot the brain directly. You'd probably want more than one gun because misfires happen.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0ve60</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>UnknownXV</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Sure, you could have 2, 3, hell you could have 10. It still wouldn't be expensive. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz13gbc</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>NuclearStudent</author>
                        <ReplyBody>The main argument, I think, is that it would disfigure the body. I know it's weird but people are squeamish. 

Where this matters is when innocent people are executed. It happens surprisingly often. When innocent people are killed via lethal injection, the state says "sorry" and goes on with the executions. It's poor for public relations when an innocent person has their head removed in an incredibly graphic way. 

Basically, the reason we use lethal injection over a mechanical gun device is about PR, not humanitarianism. If the media ran with graphic execution videos of innocent people, the future of the death penalty would be in doubt. 

The death penalty is already a bit of an elephant when it comes to diplomacy with America. Making it graphic could exacerbate that.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz141v9</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>UnknownXV</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I don't disagree with anything you say.. it's just all very depressing. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz1463u</id>
                            <replies>
<author>NuclearStudent</author>
<ReplyBody>Well, sure it's depressing. But it seems to me that the real reason behind capital punishment is so that people can wack off in their pants about killing the bad guys and/or enjoy the power or comfort of having their state dole out the ultimate punishment. Humanitarianism doesn't really play much of a part in this though. 


If we're going to kill people, keep it good clean family fun. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cz17zgs</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>SC803</author>
                <ReplyBody>Thats totally dependent on this happening, and its not really a humane of killing people

&amp;gt; Paralysis and loss of sensation of part of the body are common. This includes total paralysis or numbness, and loss of movement and feeling. **Death is possible, especially if there is paralysis of the breathing muscles.**

https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001066.htm</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0r7va</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>UnknownXV</author>
                    <ReplyBody>From that article, it seems that gunshot wounds are indirectly related, as it mentions "fragments from gunshot". 

I highly doubt that a direct shot at the spinal cord from a high power gun would ever leave the person alive. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz0re2t</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SC803</author>
                        <ReplyBody>http://m.hopkinsmedicine.org/healthlibrary/conditions/physical_medicine_and_rehabilitation/spinal_cord_injury_85,P01180/

Scroll down to C2-3 

"Usually fatal as a result of inability to breathe"

It's not always fatal, and it's not instant</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz0rld4</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>caw81</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; gunshot wounds are indirectly related, as it mentions "fragments from gunshot". 

This means the parts of the bullet, which is what the main damage from a gunshot is.

Exactly what is the mechanism from a gunshot to a spinal cord do you think causes 100% instant death?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz0roso</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>thelordpresident</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I feel like severing the brain completely from the body causes near instant death. A gunshot can do that, but a fragment could only take out part of the cord, or imbed itself in it. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz131e4</id>
                            <replies>
<author>SC803</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; "Usually fatal as a result of inability to breathe"

Suffocation isn't instant death</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cz137fn</id>
<replies>
    <author>thelordpresident</author>
    <ReplyBody>Yes, and that wasn't a bullet to the spinal cord at point plank. That was a shard of a bullet or something much less powerful that just damaged some specific Vertebrae. The source has nothing to do with what would happen in the situation the OP is describing. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cz1599i</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>TheRingshifter</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not sure about this. Sure, with a pistol or something, but what about with a high-powered sniper rifle type-thing? Is that really possible to survive? </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz1hafa</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Raptor_man</author>
        <ReplyBody>Capital punishment methods have three things to consider when permitting a method. First is lethality. A bullet to the head is not a guaranteed death and can quite easily be botched by the shooter. Second is if it's humane. This means it is not purposefully malicious or causes undue suffering. Last but most important its the effect it can have on the executioner. 

In the USA firing squad has recently been reinstated but the method is far from what you describe.  about 5 shooters are set up to fire on the heart and one person has blanks. They all open fire on the bound and blindfolded (bagged) recipient and they die due to bleeding. The issue with this is it is physiologically very damaging to the executioners (less so than if it was one sole shooter but still damaging). The issues with your idea of a "better" method is you now put the full psychological impact of pulling that trigger on the one person who set up the machine and activated it. You also greatly increase risk of missing the target due to the recipient's ability to move/failure to properly align. Think about what you are likely to hit if you are just a few inches off target. You can hit the neck and nick the carotid artery causing the person to die in minuets and in extreme panic and pain, or you can nick the cord but fail to sever it allowing the bullet to puncture the esophagus leading to the person drowning on their own blood.  Most importantly you end up introducing so many steps that the risk of failure is almost guaranteed.

If you want a truly humane method of execution push for Inert gas asphyxiation. Little to no suffering for anyone involved and 100% success rate.  </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz10hts</id>
        <replies>
            <author>5510</author>
            <ReplyBody>Personally, I think the "one gun has blanks" is a bitch move.  If you are going to be part of executing, at least sack up and say "yes, this is what I am doing."  Don't have one of you have blanks so you can all pretend maybe it wasn't you.  If I were gonna be executed, I would be pissed off that the people doing it were going to try and wash their hands of responsibility.    
      
(I'm generally not super favorable toward having the death penalty at all FWIW, but I don't like the whole idea of trying to avoid responsibility.)</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz1dlwl</id>
            <replies>
                <author>pleasehelpthankyou</author>
                <ReplyBody>You evidently haven't been in a situation where you could be on a firing squad.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1gufe</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>5510</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I wouldn't do it unless I was comfortable doing it and taking responsibility for my actions.    
     
I've never been on a firing squad, so I'm not saying I guarantee it would be easy or wouldn't trouble me at all, or that anybody who is disturbed by it is a pussy.  I'm saying I would either do it and take responsibility, or not do it at all.  But I would do it while hiding behind the "maybe i was the one with the blanks" to try and wash my hands of responsibility.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1uvlc</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>pleasehelpthankyou</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Nobody on the squad washes his hands of responsibility. For some, the possibility of blanks lets them sleep at night.

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz1xuyu</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>5510</author>
                            <ReplyBody>That is a contradiction.  How else does it let them sleep at night other than feeling like diminished responsibility?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz1ynlh</id>
                            <replies>
<author>pleasehelpthankyou</author>
<ReplyBody>The whole situation you're misinterpreting. There's nothing unethical or immoral about using the blank by any stretch of the imagination and it's incredibly hard for people to cope with the situation otherwise. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cz1zo8l</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>RibsNGibs</author>
                <ReplyBody>It's the State that wants to execute the criminal and bears responsibility, not the poor schmuck who has the shitty job of actually doing it. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1la19</id>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'm not a physiologist, but there must be some way to kill someone with a guaranteed success rate using a gun. A poster previously mentioned firing the gun at the back of the neck severing the spinal cord, but also pointing up so the bullet passes through the brain as well. 

No one can survive that. 

So lethality is in check.

Absolutely no pain, so it's humane. Much more so than lethal injection.

And as far as psychological damage on the executioner, the brilliant thing is, there doesn't even need to be one. Someone has to setup the machine, but beyond that? It could be programmed to fire at a certain time, or be activated by remote from another room. The person activating it wouldn't even have to see the inmate. 

Dying by gas is just as horrifying a thought to me as death by lethal injection.

Overall, I think how someone is to be executed should be up to the person who is going to be executed. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz13em5</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Raptor_man</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think you misunderstand what I mean by Inert gas asphyxiation. So far only a couple states have passed it. What you are likely thinking of is gas a gas chamber execution. Those use a chemical that causes the lungs to be irritated forcing mucus to be built up and the person drowns in said build up. You quite likely have experienced Inert gas asphyxiation though not to the point of death. It's laughing gas. The same thing nearly every dentist and anesthesiologist has used. It doesn't hurt nor can you taste or smell it. You might experience a high like symptom. 

The idea of setting up a loaded gun in a room that will at some point go off doesn't sound at all dangerous to you? Lets walk through what would need to happen for your idea to work. First you need to build the thing to in a way that will minimize failure but allow it to go off on a set time. Next you need to secure the person to something like a board from head to toe so they can't mess up the shot. Next you need to set the person up in the perfect position because remember just one inch off leads to agonizing death that lasts minuets. Than you leave the person there. Alone with their thoughts waiting for the eventual and inevitable shot for what would likely be a long time. The reason they would have to wait for a long time is because you don't want to rush the prep. Most importantly you also run the risk of it going off prematurely at any point putting every one in front of it at risk. Does that sound humane to you? </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz17fbm</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>panderingPenguin</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Overall, I think how someone is to be executed should be up to the person who is going to be executed.

This opens you up to ridiculous requests, i.e. "I want to drown in pussy."</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz15vrs</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>sadris</author>
        <ReplyBody>Utah already allows execution by firing squad.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz0s6gx</id>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>Firing squad... at a distance. That doesn't kill you instantly. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz0s7d7</id>
            <replies>
                <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>It generally does, actually.  There's multiple bullets fired by skilled marksmen, and even one bullet to the head will typically kill immediately.  If I had to personally pick I'd take firing squad over a rigged contraption.  I mean, I'd take "pushed off a cliff" as my option 2 for the fun of the free fall, but firing squad would be number 3 for sure.  Any of them would be well above lethal injection though.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0ya6g</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Raptor_man</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Firing squads aim at the hear not the head. The person being shot is also strapped down and mostly immobile. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz10kf0</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>UnknownXV</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Well, the specific way someone wants to do isn't really the point, moreso that lethal injection itself is utterly terrifying to me and seems well within the "cruel and unusual" punishment range. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz13fmo</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>phcullen</author>
        <ReplyBody>People like to have funerals and open casket viewings.  Mangled heads is unpleasant for the family to have to deal with. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz117e9</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>bamfbarber</author>
        <ReplyBody>I would say this as someone who has been shot. It not how I would choose to go.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz1504j</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Clockworkfrog</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why sever the spinal cord and not shot up into the brain?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz0rp6y</id>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>I've heard of some people surviving a gunshot wound to the brain.

It seems rather inconvenient that no matter where you shoot someone, there's always some incident out there where a human has survived it somehow. 

So 100% fatal may be incorrect... but it's well within the 99% range. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz0rrf3</id>
            <replies>
                <author>SC803</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; but it's well within the 99% range. 

You're making the 99% sound like its a fact when you're guessing...</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0ru1f</id>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>imanatheistsowhat</author>
                <ReplyBody>How can you possibly say it's 99%?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0rval</id>
                <upvotes>5</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Clockworkfrog</author>
                <ReplyBody>I meant through the spinal cord, I mean there is an incredibly thin chance of surviving each sepperately but both seem even less likely.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz0rz54</id>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Crayshack</author>
        <ReplyBody>Decapitation is a much more reliable, speedy, and relatively painless execution method than a shot to the back of the head or neck.  

While usually fatal, shots to the back of the head or neck are survivable.  When they are fatal, they can sometimes take days to die from.  The bullet needs to be placed extremely precisely to result in an instant death, something which would be unable to be guaranteed.  A slight error in placement, the condemned prisoner moving just a bit, or even the bullet taking a funny bounce when striking bone can all drastically affect how much and what kind of damage is done.

Meanwhile, decapitation is 100% lethal, takes effect in mere seconds, is pretty hard to mess up even with only so-so equipment, and would be a relatively small amount of pain (mostly due to the person passing out very quickly from loss of blood pressure).</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz0v70f</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>cdb03b</author>
        <ReplyBody>Oklahoma and Utah both use firing squads as an option for execution. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz1c21a</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>MikeCanada</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;For my own personal opinion of it, lethal injection would be utter horror. I have a serious phobia of needles and drugs. I'd rather die burning alive than receiving a lethal injection. The thought of it, being strapped to a table with an IV jammed into my vein and lethal drugs pumped into my system.. I feel light headed just typing this.

Along with 

&amp;gt;I can't offer a mechanical reason why, just my personal preference. A guillotine looks far, far more menacing than a gun, and would invoke more dread and fear in me.

and

&amp;gt;Well, the specific way someone wants to do isn't really the point, moreso that lethal injection itself is utterly terrifying to me and seems well within the "cruel and unusual" punishment range.

and

&amp;gt;Dying by gas is just as horrifying a thought to me as death by lethal injection.
Overall, I think how someone is to be executed should be up to the person who is going to be executed.

Here's the thing: You are being executed. The reason you are being executed is that you have been found guilty, repeatedly because almost every death sentence case goes through as many appeals as possible, of something that warrants the death penalty. You didn't drive 46 mph in a 45, pay your bus fare in dimes and intentionally come up $0.10 short, roll through a stop sign, or some other illegal activity and the courts have decided you should die. You killed someone. Or multiple someones. There might be a few other things that get the death penalty, but most of the time it's because death was part of the crime. 

Whether or not there are innocent people who are executed, and there is a lot of evidence that points to that happening more frequently than most people are comfortable with is an entirely different argument, but for what we're looking at here, you did something that the criminal justice system has decided should be punishable by death. If you're squeamish around needles, think the guillotine looks scary, gas is horrifying, etc. that shouldn't mean a "chose your own adventure" option. Someone else mentioned "drowning in pussy" as an absurd suggestion, but "having my brain/spinal chord blown all over the place so some guy who's likely getting paid a pretty crap salary has to clean up the little bits of me that are sprayed all over the room" seems like a pretty gruesome punishment for someone who didn't commit a crime.

Personally, I find being put to death by any means terrifying. Does that mean I shouldn't be executed even if I am found guilty of a crime and given the death penalty? Even if I thought "being smothered by 100 kittens" was the best way to go, why are we indulging the criminal's desires when the whole point is that we are punishing them? We give them a last meal as a courtesy, but they are still executed.

Personally, I don't agree with the death penalty. I think that the American justice/penal system (I'm assuming that's where this is coming from) has a lot of problems that need to be addressed and while disincentives and punishments for crimes are necessary to prevent people from committing them, the current system leans more towards vengeance than justice. Instead of asking ourselves "is the punishment sufficient to rehabilitate the criminal and dissuade them (and other potential criminals) from committing crime in the future?" it seems to be more "does the person who the crime effects, or their family feel like their life has been appropriately ruined for the amount of suffering they experienced?" We call it "corrections" or "rehabilitation" in some parts of the world, because the point of the system in every case except the death penalty and life without parole is to release that person back into society hoping they have changed for the better, and that seems to be the part we pay the least attention to, instead of making their lives a living hell for the duration of their incarceration. 

It has also been pointed out that your gun idea has some flaws because of your assumption that gun=instant killing machine. While guns exist to kill things/people they aren't a 100% miracle device, and if you talk to anyone who has been in a situation where guns have been used lethally, they likely have more than a few horror stories about how that isn't the case. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz1fh0s</id>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>The point is that lethal injection would be "cruel and unusual" punishment for me, and many others. The gun option is full-proof if you involve more than one gun. Have 10 guns programmed to fire on the brain. NO ONE is going to survive ten bullets to the brain. 

Even if someone committed a crime so heinous they deserve death in societies eye, it shouldn't be done in a cruel way. That's a very poor reflection on us as a society if we allow that. Punishment should be the last priority of the justice system.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz1n0iy</id>
            <replies>
                <author>MikeCanada</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Justice William Brennan.[3] In Furman v. Georgia, 408 U.S. 238 (1972), Justice Brennan wrote, "There are, then, four principles by which we may determine whether a particular punishment is 'cruel and unusual'."

&amp;gt;The "essential predicate" is "that a punishment must not by its severity be degrading to human dignity," especially torture.

&amp;gt;"A severe punishment that is obviously inflicted in wholly arbitrary fashion." (Furman v. Georgia temporarily suspended capital punishment for this reason.)

&amp;gt;"A severe punishment that is clearly and totally rejected throughout society."

&amp;gt;"A severe punishment that is patently unnecessary."

&amp;gt;And he added: "The function of these principles, after all, is simply to provide means by which a court can determine whether a challenged punishment comports with human dignity. They are, therefore, interrelated, and, in most cases, it will be their convergence that will justify the conclusion that a punishment is "cruel and unusual." The test, then, will ordinarily be a cumulative one: if a punishment is unusually severe, if there is a strong probability that it is inflicted arbitrarily, if it is substantially rejected by contemporary society, and if there is no reason to believe that it serves any penal purpose more effectively than some less severe punishment, then the continued infliction of that punishment violates the command of the Clause that the State may not inflict inhuman and uncivilized punishments upon those convicted of crimes."

That was lifted from our friends over at Wikipedia, but is supposed to be the parameters of the Eighth amendment. So, according to the 8th, you could argue that " there is no reason to believe that it serves any penal purpose more effectively than some less severe punishment" for the death penalty in any form, that it is "patently unnecessary" or any number of other things that conflict directly with the 8th amendment against the death penalty. I would agree with you, and Georgia did too for a while. 

To suggest that lethal injection is "cruel and unusual" for you and anyone else who doesn't like needles, doesn't fall within the definition. If your life was in danger and medical intervention was the answer, short of you sighting religious reasons, they will give you a needle or IV in a hospital regardless to how squeamish you are. If doing a blood test could give them information that could save your life, are you going to deny them from doing that? Have you, and most other people in the western world had needles before without society recoiling at the thought of it? 

You are suggesting that in your situation it would be "A severe punishment that is clearly and totally rejected throughout society." but our society actually strongly encourages and benefits from injections, and the only difference with the legal injection is the contents of the syringe. 

"Something I am not personally comfortable with" does not translate to "cruel and unusual punishment" in the eyes of the law. 

&amp;gt;The gun option is full-proof if you involve more than one gun. Have 10 guns programmed to fire on the brain. NO ONE is going to survive ten bullets to the brain.

There are places where death by firing squad is still an option. While that might not be considered cruel and unusual punishment for the person being shot to death, I would argue that it is for the people that have to pull the trigger(s) and especially the guy who has to clean up the mess. Even if you did your whole "set up a bunch of guns and have them activated by a remote in a different location" someone still needs to point all of the guns at the person to be executed, someone needs to pull the trigger or push the button. That is not an easy thing to do for anyone, (although I doubt the person that has to administer the lethal injection is free of baggage either) but I can't imagine being the guy that has to mop up all the chunks of your brain that are sprayed all over the room, or pry the bullets out of the wall, or move your body from where it ends up to a body bag/casket. We don't have to think just about the person being executed, but the people involved in that process as well. 

&amp;gt;Even if someone committed a crime so heinous they deserve death in societies eye, it shouldn't be done in a cruel way. That's a very poor reflection on us as a society if we allow that. Punishment should be the last priority of the justice system.

I agree and go one step further that society should not be given death as an option. As I mentioned above, I feel that option is often pursued because the victim/their family have a desire for vengeance instead of justice. I just don't agree that your personal definition of "cruel" aligns with the law, death by firing squad could also be someone else's personal definition of "cruel" and we're right back where you started.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1ql06</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>UnknownXV</author>
                    <ReplyBody>By that legal definition I can't argue against it. That 10% of people would consider it cruel doesn't seem to qualify as rejected by society. 

Like you, I wish the death penalty didn't exist at all. It serves little function besides satisfying the perverse and often biblical urge for vengeance that a lot of people have. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1t97o</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>MikeCanada</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Sounds like your view has been changed...</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz1ypue</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>UnknownXV</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I don't know. I can't argue against it within the legal framework presented, but I still think lethal injection shouldn't be the norm. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz1zfrg</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>CatRelatedUsername</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I have a serious phobia of needles and drugs.

Irrelevant. Phobias are, by definition, irrational, so it's not cruel or unusual.

&amp;gt;So the question is, why don't we use a method that is 100% fatal and completely humane, namely a high-powered gun attached to a mechanical trigger (so no one has to hold it manually to fire it) aimed at the back of the neck to sever the spinal cord instantly.

This isn't "100% foolproof." You'd be surprised what the human body can endure. Not to mention you'd need to place the gun in the perfect position, and that position would likely change between offenders due to height, weight, build, body fat, etc. And if you overpower the gun just slightly, or screw up the positioning? You now have the potential to kill a bystander, or the potential to not actually kill the offender, and so we're back to square one. Finally, there'd be quite a bit of mess to clean up afterwards, and the trauma for the bystanders associated with watching someone's neck be blown open.

If you want something that can't really be screwed up; nitrogen asphyxiation. No stress, no mess, no feeling of choking, no lethal chemicals. You just drift out of consciousness and die.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz1jz4k</id>
        <replies>
            <author>UnknownXV</author>
            <ReplyBody>Just because it's an irrational fear doesn't mean it doesn't count in cruel and unusual. It's estimated at least 10% of people have this phobia, so it's not some rare thing that only ten people have. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cz1n39r</id>
            <replies>
                <author>matt-the-great</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Just because it's an irrational fear doesn't mean it doesn't count in cruel and unusual

No, in the legal sense, it does. Cruel and unusual punishment is such that prolongs suffering, is gory (for example--shooting someone with a high-powered gun in the back of the neck), or requires the cooperation of the victim. You being irrationally fearful of needles doesn't make it cruel. It'd be cruel if the injection didn't work (which oftentimes happens) and your suffering was prolonged, but your fear doesn't make it cruel or unusual.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cz1yghv</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>UnknownXV</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Would it be cruel if 50% of people had an irrational fear of needles? Or 90%? </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cz1zggp</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>matt-the-great</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Perhaps if the public deigned death by lethal injection cruel and unusual, maybe. That's different from having an irrational fear of needles. 

I don't think you'd argue that the irrational fear most people have is of death--dying is inevitable and the after-life is unknowable, and thus, illogical to fear, yet death isn't considered cruel and unusual punishment by the populace.

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cz20427</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>UnknownXV</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Fearing something inevitable isn't irrational if it is the epitome of every horror and despair imaginable, which is what death is, oblivion... nothing. 

Fearing death is perhaps the only rational fear to have. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cz20p8v</id>
                            <replies>
<author>matt-the-great</author>
<ReplyBody>It's irrational to be afraid of something that you cannot prevent, and the consequences of which are, to our knowledge, just as likely to be beneficial (a benevolent after-life) as they are to be detrimental (a shitty after-life). It makes sense to fear the pain involved in certain deaths, but not dying itself. You have no idea what happens after death, and will not know until it happens--and it is irrational to fear something you don't, and cannot, know.

You seem to think that oblivion is a negative or fearful thing. How can nothingness be fearful? If you are nothing, you cannot experience nothing--even if the experience of nothing were to be feared, you would not exist to experience it.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cz20v0x</id>
<replies>
    <author>UnknownXV</author>
    <ReplyBody>I do know what happens after death, nothing. There is no after-life, just.. nothing. Which is much worse than the positive of my life.

Fearing a trip to perpetual, eternal neutrality is not irrational, even if it can't be avoided (although thankfully even that is debatable now). </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cz21d68</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>RasslinsnotRasslin</author>
        <ReplyBody>People are squeamish to the responsibility I'd your going to carry out a death sentence it should be hanging, beheading,  or firing squad if you can't manage to find someone willing to execute the sentence because of moral concerns let the person live. 

The idea of turning it over to drugs and the state is cowardice by the people and moral ineptitude. 

Taking a life even of the condemned is nothing good it's a terrible thing to be needing to be done but trying to wash your hands of the act in that means is wrong </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz23y94</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>meur123</author>
        <ReplyBody> &amp;gt;Killing

 &amp;gt;Humane

 &amp;gt;Oxymoron.

There's no justification for capital punishment (or really punishment in general...) 

There's no purpose. Does it make society safer? No. Does it bring back the people that have been killed? No. Criminals aren't going to  cause much harm to the world behind bars so murdering them is completely unnecessary. The idea of punishment is **petty.** It's the way a child would respond to a situation. Prisions should be about preventing further harm to society, and rehabilitation. While I doubt that anyone that you would find on death row would ever be rehabilitated and trusted to walk free, they still deserve the right to live. An eye for an eye makes the world blind.

The idea of killing somebody humanely is fucking sick. It's just a way of making people feel a tiny bit better about cold blooded murder.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cz3dm5o</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <selfText>Currently the primary method to execute the death penalty on a convicted felon is to use lethal injection. There has been a lot of controversy in the recent years surrounding failed attempts in which the person to be executed suffers for hours in tremendous pain. Either due to the drugs being incorrect, the IV being incorrectly played; or any number of other reasons.

It seems to me that this is an extremely inhumane method of killing someone. 

And it goes deeper than the possibility of failure. For my own personal opinion of it, lethal injection would be utter **horror**. I have a serious phobia of needles and drugs. I'd rather die burning alive than receiving a lethal injection. The thought of it, being strapped to a table with an IV jammed into my vein and lethal drugs pumped into my system.. I feel light headed just typing this. 

So the question is, why don't we use a method that is 100% fatal and completely humane, namely a high-powered gun attached to a mechanical trigger (so no one has to hold it manually to fire it) aimed at the back of the neck to sever the spinal cord instantly. 

This would be instantaneous and without any pain for the death row inmate, and far easier to prepare and enact for the prison. 
_____

&amp;gt; *Hello, users of CMV! This is a footnote from your moderators. We'd just like to remind you of a couple of things. Firstly, please remember to* ***[read through our rules](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules)***. *If you see a comment that has broken one, it is more effective to report it than downvote it. Speaking of which,* ***[downvotes don't change views](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/guidelines#wiki_upvoting.2Fdownvoting)****! If you are thinking about submitting a CMV yourself, please have a look through our* ***[popular topics wiki](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/populartopics)*** *first. Any questions or concerns? Feel free to* ***[message us](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=/r/changemyview)***. *Happy CMVing!*</selfText>
</redditSubmission>
