<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>GnosticGnome</author>
        <ReplyBody>You propose to "fix" someone's free will and make them literally unable to act in certain ways?  Isn't that worse than killing them?

And even if some criminals didn't see it that way, changing someone's sentence for undergoing a medical procedure is coercing them to undergo that medical procedure.  Therefore we could never ethically let that influence decisions regarding parole.  So the comparison can't be "death or nerve-stapled", it still remains "death or life without parole".  Nerve-stapling would just be an option for people who were already sentenced to life without parole that would let them rest assured they wouldn't be able to harm any of the other prisoners.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt4aoq</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Squirrel009</author>
            <ReplyBody>I agree, that's messed up and more perverted than killing people. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt56qb</id>
            <replies>
                <author>ShalmaneserIII</author>
                <ReplyBody>Kubrick made a nice movie out of it, though. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwthz1m</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>MasterEmp</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The book is right horrorshow, too, O my brothers.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtjic0</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ShalmaneserIII</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Gave me a pain in the gulliver, though, it did.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtjlz9</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>MasterEmp</author>
                            <ReplyBody>At first I thought it but cal writ by some starry old veck, but I pony it much better now, yes.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwtjvri</id>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>AjRamirez45</author>
                <ReplyBody>Is it? Letting them live in a collaborative society without the will to choose to kill is really worse than not living at all? Then we the readers who have banned books in the USA should leave because better to live in a society with no books then in one which allows only certain books to be read. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtdcw1</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Indenturedsavant</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Your logic is off</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtg3li</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>drdeadringer</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Expand upon this.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtgxpw</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>AjRamirez45</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Then show evidence or even an argument to change my view. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtjirl</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Squirrel009</author>
                    <ReplyBody>that is not at all what I said. Brainwashing is bad, what on earth are you trying to get at with your terrible book analogy?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtky1i</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>AjRamirez45</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I dont know anymore. Is it better to live in a society with limited freedom or in solitude with absolutely no rules. Would the murderer in this case trade in his ability to decide to commit crimes to be able to coexist in society? Or should he let his decision lead him to death?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtnudg</id>
                        <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>26</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>0ed</author>
            <ReplyBody>I'd argue that it isn't evil to "fix" people like this.  Let's say that I'm a paedophile.  I don't want to be a paedophile; I am able to, with great force of will, force myself to not act on my impulses.  But it is still a very unpleasant existence, where I will never be able to enjoy the full range of human experiences and where society will always be suspicious of me.

If someone came up to me and told me he could "fix" me, I would go for it.

It's the same if I were a kleptomaniac.  I don't really want to have the impulse to steal things all the time; and it's only with a great deal of willpower that I'm able to be a proper human being.  I'm losing out on what others have all their entire lives.  If someone can help me, if someone can cure me - I'd go for it.

Same with the sociopath, or the psychopath, or the pathological liar.

"Curing" these people would not be an infringement of their human rights - it would be allowing broken people to have a life once more.  I believe that any rational person would much rather be able to have those impulses removed rather than to live a precarious existence with them.  Or, in the case of the death penalty, die for them.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt9fu0</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Jacen4789</author>
                <ReplyBody>You're listing actual mental diseases where the cure is changing the brain's chemistry.  

OP is talking about someone who murders someone so they either get put to death or life without parole. We would "fix" the murders brain so they could no longer murder.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtb79r</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>chokfull</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I don't think it's different. OP did not go into any specific details, but I believe he is talking about "normalizing" people in the same way, adding empathy and removing perversions, not making it *physically impossible* for them to commit murder.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtcn7f</id>
                    <upvotes>15</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>ThatBelligerentSloth</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Which would almost certainly be a change of brain chemistry. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtdkii</id>
                    <upvotes>6</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>dahlesreb</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The argument here is that with sufficient understanding of the brain, any neurochemical or neurophysiological configuration that would lead someone to murder *is* a mental disease. Murderphilia instead of pedophilia, if you will.

For a good philosophical discussion of this issue I'd recommend [this episode](http://verybadwizards.com/episodes/59) of the Very Bad Wizards podcast. In my opinion it boils down to one's position on determinism/compatibilism with respect to the free will problem.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtequc</id>
                    <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>13</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>14</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>bjw88</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't know. I still think I'd much rather have my mind altered than be killed. Maybe others would rather die?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwta4l4</id>
            <replies>
                <author>rokkshark</author>
                <ReplyBody>Should have thought about that before you hypothetically murdered all those children.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtkyo0</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Ideal4Living</author>
            <ReplyBody>sounds like A Clockwork Orange</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtf0pw</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>Hemingwavy</author>
            <ReplyBody>Literally the only freedom being taken from them is a freedom that if they exercised they'd be put to death. It doesn't seem like much choice is being taken from them. You're just refusing to look at the idea of tinkering in people's minds. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtdhpu</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>gregbrahe</author>
            <ReplyBody>A Clockwork Orange? </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtf6g4</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>thek826</author>
            <ReplyBody>How is being rendered mentally averse to committing a crime worse than being executed? Can you expand on that?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtjhbk</id>
            <replies>
                <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>Everyone dies.  Not everyone has their humanity stripped from them, leaving them a mockery of their former self.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtjr34</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>thek826</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I agree, but I don't believe that that's what is being proposed by the OP. If we were talking about total external control of one's brain to make them a slave to the state, I'd be very much against such a scenario, but no one is advocating for that.

How is being rendered mentally averse to committing a crime having "their humanity stripped from them, leaving them a mockery of their former self?"

----

(Not as relevant to the OP's post but something I'm curious about):

Also, as an aside, if being prevented from acting in a certain way is indeed a fate worse than death, what do you think about imprisonment, especially imprisonment for life? That's a *far* more invasive restriction of freedom (compared to the influencing of an aspect of one's psyche) that is typically considered less harsh than the death penalty. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtjuve</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                        <ReplyBody>OP talked about changing my psyche and guaranteeing.  Maybe that colored my interpretation.

I would say fine &amp;lt; corporal punishment &amp;lt; short imprisonment &amp;lt; maiming  &amp;lt; long imprisonment=death &amp;lt; rewriting my psyche.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtkpme</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>basscorruption</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't know what "fix" means nor can I give any reasonable inference as to what it will mean.  It's not set to a "medical procedure" that's going to "influence decisions."  It's not a black and white issue.  I don't know what the future is.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt5fas</id>
            <replies>
                <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>Can you give me an example of some kind of plausible future development (no matter how unlikely it is to be developed in the next century) that meets your criteria?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt5ws8</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>Redgum1</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I am not he and don't really like this CMV, but regardless. It is plausible that advances in psychology could prevent most recidivism, as most people aren't psychopaths removing them from crime inducing environments and offering very good therapy could theoretically stop them from committing more crimes. 
If they in fact do have mental issues better chemotherapeutics for mental issues may help. However I don't think 100% certainty is possible here, for that you might need a shock collar. However I don't think the methods proposed are immoral. However such advancement in therapy seems unlikely for the moment. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwt6uhl</id>
                    <upvotes>4</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>basscorruption</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I don't know exactly what you mean.  Can you be very specific?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwt66jj</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ben_nystrom</author>
                        <ReplyBody>You are asking us to make a moral  judgment based on something that may never come to pass. Unless you have some specific evidence that what you think might happen will happen, how can we possibly use it to make moral decisions today?  Zebras might fly, trees might burst in the volcanoes, the sun might turn into cheese, those are all technically possibilities but none of them help me live today and are silly to think might actually come to pass. You need evidence, and you are presenting none. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwt6v7c</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>therealjew</author>
                            <ReplyBody>It is impossible to change the view of a man who does not understand his viewpoint. This is a losing argument.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwt8x1b</id>
                            <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <replies>
                            <author>basscorruption</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; You are asking us to make a moral judgment based on something that may never come to pass.

That's exactly my argument.

&amp;gt; Unless you have some specific evidence that what you think might happen will happen, how can we possibly use it to make moral decisions today? ... You need evidence, and you are presenting none.

I don't think it requires any evidence other than the future is assumed to be uncertain.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwt760o</id>
                            <replies>
<author>cilica</author>
<ReplyBody>But then your argument can be aplied to everything: it is immoral to &amp;lt;insert stuff here&amp;gt; because the future might do...something.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwt7fk3</id>
<replies>
    <author>czerilla</author>
    <ReplyBody>It is immoral to reduce risk of lung cancer, since that might cause someone to be motivated to research it more and come up with the cure that wouldn't have existed, if that person hadn't gotten cancer themselves...</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwt7ow2</id>
    <upvotes>4</upvotes>
</replies>
<replies>
    <author>fuckindumplins</author>
    <ReplyBody>I would argue that with psychology and neurology being pretty new sciences, and psychiatry a very young form of medicine with so much to gain in the future, OP's argument has a lot more merit than any old random thing. I think a lot of criminal activity spurns from undiagnosed mental illness and our whole system, if it progresses healthily and based on scientific evidence, will shift toward rehabilitation and treatment for mental illness in the future. Mental illness might also become more broadly defined in the future, or at least we may admit that most people can benefit from psychiatric treatment of some kind. I can't change OP's view because I relate to it too much, but I also think that people focusing on OP's "lack of evidence" wastes time and misses the point.

But I am a psych student working in public services, so that's my bias...</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwtilaw</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>7</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>ben_nystrom</author>
<ReplyBody> OK, I've got a bag and in that bag is a mysterious substance. You can't see it and you have no idea what it is however I promise you in the future there is a distinct possibility that what I have in my bag will be incredibly valuable. I will sell it to you for the meager price of $500,000.  Are you willing to purchase that bag based on zero evidence that it actually contain something that might one day be valuable? 

 More to the point, do you expect anyone to agree with you if you have no evidence? </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwt7gn0</id>
<replies>
    <author>hacksoncode</author>
    <ReplyBody>OP is explicitly prohibited from "getting people to agree with them" by Rule B, so it's rather irrelevant to changing his view to say that no one might agree with them. </ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwt90k6</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>8</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>therealjew</author>
<ReplyBody>The point they are trying to make, is that you can argue that in 2 years angels from heaven will rain down JusticePunch^^TM and rescue humanity from all crime. We don't know the future and can't know the future, but something implausible like that can likely be ruled out. What you seem to be implying is a medical procedure or psychological hypnotism that can control a person's actions. Maybe you mean a microchip, or a drug, or physical corrective torture, or extensive rehabilitation training, or fucking brainwash waves, but no matter what kind of mind control the future hold, that's the future and in any case, wrong. You can't spend inordinate amounts of money now in the hopes that some miracle will happen in the course of a criminals lifespan. To be fair, the death penalty at present is in no way cost effective, and there is an abnormally high number of "false positives". The system itself needs to be reworked, but while its under heavy fire as to its existence, that can be difficult to achieve. 

No matter what the individual did, the thing that most people consider "what makes us human" is our ability to choose. If you forcefully take that from someone, through drugs, therapy, or torture, you are in many ways the monster you're trying to change. You aren't ending a life, you are perverting an existence to better suit YOUR standard of normal without regards to their perspective. Who gets to decide what "Crimes" are punishable by reeducation? Now that we are "Better than the criminals" and we don't kill people, why should reeducation stop at the worst offenders? Why don't we do it to drug addicts, and thieves. Why not jaywalkers? Why stop at criminals? We can change the inner workings of anyone with "undesirable traits". Lets make the furries "Normal". Lets change gays, and republicans, and jews, and atheists! 

The issue of augmenting a persons ability to choose means you are effectively forcing your ideals on them in a way they have no defense for. I would much rather get a nice last meal and a 15 minute death ritual than have to live as some zombie dictated by some senators notion or "moral", and if we let politicians do it to the criminals, we'll let them do it to free people too. The possible future of reeducation exists, but should only ever be used voluntarily. The part of the US constitution regarding "Cruel and unusual punishment" is there specifically for this reason. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwt9q0x</id>
<upvotes>2</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-6</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>8</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>9</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>104</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Yesofcoursenaturally</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;it is immoral to act with the death penalty because we can or may be able to "fix" them at a future date. 

The death penalty is argued for on the grounds of justice, not merely as an efficient way to deal with problematic individuals.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt4u5h</id>
        <replies>
            <author>Blytheway</author>
            <ReplyBody>The purpose of justice is to create order in a civilized society. A punishment therefore should not be for the sake of justice but for the sake of order. 

Yes there should be severe punishments for severe crimes but death is not the only option nor is it the most humane option.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt7681</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Yesofcoursenaturally</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The purpose of justice is to create order in a civilized society.

No, that's a nice side-effect of justice. Justice could demand something that would create disorder - say, impeaching a popular president who has no obvious replacement. Justice isn't easy.

&amp;gt;Yes there should be severe punishments for severe crimes but death is not the only option nor is it the most humane option.

Sometimes, death may be the most just and moral sentence. I see no reason to automatically accept that it's either inhumane or always one of a number of options.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt7bt2</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>iCantSpelWerdsGud</author>
                    <ReplyBody>*Laws* are not for justice, laws are for order.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtjhee</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>xiccit</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Laws are for the percieved  benefit of those that create them, not order.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtuxcs</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>Blytheway</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Justice could demand something that would create disorder

That is very true.

What then would you say justice's purpose is then if not for order? Surely justice can't be present for the sake of justice.


&amp;gt;Sometimes, death may be the most just and moral sentence.

In what cases? If other countries with similar modernized judicial systems like France, U.K., and Canada felt that capital punishment is unnecessary, clearly they've found ways around it.

EDIT: a word</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwt984z</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Yesofcoursenaturally</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;What then would you say justice's purpose is then if not for order? Surely justice can't be present for the sake of justice.

What's the purpose of order?

&amp;gt;In what cases? If other countries with similar modernized judicial systems like France, U.K., and Canada felt that capital punishment is unnecessary, clearly they've found ways around it.

That they do something different is no demonstration that they've 'found ways' to achieve justice without capital punishment. Saudi Arabia does things differently too. Quite orderly as well, last I checked. Are they doing a stellar job with justice?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtaftg</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>Blytheway</author>
                            <ReplyBody>The purpose of order is so each of us can thrive without stepping on each other's shoes.

Canada has 3 times [a lower murder rate](http://www.nationmaster.com/country-info/compare/Canada/United-States/Crime) than America per million people. [France](http://www.nationmaster.com/country-info/compare/France/United-States/Crime) and [U.K.'s](http://www.nationmaster.com/country-info/compare/United-Kingdom/United-States/Crime) rates are 4 times lower.

Clearly they're doing something right. If any country follows the reasoning "justice because justice" then you're missing point of the people justice protects. Speaking of which:

&amp;gt;Saudi Arabia does things differently too.

Well yeah. They follow the Sharia which holds pretty close to their religion. Where they take an eye for an eye literally. Justice for the sake of justice.

Also you haven't answered my other question. What are cases where the death penalty is the most moral and humane?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwtc098</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Yesofcoursenaturally</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;The purpose of order is so each of us can thrive without stepping on each other's shoes.

What's the purpose of that?

&amp;gt;Clearly they're doing something right. 

Would it be 'having vastly different demographics'?

&amp;gt;Well yeah. They follow the Sharia which holds pretty close to their religion. Where they take an eye for an eye literally. Justice for the sake of justice.

Yep - with a lower murder rate than the US too. Hong Kong? 0.6, putting Canada to shame. Qatar? 0.8.

Shall we be emulating them?

&amp;gt;What are cases where the death penalty is the most moral and humane?

Oh, easy. A man breaks into a woman's home. She tries to scream, and he immediately cracks her in the head with a bat. Her preteen daughter is in the room and is panicking - he ties her up. Then rapes both of them. Then kills them.

That is one case where the death penalty is the most moral and humane.

Now, if it turned out that he would never, ever do this again, what do you think about letting him go after this was confirmed, and letting him go to work in a nice job at the bank, where he'd be a productive member of society from that point on, and in fact quite wealthy, successful and comfortable?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwtcfwu</id>
<replies>
    <author>roadbuzz</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; What's the purpose of that?

What do you think is the purpose of morale and ethics, do you think it's been handed to us by god and has no natural purpose? No, ethics arises from both our biologic and societal evolution. Ethics enables us  to interact with one another and be more prolific which in turn leads to a happier life for most people.

&amp;gt; Yep - with a lower murder rate than the US too. Hong Kong? 0.6, putting Canada to shame. Qatar? 0.8.
Shall we be emulating them?

The question is what we want more, freedom or safety? Everyone has different priorities. The death penalty serves neither freedom nor safety.

&amp;gt; Now, if it turned out that he would never, ever do this again, what do you think about letting him go after this was confirmed, and letting him go to work in a nice job at the bank, where he'd be a productive member of society from that point on, and in fact quite wealthy, successful and comfortable?

There is noway to confirm that he won't kill again, a therapy with a high improbability of a relapse as OP envisions would yield a reasonable security.

But I also think that you can't take people's sense of justice out of the equation entirely. The death penalty however is no ample instrument for it, it's too final and the rate of wrongful convictions is way too high.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwtfwj7</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<replies>
    <author>Blytheway</author>
    <ReplyBody>Wow disproved me with my own sources. I don't think there'd any saving myself from this aha. You did splendidly. But one final note.

&amp;gt;A man breaks into a woman's home. She tries to scream, and he immediately cracks her in the head with a bat. Her preteen daughter is in the room and is panicking - he ties her up. Then rapes both of them. Then kills them.

No matter how hard I try I still see a man. Not a monster. If he turned his life around, his joy is mine. But then again that's assuming he'd live to see the end of his sentence.

Anyway those are just some final thoughts not really a rebuttal. My white flag is raised.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwtj2yc</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <replies>
                        <author>pheen0</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Justice has no societal purpose, it just is.  And it's evolutionarily ancient.  If you ask two dogs to perform a trick but only reward one, the un-rewarded dog will recognize that something is amiss.  [source](http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=97944783)  Monkeys do it too.  [source2](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-KSryJXDpZo)

You can call that fairness, justice, or whatever you want.  But almost certainly, that recognition of inequality and the desire to see the scales balanced is where our sense of justice comes from.  That's really all "an eye for an eye" is.

Edit: I guess I should say justice NEEDS no societal purpose, rather than HAS.  You can imagine that the threat of scales being balanced on you provides some disincentive.  </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtdbmv</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>12</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>xiccit</author>
                <ReplyBody>Oh hell everyone in this thread should now go read platos Republic chapter one.  What does it mean to be "just" anyways?

I don't think we should kill anyone</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtuwv4</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>walruz</author>
            <ReplyBody>That argument holds no water, though:

* It is cheaper, in money, to keep someone locked up for life than it is to execute them (in the US).

* It is trivial to adjust the comfort of a prison stay to make life in prison either preferable to being killed, or less preferable.

So the two justice arguments would be that either these pieces of shit aren't worth society's resources to keep alive, and that these pieces of shit deserve to die because of all the horrible stuff they've done.

Since keeping them locked up is cheaper, the first argument fails. Since it is trivial to make life in prison more vengeful than simply killing them, the second argument fails as well.

The third point is that you can release a prisoner if more evidence surfaces, whereas you can't do that to a corpse.

So even if you think that the government has any business killing people, and even if you think that some people are simply irredeemable, and even if you think that the purpose of the justice system is to deliver vengeance instead of rehabilitation, prison is still preferable to execution. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwu0ewg</id>
            <replies>
                <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Since it is trivial to make life in prison more vengeful than simply killing them, the second argument fails as well.

No.  People who believe in vengeance believe that the punishment must fit the crime and not that there is a specific amount of suffering that is appropriate to each crime.

Besides, even if we were talking about Hitler himself there is a strong argument to be made that "we do not torture" is more important than giving him everything he deserves.  So if hypothetically American soldiers had captured Hitler, it would be appropriate for them to kill him or give him to Soviet soldiers, but not for them to torture him.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwu0is4</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>walruz</author>
                    <ReplyBody>If we attach any weight to the argument that "We do not torture", which is simply a statement without any supporting arguments, we must place equal weight in the argument "We do not murder defenseless people".

In order for the statement "We do not torture" to make sense, we must examine *why* we do not torture. The reason that we do not torture prisoners to extract information is that it just doesn't work. However, the only reason that we don't torture people for shits and giggles - the reason that we wouldn't torture a person purely for vengeance's sake - is either that it doesn't serve a purpose, or that we feel that it is barbaric. However, both of those reasons apply equally well to execution. You can't argue against torture and argue for execution when the same arguments apply to both cases.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwu0p0n</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>GnosticGnome</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Unless you live in a country with a moral compass based on some holy books that are often interpreted to forbid torture but permit execution.  Where we draw these moral lines can't be derived purely on reason ignoring our religious history.  Besides how can you argue for imprisonment.  Depriving people of freedom can be argued against by the same arguments if we are going to try to rely on pure reason.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwu0trx</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>walruz</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Unless you live in a country with a moral compass based on some holy books that are often interpreted to forbid torture but permit execution.

But since such an argument would just boil down to "We don't torture people but we do kill people, because God", it is countered by an argument along the lines of "Actually, we do torture people, but we don't kill people, because God".

&amp;gt;Besides how can you argue for imprisonment. Depriving people of freedom can be argued against by the same arguments if we are going to try to rely on pure reason.

How so?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwu1pse</id>
                            <replies>
<author>GnosticGnome</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;But since such an argument would just boil down to "We don't torture people but we do kill people, because God", it is countered by an argument along the lines of "Actually, we do torture people, but we don't kill people, because God".

Er, no.  It would only be countered that way if you can actually change my or most Americans' theology, which is a nontrivial task.

Basically I and most Americans start with a premise: torture is never an acceptable just punishment.  It might be acceptable to extract information and might not, depending on practicality - but it is never an acceptable punishment.  That's just a premise based on theology and history that you will find most Americans hold.

Most Americans do not hold the starting premise "execution is always wrong regardless of the crime".  Some do, and enough hold a related premise "execution is so inefficient in this country that it isn't worth bothering over" that execution is banned in some states without a majority. 

&amp;gt;How so?

Just that if you are going to admit minority premises, there's one.  So to show why one minority premise gets to be introduced into the equation even when others don't, you'd need some compelling reason why.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwu2lyi</id>
<replies>
    <author>walruz</author>
    <ReplyBody>Since nobody has ever presented a credible argument for the correctness of any religion, religious arguments can *always* be dismissed out of hand. If they can't, my argument that my God always disagrees with your God is a perfect refutation of any argument you can come up with. Whether more people agree with you or not is immaterial, because just believing in something doesn't change the world: The Earth wasn't flat even back when everyone believed that it was.

The only arguments you make are axioms: They are impossible to argue against and thus by necessity impossible to argue in favour of. "Lots of Christians believe this thing" isn't an argument.

To be able to credibly make an argument along the lines of "Most Americans hold that this principle is true", you'd have to show *why* it is reasonable to agree with them. As it stands, all of your arguments are just circular.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwu3465</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Yesofcoursenaturally</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;It is cheaper, in money, to keep someone locked up for life than it is to execute them (in the US).

So?

&amp;gt;It is trivial to adjust the comfort of a prison stay to make life in prison either preferable to being killed, or less preferable.

So?

&amp;gt;Since keeping them locked up is cheaper, the first argument fails. 

What argument are you talking about? Because I sure didn't mention 'price' at any point here.

&amp;gt;Since it is trivial to make life in prison more vengeful than simply killing them, the second argument fails as well.

It's also 'trivial' to make executions vastly cheaper. Dare I say, it's more 'trivial' than it is to make life in prison "more vengeful". You're equivocating like crazy here.

&amp;gt;The third point is that you can release a prisoner if more evidence surfaces, whereas you can't do that to a corpse.

And if more crimes are committed in prison - if people are assaulted, maimed or even killed - what shall we do then?

&amp;gt;So even if you think that the government has any business killing people

'The government is incompetent and untrustworthy' is a fantastic argument against the death penalty being used by the government, and close to a non-sequitur with regards to whether execution is itself just.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwumjcg</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>20</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Fellgnome</author>
        <ReplyBody>Fixing someone in that way raises the question: might we just be killing them and creating a *different* person? 

It also suggests we have an obligation to keep people alive regardless of the damage they've done to society. I think that's not true, and especially not if it's costly.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt4pme</id>
        <replies>
            <author>celeritas365</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Fixing someone in that way begs the question: might we just be killing them and creating a different person?

If you accidentally strike someone's head and they lose a memory have you killed them? If someone has a brain tumor that influences their behavior and it is removed by a surgeon has the surgeon killed that person? If you give someone advice that changes their personality have you killed them? If the technology in question existed and someone used it to quit smoking would that be suicide?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt7zwq</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Fellgnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; If you accidentally strike someone's head and they lose a memory have you killed them?

No.

&amp;gt;  If someone has a brain tumor that influences their behavior and it is removed by a surgeon has the surgeon killed that person?

No.

&amp;gt; If you give someone advice that changes their personality have you killed them? 

That's not how personality works(it's more innate, according to current science), but this is more arguable than the above two examples since personality is more important than just being alive to many people.

&amp;gt; If the technology in question existed and someone used it to quit smoking would that be suicide?

No.

___

But these are all very different from doing something as dramatic as it'd need to be to take a psychopath(who're the people most likely to be impossible to rehabilitate through more traditional means) and give them empathy. That far more completely changes them than anything in your examples.  </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt8mx3</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>celeritas365</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Where is the line? That is what I was getting at.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtbtc6</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Fellgnome</author>
                        <ReplyBody>There's currently no real line, because we don't understand the brain well enough plus at some point it's a problem of deciding what is/isn't essential to a personality. I'd put empathy in the essential category.

But regardless, I don't think it's ever immoral for a society to dispose of those who murder, rape, etc. They aren't owed life, and by taking or damaging someone else's they lose any legal right to it which seems very fair to me. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtg5js</id>
                        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <replies>
                    <author>[deleted]</author>
                    <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtcfgx</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Fellgnome</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I believe there is no cure for psychopathy that doesn't equate to fundamentally changing that person to the point that the original person just isn't there anymore. And I don't think forcing that on someone is any better than killing them. 


It's not a state of mind thing, it's not like depression or something more situational and chemical. 

There are also plenty of psychopaths who have as much control over their mental states as anyone else.


Sure, some sort of "fix" could be offered as an option, but I don't think if you're in prison for any serious violent crime that you're owed that choice in any way or that it would be immoral for anyone to sentence you to death instead. 


</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwtfx4s</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>OzymandiasXCV</author>
                            <ReplyBody>
&amp;gt;I believe there is no cure for psychopathy that doesn't equate to fundamentally changing that person to the point that the original person just isn't there anymore. 

&amp;gt;It's not a state of mind thing, it's not like depression or something more situational and chemical. 

Well I'll stop you right there, because everything you've just said is [wrong.](https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/mindmelding/201301/what-is-psychopath-0) and there is more than an [abundance](http://psychcentral.com/news/2012/05/11/scans-show-psychopaths-have-brain-abnormalities/38540.html) of [literature](http://psychcentral.com/news/2010/03/17/why-do-people-become-psychopaths/12193.html) [available](http://www.psychiatrictimes.com/psychotic-affective-disorders/hidden-suffering-psychopath) to you so that you can understand why [you're wrong](http://www.psychologicalscience.org/index.php/news/releases/psychopathy-a-misunderstood-personality-disorder.html)

Which this all raises the question, if you don't even understand what psychopathy is, why are you even trying to answer this question? What is the compulsion there? Again you can shill for the death penalty as you wish, but don't bring your misconceptions of mental illness into the discussion.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwtgoi5</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Fellgnome</author>
<ReplyBody>I'm not seeing anything to directly contradict me here. I'm not disputing that there are brain abnormalities in psychopaths, but a brain abnormality is not an illness or impairment necessarily. Sometimes we just don't like the differences, and define altering them as a fix - I'm all for allowing people to choose to alter themselves but forcing it on people isn't so far away from killing their personality. Your brain structure defines your personality, so dramatic changes to it can essentially render someone so different their former self doesn't exist anymore. I would make a distinction between that kind of approach and what we think of as a "cure". It's not like anti-depressants or cognitive behavioral therapy.

&amp;gt; Several questions need addressing. What does the possibility that psychopathy is genetic say about human nature? What steps can we take to “correct” psychopaths and which of these is the most ethical? If it is true that psychopaths have damaged or abnormal brains, can we hold them responsible for what they do? Are there degrees of psychopathy, so that normal people may possess psychopathic traits?

This ends pretty open ended too and suggests as I've said that it may well be innate. And it's hard to make objective distinction between damaged and abnormal in this case. For some psychopaths their abnormality may be beneficial to them or even others even if that isn't their intention.  

</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwtjxoc</id>
<replies>
    <author>[deleted]</author>
    <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cwtm1rx</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>0ed</author>
            <ReplyBody>Changing who I am, for the better, is always a good thing.  That's what human beings are for, that's why we exist - we always try to improve ourselves even further.  That's why we're never satisfied with what we have.

Look, let's say that I'm a paedophile.  I have an irrational sexual attraction to children.  I don't want this kind of sexual attraction; it's closed off to me my right as a human being to have a normal sex life with a normal partner.  In addition, I always have to exert a great force of will to prevent myself from acting on my impulses.  I feel that I am a ticking time bomb.  The society hates me for it.

And all of a sudden, some doctors come up and offers me an opportunity.  They can make those impulses go away.  They can make me a normal person once more.

Would I go for it, even if it would change who I am?  Hell yes.  

Your second point was regarding society's obligation to its individual members.  Of course we have an obligation for them.  Contrary to popular belief, death row inmates are people too.  Quite often, they're actually very, very broken people who got screwed over by the system so badly that they snapped and did something stupid.  The entire reason they are killed is because society has screwed them so badly that we don't know how to put them back together again.  Through the mistakes of society, they are denied a normal human existence, and their existence becomes a liability to others.  It's too bad for them; but since they cannot be fixed, society decides to kill them.

If society can fix these people - if we can make them human, once more, if society can find a way to repay its debts - then, we should help them.  If you're still not convinced by the moral argument for the humane treatment of prisoners, then try the economic argument.

Criminals are considered a liability to society because they do not actively produce anything.  The entire purpose of the prison system is to reform criminals so that they become useful to the society.  Prisoners who may not contribute to the economy no matter how much they are reformed are given the death penalty.  That's the economic explanation for the death penalty.

Now, if we have a medical procedure that can make ANY criminal as productive as a normal member of the society - then of course we would not carry out the death penalty.  It's senseless, and is counterproductive.  The only rational excuse then for the death penalty would be if the cost of treatment exceeded the benefits that the prisoner could bring to society.  Of course, this brings us back to the moral argument - because a doctor can't very well deny a cancer patient treatment on the basis that they're 81 and probably won't be going off to work even if their cancer was cured.  Therefore, prisoners in general ought to be cured of their criminal impulses.  Because they deserve a chance at life as well, and also because it's economically beneficial to the society as a whole.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt9yqh</id>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>walruz</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I think that's not true, and especially not if it's costly.

The thing is, it isn't costly. In the US, it is cheaper to keep a person locked up for life in a maximum security prison than it is to execute them. If you'd argue for making executions cheaper, you'd best keep in mind the fact that despite the majority of the costs of executing someone being related to trial costs, the US still manages to execute people who are innocent.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwu0gkk</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Fellgnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>I am not pro death penalty in the current situation due to how flawed our process is currently, but the procedure of altering criminals to no longer be able to / inclined to commit crimes *could* definitely be expensive - remember the OP is supposing a hypothetical future here.  And of course, the death penalty could also be made much less expensive. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwu4d54</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>conceptalbum</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Fixing someone in that way begs the question

No, it raises the question. Those are different things.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt8h8z</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Fellgnome</author>
                <ReplyBody>TIL, never really looked into that idiom!</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt8s8e</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>conceptalbum</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Thanks! People seldomly respond so positively to my pedantry.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtb5fs</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>9</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ben_nystrom</author>
        <ReplyBody>I may not know what the future holds, but I know this ability to permanently and safely alter someone's personality and behavioral tendencies is not around corner. Unless you know evidence this is being developed/possible I have no reason to think such an ability will ever come to pass. 

Your suggestion is like saying it is immoral to have pets because the future might reveal them to be perfectly intelligent beings that are being dumbed down by their captivity. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt4z35</id>
        <replies>
            <author>xiccit</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I may not know what the future holds, but I know this ability to permanently and safely alter someone's personality and behavioral tendencies is not around the corner"

No you dont.  Nobody expects monumental breakthroughs, and they happen every day.  You cannot predict the future, nor can I

That being said, even against the ethical problems in the argument,  if it's due to having certain types of neurons being over prevalent  -http://m.medicalxpress.com/news/2015-11-neurons-reprogrammed-animals.html</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtv1l3</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>basscorruption</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Your suggestion is like saying it is immoral to have pets because the future might reveal them to be perfectly intelligent beings that are being dumbed down by their captivity. 

I don't know how you can make this jump from me not knowing what the future holds to intelligent beings being "dumbed down."  Couldn't it also be "smartened up?"  Surely there are some genetic traits that humans hold that aren't ideal (fingernails keep growing, just stop already), changing those wouldn't be "dumbing down" the species.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt5ip2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>ben_nystrom</author>
                <ReplyBody>Right...the logic is dumb...that's my point. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt6q3i</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>basscorruption</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You mean your logic is dumb?  Because I'm sure we'd all agree with that.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwt6u9i</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>ben_nystrom</author>
                        <ReplyBody> OK, if I really have to spell it out for you that much, your logic, and the logic I used in my example, are the same. You are suggesting that because something might happen in the future that we need to make moral decisions today based on that possibility. However, the future could hold anything. We have no way of knowing what might happen in the future.  Yes, that is a point we clearly agree on, however, it's not appropriate to make decisions today based on things that may or may not ever come to pass. If you have no evidence to suggest that it is possible to permanently and safely alter someone's mind, then your question, your logic, and your point is moot. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwt79kx</id>
                        <upvotes>10</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-17</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>8</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>SC803</author>
                <ReplyBody>So when your fingernail breaks it'll never grow back?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt5w6j</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>basscorruption</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Not sure if you're trying to be an asshole or not, but I'll pretend you're not.  I don't know how or what could be done to make it so we don't need to keep cutting our finger nails and keep the benefits of having nails in tact.  But could there be a time when we could?  You need to not look at it as a this is how things are done now or how things could be conceivably done later.  Does that make my original post clearer for you?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwt65ag</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>SC803</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; keep cutting our finger nails and keep the benefits of having nails in tact.

They would have to harden to extreme levels, the added weight would be a drawback. I'd hope they'd stay the same, trimming nails is easy and begin able to grow them back quickly is a pretty good trait to have

&amp;gt; But could there be a time when we could?

There could be, we could evolve into more bird like creatures too. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cwt6qu7</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>basscorruption</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; They would have to harden to extreme levels, the added weight would be a drawback. I'd hope they'd stay the same, trimming nails is easy and begin able to grow them back quickly is a pretty good trait to have

You have no idea if we could say make finger nails grow back in an instant with no need to cut them or have it so we don't need fingernails at all at a later date.

&amp;gt; There could be, we could evolve into more bird like creatures too. 

Cool?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cwt6x1x</id>
                            <replies>
<author>TagaKain</author>
<ReplyBody>So your argument is that anything can happen in the future? Then I'd argue that killing off criminals will lead to humanity advancing faster than ever by removing their negative influence.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwt7zwb</id>
<upvotes>3</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>naliuj2525</author>
<ReplyBody>Sorry, but you're just ridiculous.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cwtckg4</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-7</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-8</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-8</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>6</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NowICanUpvoteStuff</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'm not pro-death penalty but your argument seems inconclusive to me. It seems to rest on the premise that everyone who commits an offense that will lead to the death penalty does so because she or he is somehow flawed. Are you really ruling out the possibility that someone is perfectly sane and still, for example, killing someone else? If yes: Why so? If no: What then would there be to fix?

Your argument could still work for cases in which someone is somehow fixable flawed - but only for those.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt6sps</id>
        <replies>
            <author>basscorruption</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I'm not pro-death penalty but your argument seems inconclusive to me. It seems to rest on the premise that everyone who commits an offense that will lead to the death penalty does so because she or he is somehow flawed. Are you really ruling out the possibility that someone is perfectly sane and still, for example, killing someone else? If yes: Why so? If no: What then would there be to fix?

&amp;gt; Your argument could still work for cases in which someone is somehow fixable flawed - but only for those.

Not exactly what I was going for.  I was trying to put it into very easily understood terms.  The "flaw" could be the ability to kill someone.  Take that away.  This isn't about mental illness or someones sanity.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt6ztj</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>Everyone has the ability to kill someone. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt84hi</id>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Treypyro</author>
                <ReplyBody>Everyone has the ability, and sometimes the urge, to kill someone.

Sometimes it's about mental illness, a paranoid schizophrenic will kill out of irrational fear. Sometimes it's about anger, a guy finds his wife cheating on him with his best friend. Sometimes it's about honor, war is justified mass murder.

How would you propose taking away someone's ability to kill someone? The only ways I could see working would be the death penalty, lifetime solitary confinement, or putting them in a vegetative state for the rest of their lives. The death penalty seems like the most humane of those options to me.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtfqgv</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>NowICanUpvoteStuff</author>
                <ReplyBody>Ah, thanks for the clarification.

I think you're using our language a little strangely: How is an ability a flaw? I don't want to play a game of semantics, I want to understand your position. So could you please explain when something is considered a flaw? If it allowed the behavior we until now punish with the death sentence?

If yes your argument should exclude the "knowing-the-future"-part, because we don't need it. We can imprison people now and we can imprison them for life. It would be able to do this in a way that they can never kill anyone again. (I'm not making an argument about adequate sentence, I just don't think you need some unsure-future-part in your argument.)</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt7aun</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>What is that "thing" you are talking about? Killing drive? People make their own decisions, the fact they choose options that you wouldn't even consider doesn't mean they are broken.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt6qn0</id>
        <replies>
            <author>basscorruption</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't know what the "thing" is.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt6tg9</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>If I invent a rule and a punishment, and yet you decide to ignore it, what would be the "thing" I must "fix"?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt7mx1</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Agastopia</author>
        <ReplyBody>If argue that it's almost more immoral to just start changing people's brains to reflect what the government wants out of the population. You can't see the possible level of corruption that could occur? Sounds like a great way to begin a dictatorship. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt7vha</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>txanarchy</author>
        <ReplyBody>The death penalty is nothing more than that: a penalty.

There are people on this planet that deserve to have their life ripped away from them the way they ripped the life from their victims. I find your idea far more immoral because you haven't meted out the proper punishment for someone deserving of death. And what do you mean by "fixing" a person? How do you "fix" a person that murders someone in cold blood? Why would you fix them? They've obviously demonstrated that they place no value on human life and are not fit to live in society. 

I also find life in prison to be immoral. If someone deserves to be locked in a cage for the rest of their life then just put them down. It is cruel and inhumane to lock a person up in a prison cell for the rest of their life. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt9014</id>
        <replies>
            <author>RexAnglorumSaxonum</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; There are people on this planet that deserve to have their life ripped away from them the way they ripped the life from their victims.

And 

&amp;gt;I also find life in prison to be immoral. 

Are my stances as well. There's a lot of talk about the treatment of the accused but what about the heinous things done to the victims? Where's their justice? And can any sane or humane person really say that life in a prison cell is humane?

I believe the litmus for the death penalty should extraordinarily high, beyond, beyond a shadow of a doubt. In those cases, I support the death penty wholeheartedly.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwteeco</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>The problem with that conception of justice is that it's bordering on revenge, and revenge is not a good societal norm to follow. It does not help the victims in any way to kill the perpetrator; it merely satisfies their lust for vengeance. They need money and therapy, not a false sense of security from knowing somebody died for their suffering. Especially with the costs of death penalty - even with the lower-than-ideal parole/certainty standards of the United States - being higher than those of life in prison.

Also, it violates another norm (that has shown to be quite effective in many countries as a basis of a justice system) which is the possibility of a second chance. If the system assumes that people can change, and offers them the possibility to get out of prison and get a decent life if they can show that they have improved as human beings, the rate of repeat offenders drops demonstrably. In the few cases where the perpetrator can be shown unable to rehabilitate to a high certainty, such as in the case of Anders Breivik, the process of death penalty would still end up costing more to the society.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtvlof</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>RexAnglorumSaxonum</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; which is the possibility of a second chance

Where's the second chance for the victims? Once someone has been victimized or killed there's no taking it back or undoing it. This creates a debt and I feel that for heinous crimes the perpetrator must pay for that debt with his life. 

&amp;gt; In the few cases where the perpetrator can be shown unable to rehabilitate to a high certainty, such as in the case of Anders Breivik, the process of death penalty would still end up costing more to the society.

I still beg to differ because it doesn't have to be that way. The crimal justice system doesn't have to be needlessly drawn out in cases where there is sufficient evidence for a conviction of this sort.

Is there an aspect of vengeance to it? Yes absolutely, I simply believe the focus should be on the victims, rather than the well being of the perpetrator.

&amp;gt;It does not help the victims in any way to kill the perpetrator; it merely satisfies their lust for vengeance.

Do you have a family? A wife, children? I do and I am proud to live in a democracy where my support for the death penalty is heard and I can rest easy knowing that at night. I rest easy because if someone kidnaps, rapes, and murders my wife and daughters then I won't have to find the guy and kill him myself. I would if I had to but the state will take care if that for me. Life is precious, I will harm anyone who harms the lives of those I love and care for.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cwtyu1r</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; And can any sane or humane person really say that life in a prison cell is humane?

Yes.  There are people like me who value any appreciable quality of life over an absence of life.  I would gladly take life in prison over death.

That said, I'm not against capital punishment as long as it's humane.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwtwbyw</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Down_The_Rabbithole</author>
        <ReplyBody>Morality is subjective.

Limiting someones freedom of choice can be seen as worse than murder by some people. Thus pro-death penalty is not necessarily immoral. It should be more seen like euthanasia. The person being put to death isn't dying for revenge purposes. But because the only reason that person might find happiness is by taking it away from someone else. Putting it to sleep might be the most empathetic solution to this, since society can't give it what it wants.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtexh6</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt4s3o</id>
        <replies>
            <author>TryUsingScience</author>
            <ReplyBody>Removed for violating rule 1. Your comment doesn't actually challenge OP's view in any meaningful way that they can respond to.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt56n2</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwt7j1l</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Jimassho</author>
        <ReplyBody>By the same logic you advocate castration for rapists. True? You believe castration is the correct punishment for rapists? 

If not, you answered your own question. 

Please answer. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt68f0</id>
        <replies>
            <author>basscorruption</author>
            <ReplyBody>This is not the same logic at all.  You're using a basic causal flaw.  Two different causes have the same effects.  The effects of both could be the same, but the causes are most certainly not the same.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwt6f3w</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Jimassho</author>
                <ReplyBody>Nice try, but that doesn't answer the question at all. 

Essentially you're saying people shouldn't be punished because they may possibly be cured at some unknown point of an unknown affliction by some unknown technology . Until that technology exists, we live in a reality without your option. 

  If the sky were green and the grass were purple, people might never murder anyone. It's a useless discussion. Your option doesn't exist. It most likely will never exist. 

 

   </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cwta5zn</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-4</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>64m3r</author>
        <ReplyBody>We already have a "fix" you are describing. Its called Lobotomy. Can you guess why no one uses it?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt7ak8</id>
        <replies>
            <author>daschne8</author>
            <ReplyBody>The Lobotomy was about as precise as an egg beater and as such came with a whole host of horrible side effects that doctors knew about and people still felt it was a better option for the patient.  Do you know why it stopped?
Because we started developing anti-psychotics, not on any moral grounds we just developed a better alternative.  The OP's CMV is based on a hypothetical and i assume much more precise procedure.  There are plenty of examples where things like traumatic brain injuries and tumors actually change a persons personality so i do not believe it too far fetched to think that with more technology that this is a perfectly feasible possibility.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtcxdz</id>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>divinesleeper</author>
        <ReplyBody>If such a "fix" exists, and the person has instead chosen to hold on to their identity and commit crime rather than obtaining said "fix", doesn't that imply that you are destroying their identity against their will?

That in itself can be seen as a sort of "death sentence".

Also, what is moral and immoral has been highly debated throughout history, and your reduction of it to a combination of utility to society (which supposedly justifies the fix) and deontological values (which supposedly makes killing immoral) is in itself already contradictory.

What would you say lies at the basis of your morality? What principle?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwta7gu</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ablair24</author>
        <ReplyBody>Alright, lets say we are able to fix people. Let's say there is something that got misfired at birth, and gave a man certain violent urges, so he goes to a doctor to get it fixed so he doesn't have violent urges anymore. 

What if after he got fixed, he still killed someone. Do you give him the death penalty? He was in perfect mental health, nothing wrong with him. Maybe he was very poor, tried to rob a store, ended up killing someone he didn't mean to. Does he still get the death penalty?

What would you do in cases like that?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtcfuq</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>ShalmaneserIII</author>
        <ReplyBody>Consider this scenario- if we were able to determine that the murderer only wanted to kill that one particular person who was his victim, and showed no more interest in killing anyone else than a random person at large would. 



Let him go free?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwti1gv</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Mdcastle</author>
        <ReplyBody>This only hypothetically addresses one purpose of the criminal justice system: Incapacitation. There's also Deterrence and Punishment. And we've already have an alternative method of incacitiation: Life without Parole, which doesn't rely on the need to fix someone. 

I know there's been a lot of doubt on the Deterrence effect on the death penalty, but what about punishment. If we could somehow have "fixed Ted Bundy and John Wayne Gacy, didn't they still deserve to die as punishment for the crime they'd already committed? I'd argue yes. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtihyf</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[removed]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtj6wx</id>
        <replies>
            <author>cacheflow</author>
            <ReplyBody>Sorry ablanchard17, your comment has been removed: 

&amp;gt; Comment Rule 1\. "Direct responses to a CMV post must challenge at least one aspect of OP’s current view (however minor), unless they are asking a clarifying question. Arguments in favor of the view OP is willing to change must be restricted to replies to comments." [See the wiki page for more information.](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules#wiki_rule_1)  

If you would like to appeal, please [message the moderators by clicking this link.](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Fchangemyview&amp;amp;subject=Removed+Comment+Rule+1+Post+Appeal&amp;amp;message=ablanchard17+would+like+to+appeal+the+removal+of+[his/her+post](https://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3s19v4/cmv_being_prodeath_penalty_is_immoral_especially/cwtj6wx\))

&amp;gt; Comment Rule 3\. "Refrain from accusing OP or anyone else of being unwilling to change their view. If you are unsure whether someone is genuine, ask clarifying questions (see: socratic method). If you think they are still exhibiting ill behaviour, please message us." [See the wiki page for more information.](http://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/wiki/rules#wiki_rule_3)  

If you would like to appeal, please [message the moderators by clicking this link.](http://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Fchangemyview&amp;amp;subject=Removed+Comment+Rule+3+Post+Appeal&amp;amp;message=ablanchard17+would+like+to+appeal+the+removal+of+[his/her+post](https://www.reddit.com/r/changemyview/comments/3s19v4/cmv_being_prodeath_penalty_is_immoral_especially/cwtj6wx\))</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cwtjk7d</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>The4thRabbitt</author>
        <ReplyBody>TLDR: hindsight is 20:20, and that's OK

TLDR2: You shouldn't refuse to ever buy a smartphone, just because they might come out with a better one tomorrow. 

Your argument is similar to the slippery slope fallacy, which asserts that cause A will have effect B, which will be the cause of effect C and so forth; most of the time assuming that effect C is unintended and undesirable. 

Your argument assumes that a future condition is a possibility, which is true, but then you also assert that we should make decisions based on that possibility. While it is true that we often make decisions keeping many possible outcomes in mind,  it is not true that we make decisions keeping any possible outcomes in mind. 

Prior to making a decision, it is smart to try and estimate the likelihood of certain possible effects. The information used to make these estimates only, and can only, exist in the present. We can also only use information we have, not information we do not have. Assume we have a situation, in which we can perfectly quantify the likelihood that decision A will cause effect B, using all current information in our possession. The quantity is 99.9999%. Now assume, our decision does not cause effect B, but something else. Afterwards, we discover the reason why, and it becomes clear we lacked information which would have significantly reduced our estimation. Did we acting immorally, or with stupidity? Should we not have acted at all for fear that any new piece of information could have arose? No, no, and no. 

It is often good practice to universalize ethical situations by broadening relevant variables. Would you will that everyone behave the same way in this situation if the variables were different? For example, if you apply your logic to buying a smartphone, you would never be able to buy one, or even invest in any opportunity for fear that a better phone or opportunity would present itself at some unknown future moment. 

Lastly, I would like to add that morality is a social construct, and exists as a social utility to maximize social cohesion. Usually when people declare that something is moral or immoral, they mean it as a universal truth, and basically that is true just because. I find this unreasonable, if you state that something is immoral, please provide actual costs. I could declare that using Reddit is immoral because its mascot has an antenna. I'm just stating facts, I don't have a real ethical argument. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtks73</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>DrWhiskeydick</author>
        <ReplyBody>I'm not really in favor of the death penalty in general, as I'm against the idea of state sponsored killing of its citizens and especially considering it's very very difficult to be 100% sure of guilt.  But the idea that we can almost lobotomize people to get rid of their killer impulses is absurd as well, maybe even worse than outright killing them, so that's where I completely disagree.

I also am in favor of the death penalty for, not revenge or punishment, but removing people who are still an influential threat while imprisoned.  That's the point of imprisoning people, for life and for the death penalty we have now, anyway.  Remove them from the society they're a threat to.  If they're still a threat, then it's arguably acceptable.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtnfga</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>JustinJamm</author>
        <ReplyBody>Then everyone will know they can do whatever they want -- with no consequences except that they'll get "fixed" afterward.

Lots of first-timers doing absolutely awful things, I'd predict.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtp499</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>villanovablues</author>
        <ReplyBody>Morality is a false human construct we created so we can go to sleep at night, it helps us live with our mistakes and our future mistakes.

Some people deserve the death penalty and others don't. The problem arises when innocents get caught in the crossfire, but the death penalty itself is not the issue.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwtz4no</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Opheltes</author>
        <ReplyBody>1) The death penalty is not solely intended to prevent future harm. There's also a retributive reason](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Retributive_justice) for it that you are neglecting. 

2) The death penalty [saves lives](http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/18/us/18deter.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=0), three to eighteen per person who is executed. For every murderer who doesn't get executed, 3 to 18 innocent people die. Your solution would cost innocent lives and is therefore is immoral.   

3) Your proposal is fundamentally undemocratic. The majority of people in the US favor the death penalty.  This whole proposal is simply a backdoor way to get around the fact that the death penalty has very large popular support.

4) It's absurdly impractical. You want us to change how we sentence criminals today because at some unspecified time in the future, someone might figure out a way to fix them (whatever that means).


</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwt7x4i</id>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>blatheringbard</author>
        <ReplyBody>To me, I suppose it depends on where your morality comes from. 

If your morality is purely logical, then we have every right to use the death penalty, evolutionarily speaking. The only reason we feel it's immoral to kill is social contract. If a person breaks social contract, it is not the duty of a society to extend the benefits of that social contract to the person in breach of the contract. Therefore, asking society to pay -- in time, money, or effort -- to support a person who has disregarded the social contract is not a moral imperative.  A society may choose to grant varying degrees of mercy, but it is not immoral for them to choose not to grant that mercy. 

If your morality stems from something more spiritual or religious, I suppose that another discussion. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cwte4oc</id>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
