<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>UncleTrustworthy</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;If studies were to show that the Death Penalty deterred more murders than it killed innocent people

So then would the death penalty be the *only way* to deter murder? Would there be other means of deterring would-be murderers? If yes, are they more or less effective? Could they be improved?

If no one opposed the death penalty, there would be no one to ask those questions. We would remain complacent with the death penalty and never strive for something better.

Beyond all that, the premise of your view doesn't make sense to me. Given the choice between "one innocent person killed by the state, or two innocent people killed by other people," I'd choose the latter. The state can not be given a pass for killing innocent people. It must be held to a higher standard than individuals, or else it might lead to abuses of power.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3j2da</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>It clearly wouldn't be the only deterrent to murder, but the idea is that the DP alone would be saving more innocent lives than killing.

&amp;gt; The state can not be given a pass for killing innocent people. 

but under your way of thinking, you're giving them a pass for letting two innocent people die, which is just as bad. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3jowi</id>
            <replies>
                <author>UncleTrustworthy</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; you're giving them a pass for letting two innocent people die, which is just as bad.

No, it isn't. There's a difference between an individual or organization directly killing one person, and that same individual or organization indirectly allowing two people to die. You are ignoring that distinction.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3jyjl</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                    <ReplyBody>There really isn't a large separation when you have an obligation though.

If I witness a car crash I have no obligation to pull an unconscious man from a burning car. If I let him die, it's very different from killing him myself.

But if I'm, say, a public servant who's job is to pull people from burning cars and I witness the same thing, it's my responsibility to do so (or at least make an effort). Especially if I was getting paid by that guy to do such a job. Letting him burn would be just as bad as killing him myself because I had an obligation to save him. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cq3k6yy</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>UncleTrustworthy</author>
                        <ReplyBody>That's not an applicable analogy for your argument because it does not involve the sacrifice of one person to save two.

The public servant witnessing a car burning is under an obligation to attempt to save a person trapped inside. He is not under an obligation to kill an arsonist or reckless driver to serve as a deterrent to others.

The United States government is under an obligation to provide reasonable assistance to its citizens. It is not under an obligation to participate in the murder of individuals in an attempt to dissuade others from attempting murder themselves.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq3kijf</id>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>6</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>skatastic57</author>
                <ReplyBody>It's not just as bad because the murderers aren't *allowed* to do that they're breaking the law and will be punished if caught.  If the state has a pass to kill people then no one is punished and that's the end of the story.  The state allows people to be killed everyday with every decision it makes.  For example, if they do road construction 24x7 they can finish a project that makes the road way safer in 2 weeks but if they just have the workers 8 hour shifts on week days it'll take 8 weeks.  In those 6 weeks that the road isn't safer the likelihood of death due to traffic accident goes way up.  This doesn't mean the state is killing people like in your example where the state actually executed a person.  Our laws on murder already reflect the difference in why someone is killed.  You can range from murder 1 all the way down to involuntary manslaughter all of which have different punishments even though people are still dead.  In many ways the state has license to involuntary manslaughter but I don't want to give them a license to first degree murder.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq4abw2</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>17</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>[deleted]</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3jbrx</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>But if we knowingly can prevent two innocent people from dying, that's essentially the same thing as the government killing them. 
</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3jkzs</id>
            <replies>
                <author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
                <ReplyBody>It's very different. That's like saying that because I haven't donated a kidney, I killed someone.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3ljv5</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Not really. 

It would be more along the lines of a mother not feeding her child so it starves. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cq3mf23</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Not at all. There is a huge difference between directly killing someone, and indirectly having someone die. Your mother/child scenario is an example of directly killing someone.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq3mukt</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                            <ReplyBody>No, a mother not feeding her child is exactly the same.

The mother has an obligation to keep her kid alive - just as the state has an obligation to keep us safe.

The mother isn't "directly" killing the kid - she's just not saving his life with food. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cq3n1de</id>
                            <replies>
<author>FlyingFoxOfTheYard_</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; No, a mother not feeding her child is exactly the same.

Here's the thing. The mother has a direct effect on whether or not the child dies. If she doesn't feed the child, it dies, making her directly responsible for the death. With the government/death penalty, the government is not directly involved should someone be killed by someone else. Much in the same way, I would not be directly involved if someone dies due to my not donating a kidney. 


&amp;gt; The mother has an obligation to keep her kid alive - just as the state has an obligation to keep us safe.


So then is the state responsible for any and all crimes regardless of who did them? That seems to be what you're implying. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cq3oa50</id>
<replies>
    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
    <ReplyBody>The state has a responsibly to do what it can, just like a parent. A parent would be responsible if the kid starved to death, but not if the kid died from a birth defect or something. Just like how the government can't stop every crime from happening but it should do what it can.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>cq3oh3r</id>
    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>5</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-3</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>7</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>BrellK</author>
                <ReplyBody>If you want to extrapolate that argument, then why not have the Government force everyone to work from home and never leave their house? We could probably eliminate quite a few murders!

Even if it were the case (similar to *if* it were the case with the Death Penalty), we accept a certain amount of risk in order to live in the society which we currently enjoy.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq41bwh</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>7</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>McKoijion</author>
        <ReplyBody>If you are taking the completely utilitarian argument, then there are far better uses of money than spending on the death penalty. A death penalty case costs 1.24 million dollars per person in taxpayer funds (vs. $740,000 for life sentences.) A life saving malaria net costs $10. When you consider that people need multiple nets over their lifetime, it still comes out to only $3,300 over a lifetime. We can provide 50,000 nets for the same price as going after the death penalty for just one criminal. 

In this way, your argument becomes would you rather have one innocent person killed by the state, two innocent people killed by other people, or 150 people killed by disease? Even if you think the money should be spent on protecting tax paying domestic citizens that than disease, there are far more cost effective ways of stopping crime.

Source: http://www.givewell.org/international/technical/programs/insecticide-treated-nets</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3jcy6</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>You do have a point, but it was more of a philosophical question rather than a nitty-gritty economics experiment. I would also argue that with the advances we've had in technology, the cost of a DP case would drop significantly with a reform process (limited appeals, DNA requirements, etc) </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3jmta</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; You do have a point, but it was more of a philosophical question rather than a nitty-gritty economics experiment

You're espousing an ethical system that *demands* that questions of ethics be reduced to "nitty-gritty economics experiments", what you're saying there isn't really reasonable, if you're a utilitarian you have to engage with utilitarian criticisms</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3q5he</id>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>ThatBelligerentSloth</author>
                <ReplyBody>utilitarianism is a philosophical position. I'm literally doing a paper for a class for moral justifications of punishments.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3s71j</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>5</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>plasticdracula</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;it would be immoral to oppose

How so? If I recall correctly, morals are subjective value systems, and if a large enough group of people think killing is wrong for any reason (and I do believe such a group exists), it would be immoral to have the death penalty at all. We can't stop evil people from existing, but we can at least exercise control over an evil judicial system.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3ja1l</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>tit_wrangler</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; So essentially what it would come down to is: would you rather have one innocent person killed by the state, or two innocent people killed by other people? And to me, the person behind the trigger doesn't matter, only the end result - and I see two dead to one dead, and one dead is a far better, or I guess "less worse," situation.  

It would only be immoral to oppose this outcome if you adhere to a strictly utilitarian philosophy. You're looking at the ontology of the actions - that they produce desirable consequences, quantitatively, regardless of how they are achieved. Funnily enough, this is remarkably robotic in that deals plainly with quantitative data, ignoring whatever ethics or moral codes are adhered to in the process. From a deontological standpoint, in which we actually care about the way we act in order to achieve an outcome (because are those actions not equally subject to moral judgment?), one can easily argue that saving one extra hypothetical life (and yes, we are talking about hypothetical lives because, even if we are working off of statistical predictors, we are still making an assumption that lives will be saved) is not morally worth the means to achieve it. You suggest that, in the grand scheme of things, we are ultimately against death. And while I understand this makes fewer deaths seem like the only viable moral goal, in a legal system that is purportedly meant to not just enforce but uphold our moral standards, murdering to prevent murder is--from a variety of ethical standpoints--immoral. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3m7wv</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>TheUnit472</author>
        <ReplyBody>By your logic, any action which the government takes which results in fewer fatalities is morally correct.

The introduction of the automobile has resulted in hundreds of thousands if not millions of deaths since its introduction. By your same logic, it is morally wrong to support automobiles since they result in the deaths of innocent lives and therefore the government should ban the automobile.

Also, in your scenario you would be fostering a long-term mistrust in the government due to its inability to prove the innocence of the various families and friends of the innocents that are executed who would then lose faith in the government and could turn to organized crime or vigilantism for justice.

You also ignore the potential for rehabilitation if the murderer serves a sentence in jail. It is possible for murderers to reform and become productive members of society. That is supposed to be the purpose of prison, to rehabilitate people. In your scenario, while two innocents may be killed, one innocent is saved by not being executed and two murderers may reform and be reintegrated into society.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3w7x4</id>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>GnosticGnome</author>
        <ReplyBody>Studies show that the Against Malaria Foundation can save human lives for about $1600 apiece.  Do I have a moral obligation to steal from my grandmother and donate that money to save lives at $1600 apiece?  Or does morality actually include a lot more than just "maximum lives saved"?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3jbpr</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>No, because you're under no obligation to protect others from Malaria.

the state is under an obligation to protect us. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3jjgn</id>
            <replies>
                <author>McKoijion</author>
                <ReplyBody>Why isn't the state under any obligation to protect us from dangerous pathogens? If not malaria, it could be any other local life threatening disease.
</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3jo0e</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Well, it differs from state to state. In the US, the government really doesn't really have any big obligation to protect us from malaria. While an epidemic is a different story, malaria isn't high on the list of stuff we worry about. 

Crime, however, falls under that umbrella of the things we rely on the state for protection for. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cq3jvo3</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>svipdag_DM</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Gov'ts in the US spends a ton of money killing mosquitos so people don't die of malaria, mostly local and state gov'ts.

http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/health/mosquitoes/mosquitojoint.htm

http://www.cdpr.ca.gov/docs/dept/westnile/mosqover.pdf

As a separate objection: in your opinion, if studies showed that having a larger army prevented deaths from terrorism, does that automatically justify a draft? 
 


</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq54rfc</id>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <replies>
                <author>Pinewood74</author>
                <ReplyBody>Then does the state have a responsibility to forcibly take this money and re-distribute it?

Sure, America isn't suffering from Malaria, but there's some homeless people dying on the streets and other people dying of stuff that money could easily cure.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3jogr</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                    <ReplyBody>The problem is - money doesn't cure that. 

And even if it did, the argument was more of a philosophical question than a money management question. the DP doesn't inherently have to cost a shit ton of money. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cq3jxdh</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Pinewood74</author>
                        <ReplyBody>What?  Money doesn't cure homelessness?

Yeah, it does.  I give you a house and you're not homeless.

The money management is relevant.  You're basically arguing that saving lives is worth it, regardless of how we do it, so if taxing the shit out of people saved lives, then why shouldn't we do it by your logic?

Also, the DP is going to have to be hella expensive to ensure it isn't killing innocent people.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq3k32l</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; You're basically arguing that saving lives is worth it, regardless of how we do it, so if taxing the shit out of people saved lives, then why shouldn't we do it by your logic?

not really, because you'd be lowing the quality of everyone's lives by taxing them. </ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cq3k8va</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Pinewood74</author>
<ReplyBody>But you'd be saving people.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cq3rm00</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>daman345</author>
<ReplyBody>And arguably living under a regime that uses the death penalty does the same. With this point, you're contradicting the other arugments you're making in this CMV</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cq4rtpr</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Hoppmjac000</author>
        <ReplyBody>You're assuming a strictly Utilitarian framework (at-least regarding murderers).  Essentially, anything could be accepted if it "saved" lives.  What if we tortured murderers to deter murder?  
You said it yourself, the person behind the trigger doesn't matter.  Does doing anything to a "caused cog" (for as material beings we are all defined by our own physical nature and how it is shaped by social and material variables) become justifiable if it saves others?  

What if instead of doing this, we promote general social welfare and Positive Liberty (i.e. material liberty) which would save just as many lives (if not more) and it would try to save the killer as well as others through helping those who have gone done the wrong path.

I know some people are very-likely "beyond" us helping them fundamentally, and them re-entering society; but I believe those people are few and far between and as caused beings they deserve humane treatment even though they are "beasts."  Two wrongs don't make a right, as simplistic and cliched as that sounds.
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3jjx6</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>Morality isn't a calculation. Morality is a value system. 

It would be **illogical** to oppose it, because the numbers say that it is. That doesn't make it immoral. 

If I don't feel comfortable with the state sending a possibly innocent person to death, I could still oppose the death penalty. There's a difference between two more people theoretically dying and the state picking one person who is innocent and killing them. 

It might not be a difference to you, but morally, it could very well be a significant difference to someone else. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3k2n4</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>SOLUNAR</author>
        <ReplyBody>i guess id take the philosophy way.

If you could kill 1 child to save 4 people, would it be immoral to opose it?

even if means harming an innocent?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3k5iu</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>looklistencreate</author>
        <ReplyBody>Utilitarianism isn't the only moral system, and at its basest form is probably opposed by most Americans. One could argue that government must be above such actions and held to a higher standard, even if they are effective. A study like this would be a good pragmatic argument, but it's not an ironclad moral argument as you suggest.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3kicb</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>stratys3</author>
        <ReplyBody>I know your situation is hypothetical - but I wanted to ask: Do you really believe the death penalty is a deterrent? If you do, can you explain why you believe this to be true?</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3kqm2</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't really know, all the studies we get back are vague and contradict eachother.

It has to be at least a small deterrent. There has to have been at least one guy somewhere who thought himself out of it because he didn't want to die. How big of a deterrent it is though I have no idea. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3ktgs</id>
            <replies>
                <author>stratys3</author>
                <ReplyBody>The reason I question this is because: 

1) Many crimes like murder are crimes of passion, where no one is thinking rationally or logically about potential consequences or long-term outcomes. 

2) Let's assume some people rationally and logically think about potential punishments. 25 years or life in prison is an extraordinarily severe punishment already. If they are not deterred by this already - then they probably won't be deterred by anything at all. The reason serious crimes still happen is not because they don't think 25 years in prison is a big deal - they happen because they don't think they'll get caught in the first place. Uping the punishment won't change their thought processes.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3lgpv</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                    <ReplyBody>well, crimes of passion generally aren't death penalty candidates. DP cases almost always involve premeditation. 

And like I said, most of our studies conflict with eachother, it was more of a mental experiment than anything. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cq3natw</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>stratys3</author>
                        <ReplyBody>I would agree with the others that suggest that the government letting 2 people die is different than actively killing 1 innocent person, however.

But that said... let's say you talked to people pre-meditating serious crimes. If you told them that there is a 100% chance that they will get caught... how many would continue and do the crime with life in prison, but not do the crime with the death penalty? I think the vast majority (basically everyone) would NOT do the crime, even with just life in prison. What crime is worth 25 years in prison?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq3nkcy</id>
                        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Ergodically</author>
        <ReplyBody>This is an overly utilitarian form of morality. Let's say that 100 people  are murdered every year. Suppose that studies showed conclusively that sacrificing 99 randomly chosen people a year to Cthulhu would appease it and cause it to magically bring down the murder rate to 0.  Would it be immoral to oppose this sort of sacrifice? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3l649</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>If thats how it actually worked, then yes.

I mean I completely understand that whoever is dying is going to be upset - but someone has to die. Why not make it 99 instead of 100?

</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3l800</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Ergodically</author>
                <ReplyBody>The government is a representative of the people in the way that a murderer is not. As such, we should hold it to a higher moral standard, because they are by extension our standards. I think murder is immoral, and I would like my representatives not to commit it. I would also like murderers not to commit murder, but I can't control them. 

At the end of the day though, I think it boils down to relative numbers. If sacrificing to Cthulhu reduced the probability of a random person of being murdered from 95% to 0%, then it might be a necessary evil. If it reduced a person's probability from 0.001% to 0.00099%, then I think it would unwise and immoral to decide to live in a society where the government has the ability to murder and deal with dark powers to solve its problems, as this might reflect in more things than just the murder rate. </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3m7gw</id>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>0</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>garnteller</author>
        <ReplyBody>Let's consider Ebola.

Let's assume that the math works out that each person who is infected has a certain chance of infecting others (who might infect others and so on), and thus the average number of people who die due to that person is 1.0001.

In that case, you're morally bound to execute that patient immediately, right?

Beyond that, in both my case and yours, there are alternatives.  You can quarantine the patient, for instance, or provide better medical care.  In your case, rather than using the death penalty, lifetime imprisonment will lead to the same number of victims lives being saved, PLUS the innocent prisoner, saving THREE lives total.

It's not an either/or.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3lpoi</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NorbitGorbit</author>
        <ReplyBody>it would be irrational to oppose but not necessarily immoral. morality is not contingent on rationality.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3o05i</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>river710</author>
        <ReplyBody>Morals aren't necessarily for the greater good. Basically what you're saying is that if state sanctioned killing effectively caused less dead people in the long run, it would be the right thing. 

The thing is that the best for the most people should never have the final say on what is the right thing to do. It would be the best for the most people to euthanize all retarded or disabled people, but almost everyone agrees that's not the right thing to do.

In the end morality is subjective anyways.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3op9r</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>leeson12</author>
        <ReplyBody>So is the end result of how many lives are saved all that matters when determining what is moral and what isn't?? Using a similar reasoning, you could probably justify the performance of many horrifying experiments on unwilling test subjects. The estimated value of lives saved in the long term from doing these experiments would outweigh the cost of violating the rights of a few. </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq4bwl9</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>NuclearStudent</author>
        <ReplyBody>In this scenario, other alternatives could still be more effective at preventing death. For instance, a re-education/containment policy might be effective at reducing violent tendencies. Even if it only succeeds with a few percent of the offenders, that's just as good as the death penalty.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq540ru</id>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Ajorahai</author>
        <ReplyBody>What do you think is the morally correct response to the [transplant problem](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trolley_problem):

&amp;gt;A brilliant transplant surgeon has five patients, each in need of a different organ, each of whom will die without that organ. Unfortunately, there are no organs available to perform any of these five transplant operations. A healthy young traveler, just passing through the city the doctor works in, comes in for a routine checkup. In the course of doing the checkup, the doctor discovers that his organs are compatible with all five of his dying patients. Suppose further that if the young man were to disappear, no one would suspect the doctor.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>cq3mtxl</id>
        <replies>
            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
            <ReplyBody>Interesting problem, not sure on the answer for that one - but the situation is different, slightly. 

If all parties are equal and the organs are failing due to luck (ie: the lungs aren't failing because they were a smoker), then yes I'd believe it's the moral choice to save 5 people. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>cq3n8os</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Ajorahai</author>
                <ReplyBody>Why do you place a stipulation that all parties must be equal and the organs are failing due to luck in this scenario, but you do not put similar restrictions on the morality of the death penalty?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>cq3nt61</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                    <ReplyBody>Because this is a specific one time scenario whereas the DP would be applied on a whole. You'd be unable to look at the individual circumstances for everything while making policy. </ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>cq3nv4j</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Ajorahai</author>
                        <ReplyBody>We could generalize this situation to the policy of forcibly harvesting organs from healthy individuals in order to save people who suffer from organ failure.

I assume that in such a policy you would place a stipulation that it can only be done if the situations of all participants are equal and the organ recipients are not responsible for their illness?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>cq3o3zw</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>CherrySlurpee</author>
                            <ReplyBody>I mean i see where you're going and it is a great parallel, but the biggest difference is that for each case of that it still would be a specific situation. With the DP analogy above, we don't know which of those 100 people was innocent, and we don't know who's going to be murdered until after it happens.

With organ harvesting we'd have to run it case by case, which would make it a legal nightmare. But on a moral level there are certainly cases where it would be better to save the many</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>cq3ok8x</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Ajorahai</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; With the DP analogy above, we don't know which of those 100 people was innocent, and we don't know who's going to be murdered until after it happens.

I agree, but we can analyze population as a whole. I think that the two groups are not likely to be "equal" (however you define that word). If the population of homicide victims is unequal to the population of people wrongly convicted then wouldn't it still be immoral?

for example, one exception you made to the transplant problem was for people who are partially responsible for their illness (for example, smoking). Many people who are killed are partially responsible for provoking the killer (for example. adulterers killed by the spouse they cheated on). Is there any reason to assume the two populations are equal? It seems logical that the population of murder and manslaughter victims, on average, did something to provoke the killer. However, I don't see any reason to assume that the population of people wrongly convicted of murder/manslaughter are in the situation for any reason other than luck on average.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>cq3p14n</id>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
