<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<redditSubmission>
    <commentCount>0</commentCount>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I oppose lethal injection. It's too much like a medical procedure. I don't think there should be any question about what's happening: the State is taking revenge.

No one's gonna confuse it with a booster shot. State sponsored executions are state sponsored executions, however they're dressed up.

&amp;gt;That said, I'm willing to accept that occasionally innocents will be executed. That's regrettable, but the doctrine of double effect, in my view, applies to this and other similar cases (e.g., unintended but foreseeable killing of civilians in wartime).

Quick review of the doctrine:


&amp;gt;The New Catholic Encyclopedia provides four conditions for the application of the principle of double effect:

&amp;gt;The act itself must be morally good or at least indifferent.

&amp;gt;The agent may not positively will the bad effect but may permit it. If he could attain the good effect without the bad effect he should do so. The bad effect is sometimes said to be indirectly voluntary.


&amp;gt;The good effect must flow from the action at least as immediately (in the order of causality, though not necessarily in the order of time) as the bad effect. In other words the good effect must be produced directly by the action, not by the bad effect. Otherwise the agent would be using a bad means to a good end, which is never allowed.

&amp;gt;The good effect must be sufficiently desirable to compensate for the allowing of the bad effect“ (p. 1021).

To be honest, I think execution fails the first condition, or at the very least the fourth. I *don't* think executing murderers is a good effect, or at the very least the increased benefit of killing them rather than locking them away for life doesn't justify killing innocent people.

This isn't a direct contradiction of any of your points, but [evidence good enough to convince SCOTUS was presented that the death penalty in America is *strongly* racially biased](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McCleskey_v._Kemp). Not only are we occasionally killing innocents, but we're deciding who to kill on the basis of skin color.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xhd5v</id>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;No one's gonna confuse it with a booster shot. State sponsored executions are state sponsored executions, however they're dressed up.

But they might confuse it with euthanasia.  Putting an animal out of its misery or getting rid of an inconvenient human being, rather than holding a criminal to account.  I don't think there should be any confusion on that question.

&amp;gt;To be honest, I think execution fails the first condition, or at the very least the fourth. I don't think executing murderers is a good effect, or at the very least the increased benefit of killing them rather than locking them away for life doesn't justify killing innocent people.

I was invoking double effect on the narrow question of unintended killing of innocents, not as the justification for the death penalty itself.

But I do think there are unique reasons why the death penalty is preferable to life in prison, in some circumstances.

A murderer took away something irreplaceable, a human life.  I don't see the injustice in exacting a similar penalty.  Hannah Arendt was no hanging enthusiast, but she put the case as clearly as possible in *Eichmann in Jerusalem*:

&amp;gt;Just as you [Eichmann] supported and carried out a policy of not wanting to share the earth with the Jewish people and the people of a number of other nations—as though you and your superiors had any right to determine who should and who should not inhabit the world—we find that no one, that is, no member of the human race, can be expected to want to share the earth with you. This is the reason, and the only reason, you must hang.

An extreme instance, sure, but one where the abolitionists would also forego the death penalty.

I grew up admiring Clarence Darrow and can still recite parts of his "Leopold &amp;amp; Loeb" speech from memory.  So I'm open to changing my mind on this question again.  But what pulls me up is this reflection: Nathan Leopold got to see the sun every day.  He got to work and read books and even get married after being released on parole.  He got to make something of his life.  And the little boy who he bludgeoned to death never did.

Loeb was stabbed to death by a prison inmate, and I take no satisfaction from that.  He didn't die for his crimes; he died because he upset another murderer.

&amp;gt;This isn't a direct contradiction of any of your points, but evidence good enough to convince SCOTUS was presented that the death penalty in America is strongly racially biased. Not only are we occasionally killing innocents, but we're deciding who to kill on the basis of skin color.

I don't support racial bias in executions and think a defendant ought to be able to present that argument on appeal (and be taken seriously if the evidence warrants it).</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xhuj4</id>
            <replies>
                <author>BlackHumor</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;A murderer took away something irreplaceable, a human life. I don't see the injustice in exacting a similar penalty. 

Fuck justice, then. Who cares about justice over a human life? 

&amp;gt;An extreme instance, sure, but one where the abolitionists would also forego the death penalty.

I wouldn't, and I'm Jewish. I think all killing Eichmann did is give him the last laugh. You don't want to do the same thing to him that he did to all those innocent people; you want to show him mercy and prove that he's alone in his nastiness.

&amp;gt;I grew up admiring Clarence Darrow and can still recite parts of his "Leopold &amp;amp; Loeb" speech from memory. So I'm open to changing my mind on this question again. But what pulls me up is this reflection: Nathan Leopold got to see the sun every day. He got to work and read books and even get married after being released on parole. He got to make something of his life. And the little boy who he bludgeoned to death never did.

Killing Leopold would not have brought that kid back. All killing Leopold would've done is add more death.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xpxoc</id>
                <upvotes>-1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>3</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>4</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Amablue</author>
        <ReplyBody>Revenge is not a goal of the justice system.we punish people for three reasons: to deter crime, to remove dangerous people from society, and to rehabilitate. 

What difference does it make if injection is like a medical procedure? As far as I know it's the most humane way to kill a person, which is important because we have rules against cruel punishment written into our constitution.

What benefit is there to valuing revenge over the rights of the accused?
</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xhf10</id>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>I think revenge is a legitimate function of the criminal justice system (even if the new Pope of the criminal justice tells me, without warrant, that there can only be three purposes).  

In particular, the State should recognize revenge is a legitimate human impulse and seek to constrain it within reasonable bounds, rather than deny it outright.

I don't think the prohibition against cruel and unusual punishment is a demand for the "most humane way to kill a person."  It's merely a prohibition against cruel and unusual punishment.

As for the question of medical procedures vs. executions, I think it comes down to moral accountability.  Are we punishing a crime or "putting down" an inconvenient person?  You might not grasp the distinction, but it seems quite obvious to me that there's a vast difference between the two. </ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xi30p</id>
            <replies>
                <author>Amablue</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I think revenge is a legitimate function of the criminal justice system

Why? What good does it serve? To make the victims (or family of the victims) feel better that someone got harmed for doing something bad? Does that mean I can use revenge to beat up or kill the guy who slept with my wife and it'd be moral? 

&amp;gt; As for the question of medical procedures vs. executions, I think it comes down to moral accountability. Are we punishing a crime or "putting down" an inconvenient person? You might not grasp the distinction, but it seems quite obvious to me that there's a vast difference between the two. 

I agree that executing someone is a punishment, I'm questioning the motive for the punishment. Regardless, why does the method of execution make a difference? </ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xje9x</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Why? What good does it serve? To make the victims (or family of the victims) feel better that someone got harmed for doing something bad? 

In part, yes.  I don't think revenge is the *only* reason for the death penalty, but the outrage and indignation victims feel shouldn't be excluded as a factor in determining a sentence.  We do this all the time with lesser crimes.

&amp;gt;I agree that executing someone is a punishment, I'm questioning the motive for the punishment. Regardless, why does the method of execution make a difference? 

I've answered this question repeatedly.

&amp;gt;Does that mean I can use revenge to beat up or kill the guy who slept with my wife and it'd be moral? 

Adultery isn't remotely comparable to murder, and it's difficult for me to believe there's even a government interest at stake.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>c9xmygn</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>Amablue</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;  I don't think revenge is the only reason for the death penalty, but the outrage and indignation victims feel shouldn't be excluded as a factor in determining a sentence. 

I believe exactly the opposite: Wanting to see another person harmed is not justification for harming them. The only time we should ever do harm to others is to prevent worse harm from occurring.

I will note here that I am not against the death penalty, I think there are places where it is a valid and justifiable punishment. I do not believe the justification should ever be revenge. The government should not be sponsoring sadism. 

&amp;gt; We do this all the time with lesser crimes.

If we do, it's unjust there as well. Can you give some specific examples?

&amp;gt; I've answered this question repeatedly.

Are you talking about in this comment thread or in the thread as a whole? Apologies if I missed it but all I can find is this:

&amp;gt; Are we punishing a crime or "putting down" an inconvenient person

It is still not clear to me how the motive for our action is changed by the means. We can kill a person with a gun, with an injection, with an electric chair, or with a variety of other means. Our method doesn't change our motive. 

&amp;gt; Adultery isn't remotely comparable to murder, and it's difficult for me to believe there's even a government interest at stake.

But he's hurt me and I want revenge. Maybe I won't kill him, just beat him up. You've stated that revenge is a valid justification, so would I be in the wrong if I kicked his ass because it made me feel better? Is there some scale I can use to determine what the correct amount of revenge is for an act of wrongdoing against me?</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>c9xns18</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I believe exactly the opposite: Wanting to see another person harmed is not justification for harming them. The only time we should ever do harm to others is to prevent worse harm from occurring.

Well, that's frankly an impossible standard.  You can't know what "future harm" someone will commit.

I hate to offer an extreme case, but abolition is an extreme position.  Adolf Eichmann didn't hurt anyone after the Nazi government fell.  He probably would've lived the rest of his life quietly, without even hurting a fly.  Once Israel captured him, do you think he should have been punished?  On what grounds, if not retribution for the crimes he committed?

&amp;gt;I will note here that I am not against the death penalty, I think there are places where it is a valid and justifiable punishment. I do not believe the justification should ever be revenge. The government should not be sponsoring sadism. 

Retribution and sadism aren't synonyms.

&amp;gt;If we do, it's unjust there as well. Can you give some specific examples?

Sure.  A thief who stole to feed his family would probably receive a lighter sentence than a thief who stole from a poor family that trusted him with their life savings.  They'd both be thieves, but one would probably receive a harsher punishment.  Attend any sentencing hearing, and you'll probably hear arguments about aggravating or mitigating circumstances.  These don't exclusively turn on the question of future harm to society (sometimes they do, but that's really difficult to prove).  Sometimes they take into account whether a defendant's conduct was "outrageous."

&amp;gt;It is still not clear to me how the motive for our action is changed by the means. We can kill a person with a gun, with an injection, with an electric chair, or with a variety of other means. Our method doesn't change our motive. 

But legal procedures aren't merely utilitarian.  They are also meant to communicate a message.  A judge can dispense verdicts without wearing a robe.  Defendants can hear a verdict just fine while slouching in a chair.  I would argue that it's the same with executions.  How we do it matters.  The chair communicates a punitive message.  Lethal injection communicates a euthanasic one.  

&amp;gt;But he's hurt me and I want revenge. 

And I think that's a fine argument to take to family court.  But it's not even remotely criminal.

&amp;gt;Maybe I won't kill him, just beat him up. You've stated that revenge is a valid justification, so would I be in the wrong if I kicked his ass because it made me feel better? 

I think a wise government realizes that feelings of vengeance are natural and rather than trying to deny it (as something only earthlings would feel), it dispenses constrained and careful vengeance in those circumstances.  

&amp;gt;Is there some scale I can use to determine what the correct amount of revenge is for an act of wrongdoing against me?

Yes, it's called the criminal code, and it's brought to you by our government.  If you think more/less revenge should be dispensed, we have a democratic process for that.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>c9xo8zm</id>
                            <replies>
<author>Amablue</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt; Well, that's frankly an impossible standard. You can't know what "future harm" someone will commit.

I'm not just referring to the person we are locking up. Locking them up acts as a deterrent to others. If we didn't punish people for breaking the law, there would be no incentive to follow it. We disincentive illegal activities by attaching a fines or jail time to them. 

Aside from that, we know that certain people are dangerous and not fit for society. These people should be removed until they can be rehabilitated. 

&amp;gt; Once Israel captured him, do you think he should have been punished? On what grounds, if not retribution for the crimes he committed?

As stated above, the reasons for punishing him are to show that his actions are not acceptable and that people who attempt to do those horrible things will face severe repercussions. 

&amp;gt; Retribution and sadism aren't synonyms.

I agree, but revenge and sadism *are*. If you can justify your punishment with something other than the desire to cause harm, then it's retribution. Causing harm *because* you want to see someone suffer isn't justice though, that is sadism, and it doesn't belong in the legal system no matter how natural or good it feels. 

&amp;gt; Sure. A thief who stole to feed his family would probably receive a lighter sentence than a thief who stole from a poor family that trusted him with their life savings. They'd both be thieves, but one would probably receive a harsher punishment.

We do not punish them differently because we want to make the victims feel better, we punish them differently because the motive of the thief makes a difference. Someone facing extreme poverty isn't stealing because he has a wanton disregard for the rights of others, he did so because he was desperate. Because of the difference in motive, different punishments should be employed. 

&amp;gt; How we do it matters. The chair communicates a punitive message. Lethal injection communicates a euthanasic one. 

The whole point of sending that message is to communicate to other people that this is what happens when you do bad things, isn't it? Then it sounds like you're arguing that we're executing people to deter others from committing crimes. 

And I disagree that lethal injection doesn't communicate a punitive message. An execution is a grim affair whether its by lethal injection or by electric chair. Only the electric chair is much more cruel. 

&amp;gt; Yes, it's called the criminal code, and it's brought to you by our government

This is just moving the goalposts. How do we as a democratic society determine what the morally correct amount of revenge? "Voting" is not an answer - I'm asking how should we determine which way to vote. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>c9xos0k</id>
<replies>
    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I'm not just referring to the person we are locking up. Locking them up acts as a deterrent to others.

I'm just not convinced deterrence is relevant when discussing the crimes under discussion here.  If someone didn't already know that raping and strangling women was wrong, I'm not sure the arrest of Gary Ridgway suddenly caused an epiphany.

&amp;gt;As stated above, the reasons for punishing him are to show that his actions are not acceptable and that people who attempt to do those horrible things will face severe repercussions. 

I'm not sure how this is distinct from revenge.  "We're retaliating because of what you did."  Perhaps you could clarify?

I'm not sure about the latter part; I doubt future potential war criminals are going reconsider genocide because of Nuremberg (or the ICC, for that matter).

&amp;gt;I agree, but revenge and sadism are. If you can justify your punishment with something other than the desire to cause harm, then it's retribution. Causing harm because you want to see someone suffer isn't justice though, that is sadism, and it doesn't belong in the legal system no matter how natural or good it feels. 

I have never argued that revenge should be the *exclusive* reason for the death penalty.  I've simply said that it's a legitimate feeling and should play a part in our moral and legal decision-making.  If nothing else, by acknowledging that the victim's family and friends want retributive satisfaction, the State can ensure some restraint in carrying out that sentence.  The problem with revenge isn't that it's unjustified; justification is part of its appeal.  The problem is that it's almost always excessive, absent the constraints law provides.

&amp;gt;We do not punish them differently because we want to make the victims feel better, we punish them differently because the motive of the thief makes a difference. Someone facing extreme poverty isn't stealing because he has a wanton disregard for the rights of others, he did so because he was desperate. Because of the difference in motive, different punishments should be employed. 

But we evaluate those motives differently in part because of outrage in the latter case and sympathy in the former.  In other words, our desire to punish "wanton disregard for the rights of others" has a retributive edge to it.  

&amp;gt;The whole point of sending that message is to communicate to other people that this is what happens when you do bad things, isn't it? Then it sounds like you're arguing that we're executing people to deter others from committing crimes. 

No, I don't think you could send that message.  The death penalty can only speak to the abhorrence with which we view the crimes actually committed.  It probably says little to nothing about future hypothetical crimes.

&amp;gt;This is just moving the goalposts. How do we as a democratic society determine what the morally correct amount of revenge? "Voting" is not an answer - I'm asking how should we determine which way to vote. 

By having discussions like this one.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>c9xpjj9</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>0</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>3</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;That said, I'm willing to accept that occasionally innocents will be executed.

I wonder if you would have that belief if you were behind bars and on death row for a murder you didn't commit.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xhkya</id>
        <replies>
            <author>GameboyPATH</author>
            <ReplyBody>...Or if OP were the spouse of a murder victim? I get that you're taking into consideration the views of innocents with wrongful convictions, but there's more than that view to consider.

Besides, [Socrates accepted his death penalty in that same situation](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crito).</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xhtf0</id>
            <replies>
                <author>BlackHumor</author>
                <ReplyBody>But he didn't accept the legitimacy of the death penalty as a method, or even the ruling of the case, just that the ruling in the case was law and as a citizen of Athens he had to accept it whether he agreed with it or not.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xpyf6</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>GameboyPATH</author>
                    <ReplyBody>I probably should have clarified it more. I just meant to say that a person's perspective of whether a law is justified or not may not always reflect the person's status as the convicted party. Bigbuddhabelly's implication that a convicted person would feel negatively toward a death penalty isn't necessarily true.

It's not the strongest connection, I know.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>c9xqk7p</id>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't relish it or think we should try to increase these cases.  It's merely a concession to reality.  Do you think the police should be disarmed, because occasionally innocents are shot?  Do you think we should surrender in every war, because innocents might be killed?  What exactly is your point?</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xhx8c</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; What exactly is your point?

My point is its called the JUSTICE SYSTEM. There is no justice in killing innocents because we might also kill criminals in the process.

Look at the middle east. Those small villages we destroy with drone strikes, they just create more anti-american hate because they see themselves as victims of american military might.

Then when Islamists show up and preach about how America seeks the destruction of the middle east, those orphans who lost their parents to the drone strikes sit and listen. 

My point is theres a right way and a wrong way.

What you are talking about is the equivalent of turning our justice system into chemotherapy.

Yeah we might kill a few healthy cells but at least the cancer dies.

The problem is this cancer doesn't spread, if we have them in prison then its isolated.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xi1l8</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                    <ReplyBody>You danced around the other questions I posed.  How far are you willing to take this rejection of the doctrine of double effect?  Would you disarm the police?  Would you surrender in every war?</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>c9xi74i</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>[deleted]</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Theres no need to disarm the cops, you instead punish the shitty ones who go around shooting unarmed people.

Theres no need to surrender in war when you are actually fighting a war. No chasing people with no uniforms through the deserts of Afghanistan. 

Real wars do not deal out numbers like this. Since we have been in Iraq more than a million people have died, if we were trying to save people we failed miserably.

</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>c9xig3j</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                            <ReplyBody>Even with the best police and military in the world, it's foreseeable that innocents will sometimes be killed.  You can still defend these institutions as legitimate.  That's the doctrine of double effect.  Do you agree with that or not?</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>c9xijxu</id>
                            <replies>
<author>[deleted]</author>
<ReplyBody>I agree with justice, I don't agree with killing innocent people in the pursuit of justice. 

Thats not how criminal justice works. </ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>c9xim0o</id>
<replies>
    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
    <ReplyBody>Then you'd disarm the police, because occasionally even well-trained officers accidentally kill innocent people.  And you'd surrender to every enemy, because in every war, civilians are sometimes killed, even when disciplined soldiers try to avoid it.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>c9xizxm</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <replies>
<author>herrokan</author>
<ReplyBody>but how many people are potentially saved by police having guns? then look at your example and tell me, how many people are saved by killing people with an electric chair, compared to just putting them into prison?</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>c9xjozz</id>
<replies>
    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;but how many people are potentially saved by police having guns?

I have no idea.  A non-trivial number of police shootings every year involve officers accidentally shooting themselves.  I actually think there's a stronger argument for disarming the police than abolishing the death penalty (for one thing, the latter case offers a trial).  But if you've noticed, I have never justified the death penalty on deterrence grounds, because the argument there is frankly too muddled either way.  It's an impossible question to resolve.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>c9xn0ck</id>
    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>3</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>GameboyPATH</author>
        <ReplyBody>The argument I've always made against the death penalty is the pragmatic argument: [it's far too costly](http://www.deathpenaltyinfo.org/costs-death-penalty). A lot more legal proceedings are involved for criminals facing the death penalty than for those facing a life sentence, and those trials require a ton of money.

Is it worth 3-4 times the cost of a life sentence just to zap a guy?

Edit: [more argument-oriented evidence](http://www.deathpenalty.org/article.php?id=42) on the cost of the death penalty</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xhzvt</id>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>I don't particularly care about cost.  The criminal justice system shouldn't be run like a fried chicken restaurant, and a capital case deserves exhaustive appeal.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xi60n</id>
            <replies>
                <author>GameboyPATH</author>
                <ReplyBody>I think it's something worth caring about. A country or state only has a finite number of resources. Is it worth financially draining an economy, thus compromising the quality of life for *all* citizens (especially the innocent ones!) for the sake of frying a guy? There's many good causes that could use that money: why is the task of bringing a small number of people's life counters lower the more important cause?

Let's look at it from a existential perspective, then. We all die eventually. Whether or not a prisoner is sentenced to death after a few years of prolonged court trials or after a lifetime in some god-awful prison, that prisoner will die. What makes bringing that death date closer worthwhile?

Even better, let's look at it from the perspective of justice, assuming that you want the electric chair to be proper punishment for that person's crimes. Is termination of life really suitable revenge? Why isn't a life sentence proper revenge? It'd not only be an environment that requires and facilitates the deprivation of freedoms that one once had, but it'd be prolonged.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xijog</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I think it's something worth caring about. A country or state only has a finite number of resources. Is it worth financially draining an economy, thus compromising the quality of life for all citizens (especially the innocent ones!) for the sake of frying a guy? There's many good causes that could use that money: why is the task of bringing a small number of people's life counters lower the more important cause?

I'm not convinced that death penalty appeals are bankrupting the country, or that they merit anywhere near this level of hilarious panic (your argument could be applied to spending on virtually anything).  If you want to cut government waste, there are plenty of other places to look besides ensuring fair trials.  I'm not comfortable with throwing people in prison for life *just to save money.*

&amp;gt;Let's look at it from a existential perspective, then. We all die eventually. Whether or not a prisoner is sentenced to death after a few years of prolonged court trials or after a lifetime in some god-awful prison, that prisoner will die. What makes bringing that death date closer worthwhile?

This is also a justification for murder.  The victim was going to die anyway.  What makes bringing that death date closer so awful?

&amp;gt;Even better, let's look at it from the perspective of justice, assuming that you want the electric chair to be proper punishment for that person's crimes. Is termination of life really suitable revenge? Why isn't a life sentence proper revenge? It'd not only be an environment that requires and facilitates the deprivation of freedoms that one once had, but it'd be prolonged.

Because the murderer still has a life, and the victim doesn't.  Because the murderer will still be able to smile, and laugh, and dream, and even cry, and the victim won't.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>c9xis4g</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>GameboyPATH</author>
                        <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;I'm not convinced that death penalty appeals are bankrupting the country, or that they merit anywhere near this level of hilarious panic (your argument could be applied to spending on virtually anything). If you want to cut government waste, there are plenty of other places to look besides ensuring fair trials. I'm not comfortable with throwing people in prison for life just to save money.

Am I right in assuming we're talking about the U.S. here? We're already having significant financial troubles, and *need* to cut back where we can. While politicians and economists argue over what exactly the downside is to excessive government spending, it's agreed that it's not good for anyone.

Yes, this argument can certainly be applied to a lot of government actions that require billions of dollars. But unlike government funding to, for example, keep public facilities operating, support seniors, or back up national defense, the goal of killing a very small number of people is hardly worth spending billions of dollars. It's cost-benefit analysis: is killing a very small number of guys worth the economic cost?

That said, your other points are actually well-argued. I hadn't read your comment about Leopold until afterward, and it's not a bad point. You live up to your title.</ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>c9xon3h</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Am I right in assuming we're talking about the U.S. here? We're already having significant financial troubles, and need to cut back where we can. While politicians and economists argue over what exactly the downside is to excessive government spending, it's agreed that it's not good for anyone.

Our financial problems come more from bailing out Wall Street, not from spending money on essential public services like fair courts.  And I'm not convinced that austerity's necessarily been a good response to the financial crisis.  

&amp;gt;Yes, this argument can certainly be applied to a lot of government actions that require billions of dollars. But unlike government funding to, for example, keep public facilities operating, support seniors, or back up national defense, the goal of killing a very small number of people is hardly worth spending billions of dollars. It's cost-benefit analysis: is killing a very small number of guys worth the economic cost?

Except that those costs come from the appeals process, not from the execution itself.  And those are costs that should be paid in life imprisonment cases too.  It's abhorrent that an innocent person should suffer for any crime.

&amp;gt;That said, your other points are actually well-argued. I hadn't read your comment about Leopold until afterward, and it's not a bad point. You live up to your title.

Thanks, that's very kind of you to say.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>c9xp3ug</id>
                            <replies>
<author>GameboyPATH</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Our financial problems come more from bailing out Wall Street, not from spending money on essential public services like fair courts. And I'm not convinced that austerity's necessarily been a good response to the financial crisis.

Perhaps, but my larger point is just that unnecessary programs that take billions of government dollars harm society. Even if the billions of dollars spent on legal proceedings for the death penalty is negligible (which seems to be what you're suggesting), when we consider the subject of whether or not to have the death penalty from a cost-benefit perspective (loss of government money negatively affecting economy vs. "justice" to an incredibly small number of people), enforcing the death penalty is just not worth doing.

Granted, as you've suggested, cost-benefit analysis may not be the most appropriate perspective to take on the administering of justice, but it's not an unimportant one.

&amp;gt;Except that those costs come from the appeals process, not from the execution itself. And those are costs that should be paid in life imprisonment cases too.

Ah, but it isn't. That cost is not nearly as great for life sentences. [This source](http://www.deathpenalty.org/article.php?id=42), while biased, gives some estimates of amounts saved in legal proceedings if governments enforced life without parole rather than corporal punishment.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>c9xpg0c</id>
<replies>
    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
    <ReplyBody>Correct me if I'm wrong, but the costs all come down to special procedural safeguards a death penalty trial requires, right?  I haven't seen a single one listed that I don't think should *also* feature in a trial for life imprisonment.  If anything, the increased rigor of death penalty trials might be an argument in their favor.  I wish life imprisonment trials were taken as seriously.</ReplyBody>
    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
    <id>c9xq7cg</id>
    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
</replies>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>2</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>2</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>2</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>Quetzalcoatls</author>
        <ReplyBody>IIRC the electric chair isn't even an effective means of execution. If you want to be sure they are going to die then there are much better executions methods to use.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xhvur</id>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>Absent more than your tenuous recollection, I'm not exactly persuaded.  Sorry.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xi66u</id>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>[deleted]</author>
        <ReplyBody>In order to hold this position you must admit that there is something inherently good about the infliction of pain for pain's sake. Most people hold the position that pain is only viable as a means to a greater end. But in your situation the electric chair is clearly causing more pain than is necessary for no other reason than to cause pain. This is called retributive justice, and I don't think it's a morally defensible position.

&amp;gt;  the State is taking revenge.

The state is not taking revenge, it's removing someone who obviously cannot function in a modern society. And it's also enacting the death penalty as a means of deterrence to observers (although most studies show the deterrence effect is insignificant with the death penalty). Our justice system does not cause harm just for the sake of harm.</ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xlqcw</id>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;In order to hold this position you must admit that there is something inherently good about the infliction of pain for pain's sake. Most people hold the position that pain is only viable as a means to a greater end. But in your situation the electric chair is clearly causing more pain than is necessary for no other reason than to cause pain. This is called retributive justice, and I don't think it's a morally defensible position.

I'm not advocating torture.  I'm merely disputing that "no cruel and unusual punishment" means "the most comfortable means possible."  Executions should be staged with great dramatic moral force.  They should make it absolutely clear that the State, after careful reflection, has deliberately decided to exact the ultimate penalty.  Timothy McVeigh called his lethal injection "state-assisted suicide."  He had a point.  Euthanasia isn't the same thing as execution.

&amp;gt;This is called retributive justice, and I don't think it's a morally defensible position.

Well, thank you, Pope Francis.  I think retributive justice has a legitimate moral purpose, if only to prevent vigilante killing (as happens to some lifers in prison).  I'm much more comfortable with the State sending Ted Bundy to the chair than I am with Jeffrey Dahmer being bludgeoned to death by another murderer.

&amp;gt;The state is not taking revenge, it's removing someone who obviously cannot function in a modern society.

That's purpose of an insane asylum, not a prison

&amp;gt;And it's also enacting the death penalty as a means of deterrence to observers (although most studies show the deterrence effect is insignificant with the death penalty). 

I've never argued the deterrence point; it seems to me a wash either way.  Not convinced either side could prove their case on that point.

&amp;gt;Our justice system does not cause harm just for the sake of harm.

Nobody's arguing this.</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xn8y9</id>
            <replies>
                <author>[deleted]</author>
                <ReplyBody>&amp;gt; I'm not advocating torture. I'm merely disputing that "no cruel and unusual punishment" means "the most comfortable means possible."

Yes you are. If you are inflicting pain as an end in itself rather than as a mean than it is wanton torture.

&amp;gt; Well, thank you, Pope Francis.

There's no need to resort to off-base ad hominem.

&amp;gt; I think retributive justice has a legitimate moral purpose, if only to prevent vigilante killing (as happens to some lifers in prison). I'm much more comfortable with the State sending Ted Bundy to the chair than I am with Jeffrey Dahmer being bludgeoned to death by another murderer.

So we should brutally murder people by strapping them to a chair and electrocuting them just to make sure they don't get brutally murdered by someone else in jail? This would make a little more sense if you weren't advocating such a barbaric method like the electric chair. But even then, you seem to be in favor of a lengthy appeals process which puts those on death row in prison where they can be vigilante murdered anyways. Finally, retributive justice means punishing because that person deserves punishment. As soon you add another reason it's no longer retributive justice.

&amp;gt; That's purpose of an insane asylum, not a prison.

More than one thing can serve the same purpose. Reminding me that asylums exist doesn't change the function of the death penalty. It's simply a cheaper way of removing those who can't function properly.

&amp;gt; I've never argued the deterrence point; it seems to me a wash either way. Not convinced either side could prove their case on that point.

Of course they can, it's relatively straight forward to show the effect of increased/harsher punishment on crime rates, there just isn't much of an effect for the death penalty. Obviously the justice system as a whole serves a deterrent effect.

&amp;gt; Nobody's arguing this.

What? That's your whole argument, that we should resort to more brutal and ancient methods of controlled murder in order to exact revenge. Revenge and causing harm for the sake of harm are the same thing.</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xofm5</id>
                <upvotes>1</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
    <redditComments>
        <author>jerry121212</author>
        <ReplyBody>Why would killing someone be better than say, keeping them in solitary confinement? </ReplyBody>
        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
        <id>c9xjsly</id>
        <replies>
            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
            <ReplyBody>Because a murderer shouldn't enjoy the life he took from his victim(s).</ReplyBody>
            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
            <id>c9xn27n</id>
            <replies>
                <author>jerry121212</author>
                <ReplyBody>Nobody enjoys their life in solitary confinement. Either way, I think it's detrimental for our society to have such a vengeful view. We should encourage second chances, forgiven people etc. I know, I know, killing is a horrible thing, but why exactly should we kill these people besides the fact that we're angry at them? Does it help anybody? Does it make the person dying somehow more ok? No, it's just killing because we're upset, and that's not how we should treat killing someone. How much more moral is it to execute someone out of spite or anger or revenge than to murder someone for the same reasons?</ReplyBody>
                <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                <id>c9xoh1h</id>
                <replies>
                    <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                    <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Nobody enjoys their life in solitary confinement.

The murderer in solitary confinement might have one happy day.  Might have a day when the food tastes better than usual, or their cot feels a little more comfortable.  Might have a day when sunlight throngs the glass or the sound of rain stirs up memories of schooldays.  Not much in a long wasteland of years, I'll grant, but one more than the victim will ever get.

&amp;gt;Either way, I think it's detrimental for our society to have such a vengeful view. We should encourage second chances, forgiven people etc. I know, I know, killing is a horrible thing, but why exactly should we kill these people besides the fact that we're angry at them?

Because they took something irreplaceable.  Because their victims never get a second chance at anything.  Because only killing them is commensurate with the horror of the crime.

&amp;gt;How much more moral is it to execute someone out of spite or anger or revenge than to murder someone for the same reasons?

I'm sorry, at what point did the victim do anything to deserve murder?  At what point did the victim receive a trial?  Or an appeals process?  No, I can't accept this lazy analogy between one selfish person's decision to kill, and the State's retaliation for that act.  It's a moral equivalence too far.</ReplyBody>
                    <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                    <id>c9xoqkf</id>
                    <replies>
                        <author>jerry121212</author>
                        <ReplyBody>Every point your making is assuming that people think in a really vengeful way. 

"Not much in a long wasteland of years, I'll grant, but one more than the victim will ever get."

This assumes the victim would honestly want their murdered to never be happy again. If I was murdered, I would want the guy to change. To make up for it.  

"Because only killing them is commensurate with the horror of the crime."

This is just a harmful way to go about life. To try to get everyone to commensurate rather than learn to be better. This is why people think hitting their children is okay, this is why drunk people get in bar fights. Nobody wins. It all boils down to...

"He did something bad, now I want bad things to happen to him"

It's god damn childish. I'm sorry, but as a species, this is not how we move forward. </ReplyBody>
                        <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                        <id>c9xp9ea</id>
                        <replies>
                            <author>excellentwordsmith</author>
                            <ReplyBody>&amp;gt;Every point your making is assuming that people think in a really vengeful way. 

It's assuming that vengeance has a role in determining an appropriate penalty, sure.

&amp;gt;This assumes the victim would honestly want their murdered to never be happy again. If I was murdered, I would want the guy to change. To make up for it. 

It assumes nothing about what the victim wants.  It merely states the cold fact that a murderer took something the victim can never have, and that even a life in solitary confinement preserves exactly what the murder victim doesn't have--life.

That said, I have no objections to potential murder victims filing notarized statements requesting their potential murderers not be executed.

&amp;gt;This is just a harmful way to go about life. To try to get everyone to commensurate rather than learn to be better. This is why people think hitting their children is okay, this is why drunk people get in bar fights. Nobody wins. It all boils down to...

No, I think a penalty should take into account exactly what the victim lost.  And especially if, like me, you have no hope of an afterlife, then it's clear the murder victim has lost *everything.*  

This has nothing to do with drunken barfights or spanking brats.  Frankly, I'm appalled you'd trivialize the grief and rage bereaved families feel like that.

&amp;gt;It's god damn childish. I'm sorry, but as a species, this is not how we move forward. 

15-year-old Charles Otero came home from school to find his father and mother bound, gagged, and suffocated with plastic bags over their heads. He found his baby brother in another room, also bound, gagged, and with three hoods over his head.  He found his sister Josephine, all of 11 years old, partially nude and hanging from a drainpipe.  

The killer wrote letters to the police, graphically describing his crimes.  Here's one excerpt: " I was go-ng to tape the boys and put plastics bag over there head like I did Joseph, and Shirley. And then hang the girl. God-oh God what a beautiful sexual relief that would been. Josephine,when I hung her really turn me on; her pleading for mercy then the rope took whole, she helpless; staring at me with wide terror fill eyes the rope getting tighter-tighter."

Three decades later, after killing more people and sending more letters, Dennis Rader was caught and convicted.  

Charles Otero, now grown up, has stated that Mr. Rader should "get a little room on death row."  You may think that's "childish" of him and holding up the progress of the species, but I'm inclined to forgive Mr. Otero for being human.

Dennis Rader received life without parole.</ReplyBody>
                            <downvotes>0</downvotes>
                            <id>c9xq1qr</id>
                            <replies>
<author>jerry121212</author>
<ReplyBody>&amp;gt;It's assuming that vengeance has a role in determining an appropriate penalty, sure.


What else would be playing a role if we're killing the guy? 

'he killed him, he should be killed'

'he did x, we should do x to him'

That's what revenge is.



&amp;gt;No, I think a penalty should take into account exactly what the victim lost.


'take into account' doesn't mean recreate unto the offender. 

&amp;gt;I'm appalled you'd trivialize the grief and rage bereaved families feel like that.

I wasn't equating murder to a bar fight. I'm saying the thought process of 'kill this guy because he killed someone' is the same thought process that causes bar fights. (He shoved me, I'll shove him back.)

&amp;gt;It assumes nothing about what the victim wants....That said, I have no objections to potential murder victims filing notarized statements requesting their potential murderers not be executed.

What I meant by "it assumes the victim wants.." was, the reason you're giving for killing people isn't something objectively helpful. It's a personal thing. It's what you think is fair. Fair for who? I guess the victim right? They're the one who lost something, so the point of taking that thing from the killer would be to pacify the victim, or at least to pacify someone. Since no one is practically benefiting from the killer dying, they're dying so other people can feel justice has been served. So saying we should kill the killer, assumes that people think 'justice' means taken what they took from the victim (aka revenge). I'm telling you, a lot of people don't find comfort in revenge of giving people a taste of their own medicine.

&amp;gt;15-year-old Charles Otero came home from school to find his...

You're really gonna use this example to try and say *all* murderers deserve to die? Sure, this guy isn't going to redeem himself, but this is probably less than half a percent of how all murders actually happen.</ReplyBody>
<downvotes>0</downvotes>
<id>c9xqfjk</id>
<upvotes>1</upvotes>
                            </replies>
                            <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                        </replies>
                        <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                    </replies>
                    <upvotes>1</upvotes>
                </replies>
                <upvotes>0</upvotes>
            </replies>
            <upvotes>2</upvotes>
        </replies>
        <upvotes>0</upvotes>
    </redditComments>
</redditSubmission>
